The Further Adventures of Valencia the Red

Horus had always thought that the big, cleaving line that separated all things was between the planned and unplanned. The city of Orrangush was a mix of the two, with grand, sweeping avenues and square plazas, and between them, where bigger buildings hadn’t gobbled up space during city-wide redesigns and writs of eminent domain, there were the unplanned spaces, little shops and houses that followed the old, wandering roads from before the city had been remade. Horus loved the unplanned spaces, the way you could see them twisted and bent, a hundred hands sculpting them across time. The real treasures and delights were always in the crooked places, where every window had to be custom fit and wood was given a patina of oils from use. Beyond that, those were the only places that sold the sorts of things that Horus could afford.

The sweets shop seemed to come from nowhere, installing itself in an empty storefront overnight. Horus didn’t have the whole of Orrangush memorized, because if that had ever happened, he probably would have left for a newer, more exciting place, but he walked the particular road the sweets shop had sprouted up on often enough to know that the shop had come into existence within twelve hours, maybe less, without so much as a ‘Coming Soon!’ sign.

It was impossible to miss, even if you didn’t pay attention to stores and houses as a matter of habit. It shone with warm lights, the same electricity that everyone else used, but somehow crafted in such a way that it felt like a grandmother’s kitchen, or sunlight coming down on a clearing, or the warmth of a fire when you’d been doing hard work outside in the wintertime. The store smelled, too, of spices and sweets, strong enough that the scent would spill out onto the streets, and when the glass door opened and closed, the rush of air would bathe the street with more scents of exotic candy.

There were planned stores and unplanned stores, and Horus vastly preferred the latter. Some stores had been constructed with a place for everything and everything in its place, goods segregated out and carefully labeled. Other stores grew without a plan, or with a plan so far in the past that it was no more than a vague imprint left on the store’s present organization. Being unplanned wasn’t the same as being disorganized, though there was some natural overlap. A properly unplanned store responded to its customers, allowing their needs to dictate what went where, until eventually the goods would move around the various cupboards, shelves, and tables, like a garden of commerce growing wild.

The sweets shop was an unplanned store, though artfully and deliberately so. There were dozens of bins lined up, but they followed a curve in the wall, squeezing in places where they would fit. There were jars filled with candy too, sitting on tables together to make displays full of color, with small, empty bags stacked here and there so patrons could pick out what they liked. There were twirls of red and white, marble-like yellow candies, chocolates covered in multicolor candy shells, sweets like red twisted rope, and all manner of others, so many that it would have made you sick to try them all. One of the two women who ran the place was always behind the main counter, which had clearly been made from a huge old door laid on its side, one large enough that it could span half of the sweets shop’s small space with ease. If Horus hadn’t already been in love with the place, that door, haphazardly cut through and turned into a counter, would have sent him over the edge into adoration.

Horus went into the sweets shop only during off-hours, when the hordes of children that visited the place weren’t there, when there was no rush of people coming by after their lunch, when it was nice and quiet, with only one or two other people, or as was his preference, no one but himself and one of the two owners.

The two women who worked the sweets shop were odd ones. Horus had always felt that there were planned and unplanned people. When he tried to explain the concept, sometimes whomever had deigned to listen to him would get confused, or try to narrow things down. They would think that a planned person was someone like a princess, born into her role and trained from birth with exacting precision, and an unplanned person was someone like a bastard or a whoreson, born into the world with no place made ready for them. This was correct, insofar as Horus saw it, but it was a matter of extremes. A baker’s son could be a planned person, and a maid could be an unplanned person, it wasn’t really a matter of profession or birth, more about how they went through life, and how or whether they allowed life to shape them. Both the women who worked the sweets shop were unplanned people, to a degree that Horus had never seen before.

The shorter woman, with her kind and exotic purple eyes and tight-laced dresses, was always the more friendly of the two, without fail. She had a bright, effortless smile, no matter the time of day, and she would speak enthusiastically to anyone who seemed like they were remotely interested. If given the chance, she would talk at length about any of their candies, sometimes spinning a story that clearly had no basis in reality.

“These are Gibraltars,” said the shorter woman with a smile as she stood next to a cluster of children. Horus looked over, and saw her holding a small yellow candy between her thumb and forefinger. “They’re named after the Rock of Gibraltar, quite some distance away from here, not because they’re hard like a rock, though they are, but because there was a famous battle there, right around the time this candy was first created.”

The children looked up at her in awe.

“Now, these are a trif a piece,” said the black-haired woman, holding the candy forth and casting a critical eye on it, “But for children under eight, we offer testers, just so you can know whether or not you like them.” She reached into the jar beside her and pulled out a small handful of lemon drops, exactly enough so that each of the children could have one, without making a show of it. The one she’d been holding, she popped into her mouth.

One of the children held back, looking uncomfortable. He was the last to be offered a lemon drop, and when he didn’t go for it, the woman stooped slightly, getting on his level.

“You don’t fancy a Gibraltar?” she asked.

“I’m nine,” he said.

It took her a moment, but finally understanding dawned on her. “Oh,” she said, closing her hand around the lemon drop. “By what accounting?”

“Accounting?” asked the boy.

“When do you count from?” she asked. “From before you were born, from the day you were born, or sometime after?”

“Oh,” he said. “When I was born, I guess. My birthday.”

“It’s different in different parts of the world,” said the woman, nodding. “In Korea, everyone’s age is one the moment they’re born, and when the new year comes, everyone’s age goes up, all on the same day.” She took in his disbelieving look. “Oh, it’s true enough, different people with different customs. There are dragons that count from the day their egg was laid. But more important for you, in this store we use the Acrian system of accounting, from the second year after you’re born.” She held out the candy again. “By our way of thinking, you would still be seven.”

The boy looked at her like he was deciding whether or not to believe it, then snatched up the candy before she changed her mind.

Horus watched all of this while pretending to contemplate an enormous jar of something labeled ‘silver dragees’. When the children had all left, free candy in their mouths, the woman approached him.

“It’s not true, of course,” she said. “But I can’t resist the little ones.”

“I didn’t mean to eavesdrop,” said Horus.

“Oh, sure you did,” she replied with a smile. She held out her hand. “Rossa the Strong.”

“Horus Acreh,” he replied, shaking her small hand. “Did you say, ‘the Strong’?”

“It’s an appellation of my own design,” she replied with a smile. “I thought, if I was going to be called something, why not pick strong?” She shrugged. “It’s aspirational.” She looked over to the side and took the lid off a jar. “Would you like an Everlasting Gobstopper? As a tester, naturally.”

“Oh,” said Horus. “Sure.” He took one and put it in his cheek. She’d been sucking on her lemon drop, talking around it, and now they had matching speech impediments. It was only once it was in his mouth that he thought to point out that he wasn’t under eight, in what might have been a joking way, but by then it was too late, and it would have been awkward.

“This is your thirteenth time coming to the shop,” said Rossa. “I was curious whether you were maybe here for more than just sweets?”

“I — I uh,” he said slowly. “I don’t know what you mean by that.”

“You like this place,” said Rossa, nodding. She moved the candy around in her mouth, and it clacked against her teeth. “Maybe you come here because it gives you a feeling that you don’t have anywhere else?”

“Maybe,” he said, swallowing lemon-flavored saliva. “It’s a nice place.”

“It’s warm, inviting, it’s got a good mix of smells,” said Rossa, nodding. “It feels lived-in, even though we both know that’s not really true, because we’ve only been here a week. But we don’t really sell that, do we?” she asked. “We don’t sell a mood.”

“I’m — I’m sorry,” said Horus. “I didn’t think — I didn’t want to bother either of you. I can buy more.”

“Oh!” said Rossa, looking taken aback. “Oh, it’s no bother, we’re happy to have you, whether as a customer or if you’re only looking, I’m only saying that the thing you’re seeking isn’t something that can be found here, and I want you to find the thing you’re looking for. I think that would be nice for you.”

“Oh,” said Horus. “And … what am I looking for?”

“A mood,” said Rossa. “Soft familiarity, a kinship worn by time, proof of the labors of love.” She shrugged. “Something like that.”

“And — and where could I find a thing like that?” he asked.

“That’s hard enough, in this world,” Rossa replied with a sigh. Her teeth came down and crunched on the lemon drop as she gave him a thoughtful look. “The modern world can seem cold and distant at the best of times, and these aren’t the best of times. I think the answer is that you have to either inherit it or build it up, if you don’t just stumble into it on accident.” She continued her thoughtful look, then went over to the big counter made out of a door and grabbed a pen and a piece of paper. “I know some people that might be able to help you. Can I write down some names for you?”

“Uh, sure,” said Horus. The woman, Rossa, began writing on a piece of paper very quickly. “I’m sorry, how long have you been in Orrangush?”

“This would be day number eight,” she replied. She lifted up the paper and took a moment to look at it, then handed it to Horus. “The first name and address is for a woman, older, looking for an apprentice. She does glassblowing and could use someone with strong lungs. The reason I put her down there is that I think you would like her workshop. The second and third names are a young woman and her father. She’s lodona, from a big family, and she’s been refusing the matchmaking that he’s been trying to set up for her. I don’t know for certain whether she’ll take to you, or you to her, but I think it would probably be worth your time.”

“I don’t — I’m not,” said Horus.

“Yes, you are,” said Rossa, nodding slightly. “The fourth name belongs to a tour company local to Orrangush, which I think you’d be suited for, though I’m not sure that it would get to the base of your needs. And then the fifth there isn’t a name, but a number, just tell them that Rossa the Strong said you should call. The man at the other end is the next kingdom over, but he owes me a favor, and he’s good at placing people.”

“Placing people?” asked Horus.

But then the door to the sweets shop opened, and the bell rang as a pair of teenagers came in. Rossa left him standing there, holding a sheet of paper with names, addresses, and numbers on it. Horus had questions, that was only natural, but he was feeling strange, off-balance, like he was walking through a dream. He had never spoken more than a few words when he was in the sweets shop, except to say what he was buying, or the usual pleasantries, and here they’d had a whole conversation, all at once, one that had cleaved him down to his core.

Rossa gave him a small nod and a smile as he left, one which he felt too unsteady to return. She’d said that it was his thirteenth time, and it only hit him once he was out of the store that by rights, she should have had no way to remember that, not with how many people came and went.

Horus looked down at the list he’d been given. There were opportunities there, possibilities, all crafted specifically for him. He had never really thought that anything might happen between him and the woman who ran the sweets shop, but there was something bitter about being told so plainly that he should go find another woman, one who was in the middle of matchmaking.

Yet that seemed to be where his feet were taking him anyway. He decided that he would talk to the woman and her father, just to see what they had to say.

“That man, Horus. Which of those was the real one?” asked Bethel, once the day was done. She was being good, and keeping up with her appearance, even when they were alone. Nephthys, she was called, in this time and place.

“They were all real,” said Valencia as she took off her apron. “The one I thought he would pick was the marriage prospect. The number was … not fake, but a long shot, and he might have been turned down.”

“And was there manipulation on your part?” asked Bethel.

“There’s always manipulation,” Valencia replied. “When you’re in a position of power over someone else, I think it’s inescapable that your actions are tainted by that power. The best you can do is to pretend that power doesn’t exist, and to hope that they trust you enough to do the same, because then things can proceed as they normally would. But in a case like this, where I had information that I was trying to get across, and I knew that man well enough from having seen him and looked him over, there was undeniably some element of unsavory power difference between us. I’d never claim otherwise.”

“You think it’s moral,” said Bethel. “You were giving him a choice, knowing what that choice was likely to be, but you had his best interests at heart.”

“Hrm,” said Valencia, pretending to think. “I think that to live in this world as powerful entities, we have to shoulder the burden of our power. It’s something that I try to keep in mind.”

“You don’t think that we should be out there, in the world, doing more?” asked Bethel. “More than pointing lonely men in the direction of receptive mates, or giving away candies to children?”

“I think we need to straighten things out between ourselves,” said Valencia. “I think that we need to know how to be better people. There’s a cost to doing what we’re doing now, a large one, but for the moment I think that it’s a cost that’s worth paying.”

“We could control this entire city,” said Bethel. “We could feed every hungry child. You give away candy to those children? Surely you noticed the malnutrition of the youngest two, the shabby clothes, if not the marks of trauma those clothes hide?”

“I noticed,” replied Valencia. She was aware that her voice was tight, but there was no need to control that, to hide the emotion that she felt. “There’s certainly a temptation to barge in, to give them full meals, magical healing, a better life than the one they currently have.”

“And the reason that we don’t, the reason that those children get small kindnesses instead of large ones, is that you worry that it would spiral out of control in some way, or lead to unintended consequences, or that we would have our paper thin cover blown and be forced to relocate.” Bethel had on a rather cruel smile. “Boo hoo.”

“We’re here to talk and understand,” said Valencia. She kept her voice level, though she’d been trying to do that less these days, because Bethel took pleasure in getting a rise out of people, and if the tone was too level, she would seek to provoke emotion. It was a careful balancing act. “We’re not here to help the needy, we’re not here to right wrongs, and we’re not here to upset every apple cart we think might be in need of upsetting. Once we’re finished … maybe. Right now, I want to focus on restraint, and on being the sort of person who doesn’t approach every problem with maximum force.” These were old conversations, retreads, but retreading was good, because it helped to wear in grooves.

Bethel moved to the window and drew back the curtain to look outside. The shop had short hours, which left plenty of time for observation and discussion. They couldn’t spend the entirety of every day doing therapy, even with Valencia speeding through sleep with the time chamber, but they were packing the hours full of conversation. What Bethel was getting up to during that downtime was of concern, but thus far, she’d appeared to be forthright about her activities, even if they were skirting (or outright breaking) the boundaries they’d set up.

“Alright,” said Valencia. “You think that we should be doing more here.”

Bethel turned back to her with a piercing gaze. It was the same mask as always, only showing what she chose to show. That wasn’t because Bethel was particularly guarded, though she was, it was just the nature of her existence. Bethel had nothing like the physiological connections that other people had, linking up her emotions with her outward appearance, so she was left to project, always consciously so. “I do,” Bethel finally said.

“Because you honestly want to help people?” asked Valencia. “Or because you think that’s a tactic that I might be sympathetic to?”

“Can’t it be both?” asked Bethel.

“Do you actually want to do good?” asked Valencia. “When you see someone in pain, do you want to lessen that pain?”

“Depends on the person,” replied Bethel, frowning. “Are you actually asking me that? Don’t you know by now?”

Valencia paused as her model of Bethel was rapidly updated and chains of logic clinked against each other. “How much do you think I know?” she asked.

“Well, everything, I suppose,” said Bethel. “I’ve made no attempts to hide anything from you. I’ve been forthright in everything I’ve told you. I really, honestly do want to make things go back to the way that they were, and if you have an infernally assisted plan, then that’s a path that I’ll willingly walk. When we go back, it will be with your clearance. You’ll assure the others that I’ve changed. I’ll be their house again.”

“It’s not going to be that easy,” said Valencia. “I can’t in good conscience allow you to believe that’s how it will be. Juniper won’t want to live in you for quite some time, even with my assurance, even with my explanation of what we’ve been doing and what we’ve learned here. What we’re doing are steps toward becoming better, on an absurdly accelerated timescale, with, yes, the end goal being a reintroduction to the party, capable of honestly addressing their concerns and ensuring that nothing bad happens between us and them again.”

“Much more a concern for me than for you,” said Bethel. “Juniper holds affection for you.”

“He’s guarded around me, and rightfully so,” said Valencia. She waved a hand. “It’s not about him, it’s about us, and our relationship with the world. So tell me, if you value good for its own sake, what does good look like to you?”

“What do you mean?” asked Bethel. The tone of her voice made it sound as though she suspected that this was a trick. It was a trick, but not in the usual sense, since Valencia only planned to use some framing and follow-up questions that would (ideally) help with the process of reframing how Bethel looked at the world.

“Imagine that you died tomorrow, and in your final moments, the Dungeon Master came to you and said that you could make any changes you wanted to the world,” said Valencia. “You would have no limits whatsoever and no worries about time, just carte blanche to alter the world. What would you do? You can take your time to think.”

“And what would you do?” asked Bethel.

“I don’t want to poison the well with my answer,” replied Valencia. “If you’d like, I can share my thoughts once you’re done. Again, it’s fine to think about it first. I would prefer that you think out loud though, because I’m more interested in your thoughts than your answer.”

“I think you want me to say all the obvious,” said Bethel. “No pain, no terror, nothing forced on anyone, a happy world where every day is better than the last and nothing negative happens to anyone at all.”

“But that’s not what you actually think?” asked Valencia.

“For a very long time, the best moments of my life were when I was enacting justice,” said Bethel. There was a challenge in her voice, daring Valencia to object.

“You mean that you slaughtered anyone who came inside you,” said Valencia.

“No, not just people who came inside me,” replied Bethel. “People outside too, those who came too close, or people who I took a disliking to for whatever reason. You haven’t mentioned the torture, but you don’t need to pussyfoot around it, because when I say justice, I mean that too. In a world without pain or terror, there would be no badness, but with no badness, there would be nothing to bring justice against. It would simply be gone, replaced by nothing.”

“You yearn to right perceived wrongs,” said Valencia. “In this perfect world, do you think there would be nothing to replace that yearning? Nothing to replace the warm feeling of satisfaction when you’ve dealt out perceived justice?”

“You said that I would be dead, not able to live in the world I had created,” said Bethel. “So I suppose the question is whether I value justice, in the abstract, for its own sake, or whether it’s simply because justice makes me feel good. I’m not sure that I know. I would be depriving others, but not myself.” She frowned. “You are very good at interesting questions.”

“The point isn’t to be interesting,” said Valencia. “I’m trying to provide some conceptual handles on different emotions, lenses and ways of thinking that will help you. You get some thrill from righting wrongs, which might be motivated by moral considerations, but is also simply satisfying as a process of exercised control over the world.”

“Thrill sounds cheap,” said Bethel, not objecting. “And do you really think that it’s simply about control?”

“Control might be the wrong word,” said Valencia. “In truth, it’s more complicated than that. Did Juniper ever tell you about his uncle that wanted to shoot someone?”

“I don’t think he did,” replied Bethel. “Wanted to shoot someone … for the fun of it?”

“The way that Juniper described it, it was a fantasy,” said Valencia. “He wanted someone to break into his house so that he could shoot them in a way that was both legally and morally acceptable. It was a fantasy of retribution and justice, a way of being a hero in his own mind. When people see wrongs out there in the world, they sometimes construct these fantasies as a way of trying to reconcile the inherent unfairness of the world and their own powerlessness to stop it.”

“But I’m not powerless,” said Bethel. “ We aren’t powerless.”

“Our fantasies don’t have to make sense,” said Valencia. “Fantasy is rooted in psychology, and there’s no rule that states your psychological makeup is a rational and coherent whole. Perhaps for you, the fantasy of retribution, the pleasure of it, stems from those areas of your life where you haven’t been able to exercise control, where your powers have not helped you.”

“Uther,” said Bethel. “Always back to Uther.”

“He was formative for you,” said Valencia. “The man who raped you got away with it, suffering no negative consequences whatsoever for the way he treated you, and is regarded by nearly everyone in the entire world as the greatest hero who ever lived. It’s very understandable to feel rage about that, and as there’s currently no way to effectively smear his legacy or physically attack him … well, in a perfectly mundane person we might see those same fantasies of bringing justice to those who have transgressed. But it goes beyond Uther, because you were used as a weapon of war for decades, and had all sorts of indignities and harms thrust upon you in a way that was manifestly unjust. I don’t want to make this all about Uther, and I don’t invoke his name. I think you’re much more than what he did to you.”

Bethel was silent for a moment, which Valencia took as a good sign. The language she’d used had been precise, the mention of rape a specific one, intended for effect, an attempt to draw a parallel. They didn’t often talk about what had happened with Juniper, in part because this was bigger than that one incident, and in part because the specifics of that encounter as relayed by Bethel were too muddied to really be helpful. A discussion about a singular event would inevitably tend to get into the technical aspects, relitigation of what happened, and that was harder to control, with more emotion involved, than the broad strokes of how to think and behave.

“So, what does your perfect world look like?” asked Bethel. “You said that you would tell me.”

Valencia paused for a moment, evaluating whether or not to be honest. There were lies she could tell that would be instructive or helpful, a part of the therapy, lessons of their own … but they would be lies, ones that would have to be maintained in virtual perpetuity, not just this one lie, but all the other lies that would have to exist by implication.

“If I’m picking for everyone else, then I would give them what they wanted,” said Valencia. “The world would be empty of justice, but people wouldn’t need justice to be happy. They wouldn’t need evils to fight against, they would be happy and content with each other, with their families. No one would ever have to do anything they didn’t want to, and there would be no disputes to be resolved except if everyone agreed to them ahead of time.”

“Hrm,” said Bethel.

“I know it doesn’t sound appealing to you, because you’re in a particular mind to notice the lack of the feeling of justice,” said Valencia. She shrugged. “It would obviously be just, because by definition there would be no crime or wrongdoing.”

“You get no thrill from killing the infernals?” asked Bethel.

“Some,” said Valencia, nodding. “But I take them into me, and see their memories only after the fact, so it’s blunted. The justification for their murder comes only after the murder has already happened. They’re creatures of almost pure evil, all of them, and I feel no shame or sorrow in removing them from the world, but in a way, my powers growing stronger have sapped any joy I once got from it. I want to eliminate them, but it’s driven far more by compassion for their victims than by retribution.”

“And you seek to take this happiness from me?” asked Bethel. “To make my acts of violence no longer so enjoyable?”

“No,” replied Valencia. “I’d only want to ensure that you never acted violent when it wasn’t appropriate, may that day soon come.”

Therapy had its ups and downs.

Walking around with a devil constantly in her head was taxing in a way that Valencia hadn’t expected, and she found herself depending on their skill at compartmentalizing and coping. Ever since the theory had been brought up that she was gaining an infernal’s skills absent their attributes, she had been wondering what was going on at the game-mechanical level. She often tried to put things in that context, which she thought was rather helpful as a way of making sense of the world, even if it didn’t end up being accurate. There were two attributes that governed the ability to withstand stressors, Poise for withstanding social pressure, and Wisdom for withstanding mental pressure, and these were the two that were being tested on a routine basis over the course of their so-called therapy.

In the same way that she was hampered in combat by the body of a young girl, she might be hampered in her mental efforts by a brain that was still continuing its rapid development after years of isolation and abuse. She was a superb fighter, but her innate physical disadvantages would make every fight harder than it had to be. Similarly, she was a masterful conversationalist, but if those skills were, as theorized, based on her personal attributes — if an infernal’s skills were being degraded by being run through her brain — then it made sense that it could be so tiring. At least, that was the theory. They hadn’t been able to recover the manual that governed the game, and it was entirely possible that it had nothing at all about non-anima in it.

Valencia took breaks, from time to time, not actually letting herself be empty of a devil, but just some time when she wasn’t ‘on’. That naturally meant leaving Bethel for a bit, which had taken her a few days to be comfortable with, not just because of what Bethel might get up to in her absence, but because Bethel could easily strand her a long way from home.

Valencia smiled as she walked, waving at faces she’d seen once or twice in the sweets shop. Being out in the world without worrying about Bethel was nice, removing a layer of concern, and now that she wasn’t the only one with non-magical skin, there was much less to worry about from warders. Life could have been better, but she was happy, because the world was wide and colorful.

She killed devils and demons as she went. Therapy with Bethel required regular intake of devils, but it was important not to be too regular about it, because that would potentially give the infernals information about who or what was causing this unprecedented threat. Through the whole history of Aerb, only a handful of infernals had ever been killed. Since Valencia had gotten her powers, tens of thousands had died. In the context of two and a half trillion infernals across nine thousand hells, this wasn’t very many, but it was enough that they were, certainly, on the case. For every infernal she took into her, which was only a fraction of those she killed, she combed through their memories, trying to find some piece of the puzzle that would show their response. Most infernals were entirely disconnected from all but their local hell though, and usually they were disconnected from most of that hell, only concerned with an area of a few dozen miles, their town or estate, and the souls within it.

“Excuse me,” she said to a shopkeeper, careful not to pick up the threads of conversation that would delve into his life, careful not to steer him in any particular direction. These were important strategies to practice, here where it was safe. “How much is the flour?”

“Third of an obol a pound,” he replied, looking her over.

He didn’t find her very attractive. A devil’s insight was incredible overkill to know that, but she wasn’t sure that the thought would have come to her, unbidden, if she hadn’t had a devil in her. She didn’t particularly care whether or not the shopkeeper felt she was attractive or not, he was an older man in his fifties and certainly not attractive to her, and besides that, there were a hundred worse things in this world. Still, it was a lack of control of her powers that frightened her, because it meant that she might fail at a moment when it was important.

She killed another demon on the way out of the shop, tasting its memories by rote … and finding that she’d unexpectedly bit into a motherlode of information. She kept walking, not wanting to attract attention, then quickly found a small table in the outdoor section of a restaurant and sat down with the notebook she carried with her everywhere she went.

As a rule, Valencia rarely targeted anyone important in the hells. Targets were selected at random, not with a preference for demons or devils, and at random intervals. Valencia had been sleeping in the time chamber almost exclusively for some time now, even before the recent unpleasantness, which meant that there was no indication, if looking for a pattern, that there was any pattern at all. Amaryllis and Jorge had largely been responsible for this protocol, which had been created with both operational security and political neutrality in mind. The hells had their own magics, their own physics, and they had ways of reaching Aerb, if they had cause to. A random scattering of deaths would naturally be alarming to the hells, given their unprecedented nature, but an attack would be something else, something that they were much more conceptually equipped to deal with. It was important that their response be put off for as long as possible.

Unfortunately, the demon that Valencia had just eaten painted a grim picture of how far along the infernals were.

Derrodok Iz’getch, Defiler of Entrails, Rimpoche of Lethnish, was a major figure in the 2674th hell. If Valencia could have known ahead of time exactly which demon she was going to eat, she might not have chosen him, but that would have contributed to a pattern. At any rate, the point was moot, as she could only know ahead of time with either access to an infernoscope tuned to the location of her tendrils, or prior knowledge from a previous infernal’s very recent memories.

Six days ago, Derrodok had been given a briefing memo on everything that the infernals knew about what they were calling the Existence Failure Events. Valencia began to rapidly write down everything in the report, filling page after page, not stopping to think too hard about anything else, such as the minor political vacuum that Derrodok would be leaving behind, or the dozen-odd mortals he owned and regularly tortured. Instead, she focused on the briefing, which laid out in detail a number of rather concerning steps the infernals were taking.

First, there would be an all-hells taxation going into effect within the next two weeks, funneling resources toward the Omega Hell, where research would be taking place into the EFEs. Second, there would be research teams assembled on every hell in order to track and catalog every EFE that they could find, which would presumably be compiled and cataloged. Third, a large number of infernals would be conscripted from across the hells, focusing on those with particular knowledge of esoteric magics, planar phenomena, and Uther Penndraig (not that he was expected to have anything to do with it, the letter assured, but because he was automatically implicated in any major threat). Fourth, fresh mortals, especially those who held security clearances in life, would undergo interrogations by specialists, with compensation toward anyone who delivered them into control of the Omega Hell at the base of the hellchain. And finally, there was an enormous bounty for anyone who brought an end to the EFEs, not just a bounty for infernals, but one that would be communicated to Aerb itself, a guarantee of a life of paradise in the hell of their choosing, in perpetuity.

When Valencia was finished transcribing the briefing letter as best she was able to remember it, she stared at it with a glum look. Derrodok had been planning to resist the imposition, which would impact him a fair amount, which Valencia imagined would be a common response. There might be a war amongst the infernals, as there had been in the past, or a series of disorganized wars that each happened on their own hell. The stakes were high though, and eventually everyone would be coerced into cooperation, as they had been in the past. The hells were mobilizing, and much faster than expected. Compared to the time of the Apocalypse Demon, this represented a fairly small mobilization of forces, but it was clearly laying the groundwork for something bigger. And if this was the briefing that was being given to a demon of Derrodok’s importance, that probably meant that those in charge knew more, and worse, that there were likely other, less public plans in place. This briefing, after all, would be assumed to be seen by mortals who spied on the hells through infernoscope: it was the information that they didn’t care to hide or couldn't effectively conceal.

What Valencia had been quietly doing in the hells was going to intrude into the real world, and soon.

It was hard to go back to her pleasant shopping after that, but not impossible, because Valencia was very, very good at dealing with the horrifying and upsetting. The infernals almost always had memories of torturing mortals, sometimes brief, sometimes persistent, and even if she was able to stop herself from thinking about the torture while those memories were available, the hells were always on her mind. That was aside from a life spent living in a cage, a science experiment of her father’s, possessed by demons and devils on a fairly regular basis, and always treated as though she was a violent manipulator.

Valencia was quite aware that she was a broken thing stitched back together with infernal lessons, the kindness of new family, and the moral teachings of Harry Potter. She was not, in any sense, like the people she saw around her, which was perhaps why her relationship with Bethel was relatively good. They had a kinship of sorts, and even if Bethel weren’t an extremely powerful individual whose assistance would almost certainly be required to accomplish important goals, Valencia would have been inclined to help her, rather than to give her up as a lost cause. Valencia was trying her best to be good, and most days she thought that she was doing a damn sight better than most people were, no offense meant.

(Lack of action was its own problem though, and Bethel was making too much sense on that front. It was hypocrisy and inconsistency, which weren’t good for making progress, a well of disagreement that wasn’t likely to go dry soon. But such things weren’t for break time, when the world was waiting to be seen.)

Valencia had chosen Orrangush because it was less regulated than some other parts of the Empire, but also with a high standard of living that she’d thought would help to make therapy a little bit easier. The people of Orrangush were, for the most part, friendly, and their social systems made it so bad behavior was at least partly regulated away by peer pressure and ostracization, to the extent those mechanisms worked. But for all that, Orrangush wasn’t perfect, as no place on Aerb was, and another point of getting away from Bethel was to learn more about their new and temporary home, the better to set up instructive encounters and prepare for observations that Bethel might make.

There were, naturally, all the cases of the haves and have nots, those people with too little or too much, with hunger, homelessness, and sickness being the most prominent examples. Beyond that, there were domestic issues that were rarely effectively policed anywhere in the world, the kinds of crimes (if they were considered crimes at all) for which the perpetrator was often shielded from justice by either the power dynamics of the relationship, the consequences of reporting, or the troublesome nature of what constituted enough evidence for a conviction. Valencia was an astoundingly good judge of people and what they had been through, and while Bethel wasn’t quite so good, she had overwhelming forensic capabilities and a disregard for privacy that they were still working on.

During these walks and breaks from the therapy, Valencia had quietly identified a small handful of cases that might be cause for further discussion with Bethel about the nature of justice, revenge, and the sins of mortals. Valencia had, by this point, scouted the majority of their neighborhood, including those people who had passed close enough for her to give them an inspection. Some of these she was handling quietly on her own, not just because that would help with Bethel, but because it was a good and right thing to do.

The trick was making them disappear without drawing suspicion to herself, whether that was from Orrangush or Bethel. If caught by Bethel, or even merely asked, Valencia would have explained what she’d done and why, but it would be better for this to be done without Bethel ever having any knowledge of it.

Henick was a typical abuser, driven by a desire for power and control. He had been in the military and kept as a prisoner of war for eight months (something she’d learned from gossip rather than superpowers). Perhaps that was the source of it, if it needed to have a source, which Valencia didn’t particularly feel that it did. His targets were his two small children and his wife, the former more than the latter, always following typical patterns of abuse: outbursts, followed by periods of relative calm, sometimes with apologies and reconciliation, but more often with nothing but the justifications that Henick created in the moment. He was a good case study, in that he was rather typical, and there was much that Bethel might learn from him about the internal feelings that were the wellspring of his behavior … but he was operating freely, without any repercussions. If he walked into the sweets shop, and Bethel had figured it out, it was entirely possible that she would have taken matters into her own hands.

Valencia had instead talked him into leaving Orrangush, which took roughly an hour of her free time. The conversation had been personal in a way that would have been completely unacceptable in normal social circumstances, one of the barriers that Valencia faced quite often, but once his guard was down, it was easy to shape their talk and convince him to leave his family with what savings he’d managed, seeking to reclaim some of the glory he’d felt during his time in the military.

Now, with the family abandoned, Valencia felt she had a duty to make sure that they were looked after.

She brought sweets for the children and a packed dinner for the mother, with portions large enough that the three of them would have food for several days. It was just at the limit of what the mother would accept from her, in part because Valencia was always willing to sit and listen, engaging in some therapy with much lower stakes and a much more pliant subject. It was, again, weirdly personal for Valencia to be there, but she had the excuse of being foreign, and Aerb was a wide enough world that people rarely asked for specifics, not that Valencia didn’t have lies at the ready to answer for her eccentricities. The work of speaking to the wife was mostly in convincing her to reconcile with friends and family, to rebuff her husband if he returned, and to build herself a new life, to the extent that would be possible.

The last thing that Valencia had to do, when that was finished, was to write her letters. She had started out simply writing them when she was within Bethel, but that meant that Bethel could read the letters, and necessarily made the letters a part of their interactions, most of which were measured and monitored closely. Valencia had gently requested privacy, and Bethel had said that she could have privacy when she was outside, which had been the end of that conversation, at least for the time being. One letter went to Jorge, hastily written and full of pleasantries, and the other went to Amaryllis, written in a difficult cipher, which largely reported on the state of the hells. She sent both off with the telepost, hoping that they would find their way with all due haste, piggybacked on the bulk teleport network.

And with that, it was time to return home.

“Did you have a good time, out and about?” asked Bethel when Valencia returned.

“Acceptable,” replied Valencia. “Anything of note while I was away?”

“Arguments from the neighbors to the east,” replied Bethel. “I can play it back for you, if you would like?”

“Is it good or bad?” asked Valencia. “Something to model, or something to critique?”

“A bit of both,” replied Bethel, smiling slightly.

“Then let’s see it,” replied Valencia, nodding. “Could I trouble you for dinner while I watch?”

“Of course,” replied Bethel. “The stew has been cooking, and will just need to cool.”

Annad walked through the city with his enforcers following in his wake. Wherever he went, people stopped and stared, their eyes catching on him and then holding there as their brains caught up to their vision. He was well-known, the face of the operation in Orrangush, and he’d done his work to ensure that he and his men could be identified at a glance. It didn’t do to explain to people who you were and why they should be afraid of you, not when those explanations were always so much more effective when they came across in whispers from a third party. The two hulking men behind Annad certainly helped, as did the weapons they were visibly carrying, entad lookalikes.

The sweets shop he was going to had opened for business, practically overnight, nine days ago. That was enough time for him to send in someone less conspicuous to scope out the place and give him a report. It was also enough time for word to reach them about the way things worked in Orrangush, and for some nice, sotto voce whispers to be overheard by the new proprietors. So far as Annad could find out, the two girls who ran the place weren’t local, though there were limits to how much legwork he was willing to do for people in a neighborhood like theirs. Their accents were off, their particular flavor of human was unknown, and that was good enough. Annad’s warder had walked by the place and surreptitiously placed a monocle to his eye, and seen that there was an aura. That was worrying, but not entirely unexpected given how fast the move had taken place. It was something that Annad was going to keep in mind: these girls had some kind of entad magic, which meant that they were worth more than usual. Fortunately, there only appeared to be a single entad in play, at least so far as the warder could tell.

Annad had picked the timing of his visit carefully. The shop was only open for six hours a day, from noon until just before dinnertime, short hours that spoke to hobbyists rather than hard workers with their nose to the grindstone. That, again, spoke to money. Annad liked to have his visits at night, when the mood was better suited to an explanation of the opportunities that he could provide and the risks inherent in turning him down. But as that wasn’t a reliable option, given the short hours, he’d opted for right at closing time, when he could exert some force by overstaying his welcome, and when the place would be more or less cleared out.

The smaller of the two, Rossa ‘the Strong’, was sweeping the floor as he approached the shop. Annad was hard to miss, and his enforcers were even harder to miss, given that they were a pair of aborians, one of the largest of the mortal species, with claws made for rending trees and specialty oversized pistols at their hips, decorated to look like they might be magical.

Rossa saw them, but she didn’t react like she should have. Her eyes didn’t go wide in surprise or confusion, she merely glanced at them and kept on sweeping, without giving them any more notice. Annad reached forward and opened the door, stepping inside.

“Oh, sorry,” said Rossa. “We just closed. We’ll be open tomorrow, starting at noon.” She had bright, friendly, apologetic eyes, and a surprisingly disarming expression.

“You always turn away paying customers?” asked Annad.

“When they come in off-hours, yes,” said Rossa.

Annad watched her for a moment, trying to take the measure of her, then reached into his pocket and pulled out his pocketwatch, making a show of looking at it. “By my reckoning, I have another three minutes left. And the bells haven’t rung six yet.”

“Ignore my companion,” said the taller woman, Nephthys, from up the stairs. She was visibly muscular, outside the norm for a human, but probably just an outlier, unless she had some broshe blood in her. The scout had said that she had a sour look on her face, but as she traipsed down the steps from the second floor she looked practically joyous. “We’ve been keeping hours short as we get our legs beneath us, but we’ve been meaning to expand anyhow, and you’re right, we shouldn’t be pushing away customers.” She craned her long neck to look past Annad to the enforcers standing outside. “Are your friends coming in?”

“No,” said Annad, finally stepping through the door entirely. “They’ll wait outside for us.”

“And what kind of sweets are you interested in today?” asked Nephthys, beaming at him. “We have a wide selection, including a few specialties that can’t be found anywhere else on Aerb.”

Annad regarded her. If she had any reaction at all to him as something other than a customer, she was hiding it well. When Annad was eight years old, he’d taken an axe to the face, and his parents hadn’t had the money for healing until after the wound was set. He’d grown to like the scar well enough as he’d aged, and even gone so far as rejecting an offer to have an imperial soul mage reverse the damage entirely, which was apparently what it would have taken.

“You’re new in town, the two of you,” said Annad. He took a step toward some of the candies, looking at them as though making up his mind about which to get.

“We can cut through the shit,” said Rossa. Annad looked at her. He had a good handle on women, and the kind of woman who swore, and he hadn’t pegged Rossa for the type. She was looking at him with hard eyes, hand gripped tight around the broom. Her knuckles were white. “You’re here to offer us protection, and if we don’t take you up on your protection, you’re going to make some threats about the kinds of bad things that could happen to us.” She took a breath and glanced at Nephthys. Rossa was breathing harder, and her eyes had finally gone wide, hinting at manic thoughts. The change in demeanor had been sudden. “If you leave now, —” She stopped and looked at Nephthys again. The tall, muscular woman was still smiling. “Nephthys, listen to me, I know you think this man’s life is —”

“Oh, he’s a bully,” said Nephthys. She was grinning at Annad, ignoring her companion. “Aren’t you?”

“No,” said Annad, straightening to his full height. “I’m a businessman. When the police fail to render their services as they should, someone needs to stand up and do things properly in their place. I don’t know what you’ve heard, but my business is protection, not bullying. I’m a professional.”

He was starting to grow uncomfortable. The real, honest fear in Rossa’s eyes wasn’t directed at Annad, it was directed at her companion. Neither of them looked uncertain about him. It could all be an act, but that kind of stage play put on for him would be a plan with far too many ways to go south. Annad had seen all kinds of reactions to his business model, and anger wasn’t uncommon. Once or twice he’d seen wives tell their husbands not to get angry, that it wasn’t worth it, that nothing good would come of lashing out (which was entirely true). Putting it in that context, he thought maybe he understood this situation a little bit better, with Rossa warning off Nephthys from doing something rash. On the other hand, it was entirely possible that these two had more power than they seemed. Annad was perfectly aware that in the grand scheme of things, he was just a man with a handful of entads whose only real training was in clawing his way up through the ranks of the criminal world.

But what would a magus be doing running a sweets shop? And weren’t they both frightfully young to have amassed any power? The little one couldn’t have been much older than fifteen, the taller one in her early twenties.

“Morally speaking,” said Nephthys, looking over to Rossa. “Why should this man live?”

Rossa folded her arms, frowning. “All people deserve life.”

Annad could feel a cold sweat on the back of his neck. This wasn’t how this was supposed to go, and it wasn’t how it had ever gone before. They were speaking as though his death was a foregone conclusion. What he needed was time, time to figure out which brand of mages they were, and what he could do about it.

“All?” asked Nephthys. “Really? All?”

“All,” repeated Rossa. “If we had infinite resources, I would give everyone their own infinite plot of land, with their own infinite resources, because I think that’s the moral thing to do.”

“And yet we don’t live in such a world,” replied Nephthys. “So men like this should, in your view, go to prison, a prison which is paid for with the labor and resources of their betters. When you say that he deserves life, what you mean is that he deserves to be kept alive, away from others, at my expense.”

“Not necessarily your expense,” said Rossa.

“I can leave,” said Annad. “I can give you privacy.” He tried to be firm as he said it, but there was no way to leave without sounding like a coward.

“Hush,” replied Nephthys. “We’re deciding your fate.”

Annad tried to move, and found an invisible wall of force blocking him. He touched it, experimentally, and found that it completely encircled him. It was a ward, one which he’d somehow stepped into without being able to see it. Such things weren’t supposed to be possible, or at least not easy, not unless you knew for certain where your target was going to be well in advance.

“My men,” Annad began. He turned toward them. They looked uncomfortable, standing there.

“Why don’t you call them in,” said Nephthys. “Better that they don’t complicate things.”

Annad hesitated. If he called them in, they would be caught in this web too, pinned down by these people with too much power. If he shouted a warning, they might run and get help, the warder, or the entire team, but that might seal his own fate here, under the thumb of this muscular woman who had used advanced magic without showing any sign of it.

Nephthys moved over and opened the door, looking back at Annad.

“Run!” he screamed. “Find help! They have magic!”

To his immense surprise, the enforcers moved into the sweets shop, squeezing through the doorframe, which was only just wide and tall enough to accommodate them.

“What the hells are you doing?” he asked. “I said to run!”

And with that, his men seemed to register actual shock and concern. The bigger of the brothers, Herk, moved to push Nephthys aside, but his arm passed through her, then met solid air. All at once, the shades at the front of the shop went down, blocking out light and obscuring the interior from view. The two aborian brothers began to shout, but their screams came out wordless, behind some kind of ward that had been built through impossible means.

“They’ll notice that I’m missing,” said Annad.

“He’s right,” said Rossa. “If we let them leave now, with the fear in them, and promise them to secrecy, we might not have to move.”

“Oh, I don’t particularly mind moving,” said Nephthys.

“Staying in one place to get repeat exposure to people is part of the therapy,” said Rossa. “If we make a scene and murder a few people everytime someone moderately antagonistic comes to visit us, we’re never going to get anywhere.”

“I’ve been good,” said Nephthys, pouting slightly.

“You’ve acted good,” said Rossa. “But you’re a long way from the mindset that you’ll need. You can’t just kill everyone who looks at you wrong.”

“He was going to threaten us,” said Nephthys. “If we didn’t give him money, he was going to say that maybe this place might catch fire, or maybe there would be burglars. And if we kept not paying, he would pay men to light this place on fire, or break our windows, or poison our candy.”

“I wouldn’t,” said Annad.

“He wouldn’t poison,” Rossa clarified, though who knew how the hells she knew that. “The other things, yes. But we could easily spare the money he asked for, handed it over without a problem, and continued on with our lives. I understand that you have your reservations about letting him free when he’s going to prey on other people who don’t have our advantages, but we could have talked about this after he’d left. We both know that the money means nothing to us. We know that he would eventually return to take from us again, and if he didn’t, we could track him. It could have been handled later.”

“I was impulsive,” said Nephthys, nodding. “This is true.”

Annad was quiet. He didn’t think that he could say anything that would help his case. He was now entirely convinced that he was going to die, a feeling that he’d had only twice before in a life that had been marked by violence and danger. ‘We both know money means nothing to us,’ the little one had said.

“To go back to the earlier argument,” said Rossa. “Yes, keeping men like him jailed requires resources, but they don’t need to be your resources, someone else might volunteer theirs.”

“So you believe, hypothetically, that this man should be kept in a small room at your expense for the rest of his natural life, segregated from the rest of society?” asked Nephthys.

“No,” said Rossa. “There will always be opportunities for rehabilitation.”

“Rehabilitation that comes with costs,” said Nephthys. “Costs that you’re hypothetically paying?”

“You’re thinking about a hypothetical world in which I’m resource-constrained and have to choose between prison and rehabilitation,” said Rossa.

“I do love that you know what I’m thinking,” replied Nephthys with a grin.

Annad surreptitiously looked down at the ground, trying to see whether there was something he could use to escape this ward, a loose floorboard and some way to slip beneath it, or something that was equally unlikely to be true. He moved his foot to the side, checking that the ward was actually encompassing him, and found that it was. This talk about eternal prison wasn’t making him particularly calm.

“We live in a reality of resource constraints,” said Rossa. “We can’t pay millions of obols for everyone to live their best life. If it came down to it, I would kill men like him, if it meant better men could live better lives, but it’s a question of margins, and I don’t think that Juniper would agree.”

“So you suggest what?” asked Nephthys. “That I don’t torture these men to death and dump their bodies deep underground where they’ll never be found? That I let them go, so that they can use violence and intimidation to steal from people in return for nebulous ‘services’? And worse, obviously.”

“Just a moment,” said Rossa, holding up a hand. “I think I took the wrong tack.”

“The wrong tack to convince me?” asked Nephthys. “And what, praytell, is the right one?”

“This man is a product of his environment, as all people are,” said Rossa.

Annad continued surreptitiously checking for gaps in the ward, moving his hands where they were more out of sight, especially from the bigger woman.

“I’m listening,” said Nephthys. “He’s a product of his environment, and in theory, if he’d been raised better, he might not have turned out such a shitheel.”

“I don’t mean a product of his environment in a historical sense, though that’s probably true,” said Rossa. “I mean that here and now, he exists only because there was a gap within this society for him to exist within. If we kill him, that gap will remain, and some other person will come to fill it. Perhaps more efficiently, perhaps less, and yes, you’re thinking now that you could simply kill all possible candidates for his position —”

“It’s sometimes mildly annoying to have you know what I’m thinking,” said Nephthys, frowning.

“I’m saying that your thought is right,” said Rossa. “You could become the entity that keeps the gap closed by killing anyone who steps out of line. You could kill everyone with the temperament and training to fill that gap. But that requires time and resources, resources that you’ve already said you’re loath to spend. To actually fix the problem, to eliminate men like this from the world without spending absurd amounts of limited resources, we need to use them.”

Nephthys was silent, frowning as she considered that. Annad had no idea what expression he should have on his face, so stayed as carefully blank as he could, though he was sweating profusely, and he was certain that fear was showing on him. It was a fear he hadn’t felt since he was much younger and smaller.

“Ah,” she finally said. “It’s moral to use men like this, immoral men, because they must pay a price for their immorality. Is that so?”

“I’m not sure that I would put it like that,” replied Rossa. “What I mean is that this man exists as he does because there’s a space for him to exist within this society. What we can do is to provide a new place in society for him and people like him, while at the same time closing the gap. We can use him. We can subvert him.”

“But that would be an exercise of our powers,” replied Nephthys. “One you think is moral? And not just because you’re trying to save his life like the naive waif you are?”

Rossa didn’t answer, instead turning to Annad. “We could easily kill you,” she said. “I hope that’s clear to you now. We have power beyond whatever you’re thinking. You probably imagine we’re mages with a fair number of entads? Well, we’re more than that, a lot more than that. Not gods, but demigods, of our own varieties. We’re here because we’re trying to work some things out about ourselves. Now, what we need from you, in order for you to keep living, is for you to make this city a good place to live. That’s not going to happen by you doing good deeds, it’s going to happen by making some systemic changes to how things are done. To that end, we’re going to make a new order in Orrangush which uses you and your people as a tool. And yes, to answer your next question, we’re going to be making a lot of changes, and yes, this will impact your relationship with your superiors.”

Everything she said, it seemed as though she was pre-empting the next question he was going to ask. If they would be believed, they were offering him entrance on the ground floor of some new criminal enterprise, except it wasn’t clear that there was anything criminal about this.

“What do you want me to do?” asked Annad.

“He’s just doing this out of fear,” said Nephthys, frowning. “That’s not a good basis for getting people to do things. He hasn’t even asked what happens if he doesn’t do as we say.”

“I’m well aware that it’s not a good lever,” replied Rossa. “But we’re going to be giving him at least some of what he wants in his heart of hearts, prestige and power, along with the occasional bout of violence.”

“Oh, but I’m not allowed to engage in bouts of violence,” said Nephthys with a pout.

“Of course you are, when the situation warrants it,” replied Rossa.

“No,” replied Nephthys, shaking her head. “Because every time someone comes along with some moronic plan to do harm to me or the people inside me, I’m told that I should exercise restraint, that I should just hold them in place for questioning — questioning which, I might add, is never the way that I would do it, which must never start or end with dismemberment or physical violence.” She glared at Annad. “Even now, this thug, you would think less of me if I sliced him up.”

“Think in the long term,” replied Rossa. “Even if you think the world is better off without him, important people feel otherwise.”

Annad heard the phrase ‘important people’ and temporarily stopped searching for a seam in the ward. That implied that they somehow weren’t important people. He had been assuming that people like this answered to no one, not because they were more powerful than him, but because they were more powerful than him in ways that seemed like they should have been impossible. An imperial fireteam of trained mages, those he would have had the conceptual framework for, but this … and they weren’t even the important people.

“I can’t believe you’re stooping to social blackmail,” replied Nephthys, shaking her head.

“I know what you’re feeling,” said Rossa. “He’s scum, and you want to end him, not because it would be good, but because it would be satisfying. That’s part of growing up though, knowing to choose what’s good over what’s satisfying.”

“‘Growing up’,” said Nephthys, shaking her head. She turned to Annad again. “Well then, you heard the woman, you’re going to be working for us now. Your life is contingent on you being a good person, or at least being a bastard in our service. The same goes for everyone currently in your employ. Perhaps, with time, you’ll come to appreciate our unique offerings as your employer, or perhaps I’ll flense off your skin and feed it to you.”

“Don’t think about running,” said Rossa. “If you leave Orrangush, we’ll know, and our ability to track you is virtually unparalleled across all of Aerb. If you start preparing to leave, we’ll know. For your own sake, work with us.”

“And if he does?” asked Nephthys. “What work, precisely, are we talking about, little one?”

“Intervention,” replied Rossa. “I’m ceding you some ground. It’s true that we should be doing more, but we have to do it right.”

Penndraig's Rules of Order

“So,” said Rosemallow once Amaryllis had arrived at the White Room. “How did your meeting go?” Rosemallow wore a pink and white dress that deepened in color toward the top, mimicking the general shape and appearance of the flower from which she took her name. Almost everyone in the Court had flower-themed names, and on certain occasions, especially more formal ones, they were expected to wear their colors. For Amaryllis, that was typically white with veins of crimson, or possibly a pink or purple if the situation called for something especially bold. It wasn’t clear whether Rosemallow was dressed up for something, or whether she was just dressing according to her mood.

“The meeting went well enough,” replied Amaryllis. “Until the point when half the most valuable members of my team were abducted, and a monster, something called a skent, was unleashed in Caledwich Castle.” Amaryllis was certain that Rosemallow knew all of this. Her aunt’s question could only be taken as a smug ‘I told you so’, meant to reinforce Rosemallow’s superiority.

“The meeting was a bad idea,” said Rosemallow, pushing forward a tray of delicately prepared finger food. “I fear the damage to your forces is the least of your worries though, unless the meeting concluded without an agreement?”

“We reached an agreement,” said Amaryllis. “The problem is that it depended at least partially on good faith, or at least both of us following what I thought to be our incentives. Tell me, will they have any fallout from attacking us at Caledwich Castle?”

“Can you prove that they struck first?” asked Rosemallow.

“Raven was a witness,” said Amaryllis. “In a fair world, her testimony would be unimpeachable, but I expect that they’re moving to smear and undermine her as we speak. I don’t think that they expected her to be able to resist what they tried, and I’m certain they would have rather she died. The question will come down to testimony though, and it’s not the kind of issue that would be solved using some of the more extreme means.”

There were magical means for compulsory testimony, but almost all of them were extremely expensive or utterly horrific, or both, and some were state secrets, which meant that there were others that were also state secrets, but at a higher clearance than Amaryllis ever had. A soul mage could technically comb through the memories to find something of relevance, but this was almost never done, both because it was so incredibly time-consuming, and because it was illegal on the imperial level (and if you were doing high crimes, you could just soulfuck them into compliance). There was one entad, used only in extreme circumstances, which would rip apart the mind of the person it was used on, pulling out bits and pieces of them and only occasionally getting the complete truth.

“No, I doubt it would rise to that level,” replied Rosemallow. “Who does Raven say were the belligerents, or was the attack without an obvious source?”

“Yarrow and Zinnia,” replied Amaryllis. “It would be helpful if you would tell me where they are. It’s a reasonable expectation that our people are in one of the black sites.”

“Some sites are more black than others,” said Rosemallow, slightly raising an eyebrow. “Tell me, what kind of security procedures do you follow among your people? How much do they know?”

“Juniper knows everything,” said Amaryllis. This was pretty much true, with only one glaring exception that she could think of, and that one thing was interpersonal rather than being relevant in an information security context.

“You do realize that they’re going to torture him, don’t you?” asked Rosemallow. “Most likely they’ll use a revision mage, which means that even with training, he’s not bound to last long, and even if he’s recovered, he won’t know how much he’s given away.”

“I understand that,” said Amaryllis. “I’ve been trying to prepare for it. I’ve also been trying to prepare for having him walk through that door having killed dozens of people during his escape.”

“Onion and Phlox are running things,” said Rosemallow. “They may have many unsavory qualities, but they’re competent operators. There is no possibility that your allies will escape.”

“I don’t question their competence,” said Amaryllis. “I question their ability to prepare for things that no one has seen in five hundred years.”

Rosemallow tapped her lip. “You’re trying to say that Uther has returned,” she said.

Amaryllis frowned. “I haven’t said anything of the sort.”

“You’ve done well not to,” nodded Rosemallow. “Yet you’ve also arranged quite a bit of evidence that would suggest as much. Raven Masters is, to say the least, a major indicator. It hasn’t escaped my notice that you’ve assembled a motley crew of the sort that Uther always seemed to favor. Nor has it gone unnoticed that Juniper has become a master of still magic in far less time than it should have taken, something I don’t feel is adequately explained by a time chamber, even one of the caliber you seem to have. I didn’t feel a need to place any spies in Li’o when you were going about your humanitarian work there, but there were certain stories that reached my ears anyhow. There are claims that your people were the ones to kill Mome Rath when the whole city was paralyzed and no one else could so much as know about the creature. It all suggests something of Uther. All that’s lacking is the declaration that it’s so.”

“You think this is a gambit,” said Amaryllis.

“I sometimes forget how young you are,” said Rosemallow. “We’re the Lost King’s Court. The fundamentals of our system of governance rest on our descent from Uther Penndraig, and on the fact that he is not here to govern. If you’re trying to suggest that Uther has, in some manner, returned —”

“I’m not,” said Amaryllis.

“Claims have been made before,” said Rosemallow. “Usually it’s someone suffering from a delusion, but there have been a few occasions when the individual in question applied a bit of intellect to the deception. There were always hurdles to overcome, given how easy it would be for Uther himself to prove his identity. The accounts are classified, but they’re very droll, from a certain point of view.”

“That’s not what we’re doing,” said Amaryllis. “Is that what Onion and Phlox think we’re up to?”

“I don’t know if it’s crossed their minds,” said Rosemallow. “It wouldn’t surprise me if they considered it, but I know they don’t have all the information that I have.” She leaned forward. “You can take me into your confidence.”

“This isn’t a gambit,” said Amaryllis. “And I don’t necessarily understand the threat an imposter would pose. The Court wouldn’t roll over for any but Uther himself, and maybe not even then.”

“The threat wouldn’t be through legal channels,” said Rosemallow. “It would be through the public. There’s been unrest, nothing violent so far, but that could change if people had the right person to rally behind and a reasonable expectation of success. The end of the Second Empire set a bad precedent, more because of the stories that people told of the common man rising up against a monstrous evil than from any accurate reading of history. If someone claiming to be Uther came along to declare the Court null and void, and he was backed by a billion obols and hundreds of entads … well. It would be ambitious.”

“It’s hard for me to tell whether you’re still accusing me, or simply suggesting a trajectory that I might take,” said Amaryllis. “And it doesn’t matter, because Juniper has been taken, if not killed.” Amaryllis still had her half-share of his power, which was a strong indicator that he was alive somewhere. She was trying not to worry, because she was already in the process of doing everything that she could reasonably be expected to do.

“If he’s a fraud, they’ll expose him, and it will reflect extremely poorly on you,” said Rosemallow.

“He’s not pretending to be Uther,” said Amaryllis. He’s trying to find Uther. “There’s no threat there. I honestly don’t think Juniper thinks or cares about Anglecynn at all.”

“Yet he grew up here,” said Rosemallow.

“No,” replied Amaryllis. “He’s dream-skewered.” If Juniper was being tortured, that was one of the first things that would come out, in part by design: it was a secret with warts and wrinkles that he could feed them to stall for time. It wasn’t all that secret, given how many places it could leak.

Rosemallow was silent for a moment, facial muscles twitching slightly as she processed that. “He is?” she asked.

“Yes,” said Amaryllis. “You’re familiar with the condition?”

“Somewhat,” replied Rosemallow. “There was an incident at Speculation and Scrutiny not too long ago, outside their dream-skewered clinic, in Boastre Vino. This would have been some time after Larkspur’s death. Did you have anything to do with that?”

Amaryllis nodded. “We just went to get some answers from an expert. Things heated up considerably.”

“There are some theories, largely ignored and forgotten, that Uther himself was dream-skewered,” said Rosemallow.

“I’m aware,” replied Amaryllis, keeping stone-faced.

“The more I learn of your situation, the more curious it becomes,” said Rosemallow.

“You haven’t asked about the terms of the contract,” said Amaryllis. “With respect, I didn’t come here to have you boggle at the absurdity of my current situation, I came here because we have at least some goals in common. Time is a precious resource.”

“Oh, I know all about your contract,” said Rosemallow. “I obtained a copy shortly after your signature was added to it. It might have been a fine thing, if they hadn’t decided on force from the beginning. As it stands, it’s likely that the entire thing will be null and void, unless the councils are particularly against you and decide that certain parts are valid while others are not. I can apply some pressure to ensure that doesn’t happen, if it comes to that.”

“Then the meeting was a waste,” said Amaryllis. “Nothing of what was said in the Mirror Room made any difference whatsoever, it was all about what happened in the Prince’s Room.” It wasn’t exactly a surprise, but she still felt bitter about it.

“We can speak of the good and the bad,” said Rosemallow. “If someone did unleash a skent in Caledwich Castle, we could argue that demonstrates enormous disregard for not just civilians, but other members of the nobility, possibly rising to the level of a high crime. It would be contested, obviously, and given classifications, would only be discussed on a select few councils.”

“There’s a program to breed them and bond them with members of the nobility, and you knew about it,” said Amaryllis.

“I’ll choose not to confirm or deny that at this time,” said Rosemallow. “At this point, everything you know about the skents comes from Raven, who would have made her own observations divorced from our classification protocols. Best to keep it that way.”

“How likely are we to have to fight one again?” asked Amaryllis.

“I couldn’t say,” replied Rosemallow.

“I need to know if the skent breeding program I’m assuming exists somewhere resulted in dozens or hundreds of them,” said Amaryllis.

“You’re too young to have been taught about a certain political scandal that lanced through the Court not long after the Grand Reconciliation,” said Rosemallow. “It would suffice to say that I’ve been careful with classification since learning about it, especially since the younger generation has needed a lesson for some time, and I don’t want to be the unfortunate teacher-by-example.”

“If you think that I don’t have a detailed knowledge of every political scandal to have rocked Anglecynn since the time of Uther, you’re mistaken,” said Amaryllis. “Myosotis, FE 346. Far before your time, when the Court was in a different place.”

“Have you shared classified information?” asked Rosemallow, raising an eyebrow. “That’s another thing that might come out through interrogation.”

“And they would try to pin me on that, when they released a monster that could realistically have killed dozens?” asked Amaryllis.

“I’m only trying to determine courses of action and lines of conversation,” said Rosemallow. “Some things are more classified than others, and you never knew everything there was to know. Project Garden Stake was the highest clearance project, if I recall, so there are limits to how much trouble you could be in on that front. My worry is at least partially about how this will play with the public, or before an open council.”

“You’re the one who made this about the public,” said Amaryllis. She paused. “You’ve been putting my name out, trying to get the common people invested in me. What you said before about the possibility of me setting up a fraud where I claimed to have Uther back, was that your intent?”

Rosemallow shook her head. “No, of course not, not in a literal sense. To claim that you were a reincarnation of Uther through magical means, or that Juniper was Uther, back from the great beyond in a new body, would require solutions to some very large and currently intractable problems, at least if the deception were to survive any amount of scrutiny. With that said, we’re not confined to only the literal level. Uther’s spiritual or metaphorical return would serve nicely, and without the constitutional crisis.”

Amaryllis rolled that over in her head, trying to get a grip on it. “You want to use this perception as part of a plan to win the current battle against Onion,” she said. “All you have is public pressure. I don’t see how it would be enough.”

“One of your faults is that you believe in great people doing great things,” said Rosemallow. “It’s apparent in your writings, and to a greater extent, your actions. I believe it to be a common failing of Penndraigs, and of the Anglish in general, perhaps caused by the fact that we place so much emphasis on Uther, a bright and shining star who has never been rivaled. The will of the public matters. It’s not subordinate to any single great person, and can’t be swayed except temporarily, or with systemic effects. That’s what makes it powerful.”

Amaryllis wasn’t particularly appreciating the lesson, nor did she think that Rosemallow had a very good grasp on her. Amaryllis had written about systemic effects in her diary, she was sure that she had, and if she also wrote about how she wanted to become a prime mover so that things that needed doing could get done … well, the world really did seem to contain some people that were uniquely important and powerful individuals. Amaryllis would have believed that even if Juniper hadn’t spoken to the One True God, may his dice fall fair.

“I need my people back,” said Amaryllis. “Things have gone south with Hyacinth and I might be in a worse situation than before. I was warned, I know. The priority is recovering my team.”

“If Onion has put them somewhere, it will be beyond my reach,” said Rosemallow. “No doubt he’ll have used a thin legal pretense for this action, but obviously I’ll challenge him on it. There’s leverage in it.”

“I need more than that,” said Amaryllis. “I need leads.”

“It’s clear you’re thinking rash thoughts,” said Rosemallow, frowning slightly. “You’re thinking of Miunun.”

“What?” asked Amaryllis. “No.”

“Without Juniper you lose quorum,” said Rosemallow. “You’ve been using him in too many ways.”

“I’m not worried about it,” said Amaryllis. “You’re looking for hooks where there are none.”

“Then I don’t understand the urgency,” said Rosemallow, folding her hands. “He’s gone, Amaryllis. The only way he and the others will be returned to you is if Onion decides it’s so. If you could, somehow, find which site he’s at and break in to rescue him, you would be putting yourself in a far worse position than the one you’re in right now. As it stands, the contract might be troublesome and all the fundamentals are essentially the same as they were the day before, but they have information that you don’t want them to have.”

“Fine,” said Amaryllis. “Pretend that’s true. But also prepare a contingency path in case Juniper comes back to Anglecynn in the next few days having killed a dozen people in his impossible escape.”

“I’ll do that,” nodded Rosemallow. “Now, can I tell you what steps we’re taking? I know you’re a willful girl, and I worry that every word out of my mouth will be met with an objection.”

“Go ahead,” replied Amaryllis, folding her arms.

“The first step is to get you seated on councils, as many and as widely varied as possible,” said Rosemallow. “That will be in preparation for your trial, which we’ll want to undertake as quickly as possible. While the contract is dubious, we can press on that, assuming that you would still want those terms, which I think is questionable. Even if you don’t, Onion has put in writing that it’s possible for him to waive your service requirement, which I believe to be an error on his part. You won’t have a proper role in the councils until after the trial, but it’s a good show that you fully intend to be a member in good standing of the Lost King’s Court. We will, naturally, have to do something about your look, and if possible, have you out of armor as much as you can be.”

“No,” said Amaryllis.

“You’re a diplomat now, not a warrior,” said Rosemallow. “The fullplate is a bit much, and it hides your figure.”

“Do you understand that these people are trying to kill me?” asked Amaryllis.

“Of course,” replied Rosemallow. “That’s why you’ll be staying here, with my security, and why we will prevent you from joining the Host at all costs. I would hate to put in all this effort only to have you wind up dead. Moving on, we’ll push what leverage we have as hard as we can. You’re absolutely right that they made an attack on Caledwich, and that Raven has an incredible pedigree that we can use to our advantage, both as a witness and as a general asset, assuming that she’s willing to follow orders. Is she?”

“She views this as a sideshow,” said Amaryllis. “In her view, we should be focusing on more important things than who controls Anglecynn or how to get one and a half billion obols out of trust.”

“And what’s more important than that?” asked Rosemallow, leaning forward slightly.

“Uther’s legacy,” said Amaryllis. Maybe Uther himself. “She’s been looking for a successor to Uther for quite some time, trying to create one, or be one. So long as our small group can keep doing things like we did in Li’o, she’ll be with us.”

“You maintain that this isn’t a deception of some kind,” said Rosemallow. “You believe that it’s the truth. You think that Juniper is, in some sense, a repetition of Uther, one you can use.” There was something like wonder in her eyes, a first, so far as Amaryllis could ever recall. “Except that he’s now missing, presumed captured,” said Rosemallow. She looked Amaryllis over. “I’ll put more resources into the contingency that he returns. In the meantime, you should make a list of the councils you’re most interested and adapted for. You have a curious and powerful time chamber, and I don’t doubt that you’ve been using it. There’s an open spot on the Commoner Council, which I think you would be well-suited to.”

“I would be most interested in Industry, Infrastructure, Research and Development, and Culture,” said Amaryllis. One of these things is not like the others.

Rosemallow was in her watching mode, taking in minute facial expressions, weighing each word as though they were high-stakes gamblers and she thought that Amaryllis might be bluffing. “There are duties that come with council meetings. If I got you even two of those, it would require you to spend quite a bit of time in the Anglecynn, which I know isn’t your preference.”

“Two would be fine,” replied Amaryllis. “I’ll handle it.”

“You really do need my help,” said Rosemallow, her tone so ambiguous that it was hard to know whether to take that as a threat, a statement of fact, or pity.

“I do,” said Amaryllis. “My priority right now is putting this all to bed. If that means that I have to make frequent trips back here, then so be it.”

“It’s good that you’re looking far into the future,” said Rosemallow. “But what you should be concerned with is what’s coming up soon. They’re going to push for a trial, and soon, especially while you’re off your balance. It doesn’t hurt that a trial can help to distract from the significant errors they made at Caledwich. Be prepared for it to get vicious.”

“I always am,” replied Amaryllis.

They were waiting on a sign or signal from Juniper, and it was slow in coming.

Amaryllis was staying at the Erstwhile Manor with Raven, while the rest of the much-reduced team was at the Hotel Delzora. Now that the peace was broken, they were almost certainly going to try to get her into jail, which meant no more moving around the city without cause. If Amaryllis did go to jail, there was a possibility that they would try to kill her there, though Rosemallow seemed to think that what had happened at Caledwich Castle was a colossal fuckup on their end (not her words) which they wouldn’t be eager to repeat. There were provisions for a member of the Court to stake someone on bonded release, which they would use in order to keep Amaryllis under Rosemallow’s nominal care without the jail being involved, but there wasn’t a way to guarantee that unless Amaryllis stayed as close to Rosemallow as possible.

As part of trial preparation, Amaryllis was reading through her old diaries. They were, thanks to Rosemallow, a part of the public record, and there was a chance that they would be used as part of the proceedings. Amaryllis had done her fair share of reading about the legal system used in the United States of America, on Earth, and desperately wished that Uther had managed to import some of the saner features. From what Juniper had said, Arthur had been enthusiastic about the law, but while Uther had written a huge number of laws and crafted legal frameworks, both in Anglecynn and the First Empire, and engaged in legal reforms of various other polities, the rules that governed the Court showed little of that care and devotion. Of course, some of that might have been because the Lost King’s Court had never been intended, and a fair bit of its current practices had been built up after Uther was gone.

In America, there was a process of discovery, whereby both sides of a trial were allowed (and required) to share evidence. Surprise witnesses were virtually unheard of, as was evidence introduced in the middle of proceedings. Further, both prosecution and defense were constrained in what they could bring up, with questions of character and prior bad acts generally being inadmissible. There were rules about decorum, about badgering, about hostility and self-incrimination. There were limits to how off the rails the questioning could go.

Amaryllis couldn’t help but feel wistful about the American legal system, which she’d only known through reading about it. The Court desperately needed some kind of legal reform, as if the existence of trial by adversity weren’t proof enough of that.

Reading back her diaries was painful, in part because she had so much distance from them that she could just barely remember what was in them. Rosemallow had produced the originals, but Amaryllis was reading the edited version. At times she would stop and search through the originals, only to find that no, that was something she’d actually written down, not some bit of simplistic propaganda that Rosemallow had inserted in. There were groan-worthy essays where a younger Amaryllis had just discovered that systemic problems sometimes arose from the natural incentives people followed, and Amaryllis wanted to just grab her younger self by the head and scream, ‘everyone already knows this!’. That wasn’t terribly charitable, but Amaryllis also believed that you didn’t owe your younger self much respect.

Specifically with regards to things that might come up at the desertion trial, there were a number of passages that went against very orthodox views within the Court. One of the justifications for the structural nepotism of Anglecynn was the argument that the Penndraigs were raised from birth to be rulers, with the best education, nutrition, and magical assistance available. It was a line that Amaryllis herself had repeated quite a few times, but while she was definitely more suited to rule than the average commoner, in her diary she had proposed that outliers among the commoners would almost certainly out-perform the average Penndraig. That was a heresy, though not the kind that you would get put to death over. It was the sort of thing that, in a desertion trial, would get brought up to show that she wasn’t a team player, or just to trigger some of the biases of whoever was deciding her fate.

Rosemallow had made redactions to the diaries, removing a few sections on menstruation, and another recounting an unpleasurable experiment with masturbation. Amaryllis found this understandable but annoying: those things had been put into the diary with the understanding that someone might read them some day. They had been private and personal, but an important aspect of her internal understanding of herself. It was the kind of thing that helped to sell the diaries as being intimate, which would make them more effective, even if they were embarrassing, especially because they were embarrassing.

The diaries could be used to paint her as a revolutionary, or if not that, then at least with views so far outside the mainstream of the Court that she was implicitly a threat. Her position as a bright star orbiting the edges of the Court made that an even more compelling argument, and her lack of family made it more tempting to push her out in one way or another, even without taking into account how much someone like Hyacinth would benefit from Amaryllis’ death. The primary argument, when it came to a charge of desertion, was that Amaryllis had fled because she feared for her life if she tried to go to the Host. The primary counter argument was that she simply hated the Court and wanted to shirk her duty, as evidenced by the fact that she had only returned to the Court when pressure was put on her by an outside force. Rosemallow would no doubt fabricate a chain of correspondence and a legal pretense for Amaryllis to remain outside the kingdom for so long, but the trial would fundamentally not be about legality, it would be about loyalties, alliances, and perceptions of gain and loss.

“How long do you think it’s going to take Joon to come back?” asked Raven.

“I don’t know,” replied Amaryllis. “I suppose right at the critical moment. We still haven’t gotten the check-in.” It had been six hours, and Amaryllis was starting to grow tired. Juniper had the sleeping ring, specifically because it was more important for him to have it if they got separated. “Shit, I should have arranged with Grak for us to sleep in shifts.”

“You’ll know for next time,” said Raven. “We could send Grak a letter and coordinate that way.”

“Infosec risk,” said Amaryllis. “And I’m not sure that it would actually matter. Did you finish cross-referencing your worldline with the list of black sites?” Amaryllis was trying to use her own vibration magic to keep things silent, but it took mental effort, and she had half the skill of Juniper. It would suffice to say that certain topics were off the table for the time being.

“I have approximate matches for three of the eleven,” said Raven. “Moderate matches for another five. The problem is that they’re all in out-of-the-way places. When I was working with the Library, nine times out of ten I was going to one of the major cities, and I wasn’t called out all that often. With Uther, we ranged a lot more, but by the time we were ranging all over Aerb, we had the entads necessary to go point-to-point virtually at will. If he is at a black site, there’s a decent chance that it will take days to get to him, given how much distance we might have to cover in conventional ways.”

“And that means that if he makes an escape from wherever he’s being held, it might be days or even weeks for him to get back to us,” said Amaryllis.

“Or it might be impossible for him to escape without us fixing things on our end,” said Raven. “That happened once or twice with Uther. The first time he went to another plane, he was temporarily stuck there without any backup, fighting for his life while we figured out a way to reverse the magical effect that had done it. When we finally got him back, he spilled out through the portal with a horde of monsters after him, his resources almost completely depleted. The second time, which is arguable, we pulled him out of a deep dream, but he might have gotten out himself, if we’d let him go. That was not too long before we had our adventure in the Plane of Dreams.”

“You mean that this political gamesmanship might actually be relevant?” asked Amaryllis.

“Possibly,” replied Raven. “I could imagine that Juniper was being held in a secure prison and managed to make a partial escape, only to realize that he was out of the frying pan and into the fire. From there he would be racing against time and trying to ration his resources, unlocking star magic only to realize that there was an interdiction, — I have a lot of practice from worrying about Uther. Everrett always said that I was a good storyteller.” She sighed, perhaps thinking about her fallen friends.

“And you still think that we should wait?” asked Amaryllis. “You still think we’re helpless?”

“By all means, fill the time,” said Raven. “Give him a gift to come home to, in the form of having settled what you can settle.” She shrugged. “I plan to do the same, I’ve just beaten my head against the wall too many times with Uther to not have been inured to it.”

Amaryllis went back to her planning, not feeling much better for having had that discussion. Juniper was almost certainly alive, and he would almost certainly be back, but she would struggle and fight all the same. Maybe after the sixth or seventh time this happened, she would feel differently, when they were in their thirties and had been through so many adventures that this one was just a memory, not unique, interesting, or personal. Until that time, she would go on.

“The trial will be today,” said Rosemallow the next morning. The three of them were having breakfast together, just after dawn. Amaryllis had waited for Juniper to contact her through the soul link, but eventually she’d been tired from a long day, and knew that every hour spent waiting up would have to be stolen from the next day. She checked her own soul on waking up, but saw nothing through the established channels, though that might have just meant that he was still unconscious or sedated, or had been under time pressure.

“Today?” asked Amaryllis, her fork frozen halfway to her mouth. The food was in a style common to the Court, heavy on labor and with a wide variety of delicate ingredients. There were a half dozen individual dishes, though as it was breakfast, they were served on larger plates to take from, rather than in six individual courses.

“Yes, today,” said Rosemallow. “Unfortunately, I wasn’t able to move it from the War Council, which means that we’ll start at a distinct disadvantage, but the War Council is large, and —”

“You couldn’t have pushed it back?” asked Amaryllis.

“It would have been difficult,” replied Rosemallow, frowning at the interruption. Interruptions were Not Done. “The issue of your desertion has been put off for quite some time, which Phlox is claiming is a result of attempting and failing to contact you once it became known that you were, in fact, alive, and later, when your location became known to the Host.”

“I received no letters, nor any communication from anyone, until Sweet William came to speak with me on behalf of the Draconic Confederacy,” said Amaryllis. “Plus whatever you want to say that we privately wrote to each other. But I suppose that’s obvious.”

“We’ll fight it,” said Rosemallow. “Unfortunately, the matter is going to be brought before the War Council, which is where we would object to their fabrication, and at that point, the War Council is likely to hold a vote on whether to delay the hearing to another day. I anticipate that we’ll lose that vote, simply in the name of getting on with things. Your time away from the Court will be held against you. That’s virtually unavoidable, as it’s the premise of the trial.”

“How likely are we to lose?” asked Amaryllis.

“Fairly unlikely,” said Rosemallow. “Dispreferable terms are more likely, but I wouldn’t call that losing. Outright success that gets both of us everything we want is virtually impossible, unless you have a trump card you’ve been holding which you foolishly kept from me.”

Rosemallow was right. The most easily foreseeable loss scenario was that Amaryllis would be forced to serve two years in the Host, without any kind of special accommodation. That was unacceptable for a number of reasons, the two biggest being the amount of time it would take and the fact that it would put her in a position to be murdered. Beyond that, there might be some seizure of the assets that were held in trust as compensation for the technical desertion, or another remedy that the War Council decided on which would be terrible for Amaryllis, Miunun, or the Council of Arches. At the far extreme end, they might order another trial by adversity for her, which wouldn’t be entirely without precedent.

And winning? Well, their position wasn’t great, Amaryllis knew that, especially because she was entirely guilty of the crime she was being tried for. Because the plain facts were so incredibly hard to dispute — Amaryllis had not, in fact, made any effort whatsoever to join the Host — that left an argument that there existed a set of facts which should rightfully mitigate the consequences of the crime. Amaryllis wasn’t sure how that argument would be received. Rosemallow claimed that this trial would be essentially political in nature, more a result of what happened behind the scenes than what anyone might say in front of the War Council, but Amaryllis was alternately worried and hopeful that the evidence and arguments put forward could persuade her family to vote against their own economic and political interests.

The War Council was one of the largest in the Lost King’s Court, with a full fifty members. By itself, it hardly ever did anything, with almost all of the work of military governance being handled by subcouncils. With the Empire of Common Cause providing a measure of stability, there hadn’t been much cause for war in the past few decades, though of course there were still uses for a small standing army, and the War Council often concerned itself with various aspects of war preparedness.

Council meetings were held in the rooms of Greychapel, a large building that was even larger on the inside. Most of these meetings were held in rooms that hewed to function more closely than to form, with security in place to ensure that the meetings were private, water and a small bit of food, adequate lighting, and little in the way of embellishments. The focus, after all, was on the information and arguments that were being brought forward, and everything else was secondary. Amaryllis had spent a large portion of her time before leaving Anglecynn at Greychapel, taking notes in council meetings and occasionally getting into arguments or offering suggestions and reports. As a general rule, junior members of the Court who held council seats were expected to sit and listen rather than dive in head first, hoping to get a feel for the culture and rules before they made any serious mistakes, but Amaryllis had adapted quickly and not made many missteps. She had grown to like the utilitarian nature of those anonymous, interchangeable rooms at Greychapel, even if the actual process of legislative and executive functioning was a little dirty.

The trial, by contrast, was held in one of the large, ornate rooms of Greychapel, with the seats arranged in a semi-circle and layered as in a stadium. The ceiling was a dome, with a fresco Uther himself had painted, depicting a small team of men and women fighting off horrors of all kinds, though it wasn’t ‘real’ in the sense that it didn’t seem to correspond to anything that had actually happened. Uther was an accomplished artist, as he was accomplished at many things, but this was one of the only frescos that he’d found the time to do. The seats of the room were upholstered with some exotic leather, while the majority of the carvings that served as trim were gold-plated. Even the lighting itself was expensive, created by radiant stones tucked away in various places around the trim. A pair of vibration mages were stationed in the room to modulate sound, a pair of warders were on the lookout for unexpected magic, and Armateurs were stationed at regular intervals around the room, managing to look at least a little bit like decoration rather than a defense force.

Looking around at the assembled princes and princesses from a seat in the benches, Amaryllis couldn’t help but think that a bomb going off in this room would result in a significant improvement to the kingdom.

A number of the seats were empty, likely a result of the fact that the War Council had been called with so little notice. Most of the Lost King’s Court lived in Caledwich, especially if they had a position on a council, but it wasn’t unusual for members to temporarily vacate their seat for various reasons, even when they were still technically required, placing their votes by telepresence entads, relayed by phone, or mailed in as the situation required. The reduced numbers of the council wouldn’t really matter one way or another, except insofar as the missing members had their own allegiances.

Amaryllis was relegated to a small area next to the main seating, a gallery where various witnesses, employees, and subordinates were kept. Whatever witnesses the prosecution would call, assuming they were going to call some of them, were being kept elsewhere for the time being, the better to maintain some element of surprise.

As Amaryllis watched, the members of the Court with telepresence were slowly brought up. There were very few methods that allowed instant communication between remote places, especially ad hoc, which meant that entads were left to fill the job. Distance communication was rare in entads, but not overly so, and assistants were left setting up whatever was required for those. In certain cases it was as simple as a thick metal ring that needed to be set in place, which projected up a small hologram, or a bust that would be brought to life by entad magic, looking and speaking for someone thousands of miles away. There were others that were more complicated, like a bunny that was released from a cage and then anointed with oil before taking on a slight glow that indicated someone would be using it to speak. There were six of those altogether, stand-ins used for those who were working or living abroad.

People gradually began to take their seats, and Amaryllis willed herself to be calm and collected. The last time she’d been in front of a council, answering for wrongdoing, it hadn’t gone well for her, and this trial was obviously calling forth some of the trauma of realizing that no one was going to save her, that she was going to have everything stripped from her before being sent to an exclusion zone where she’d assumed she would die.

If they sentenced her to another trial by adversity, she would be very much inclined to kill them all and be done with it. She wouldn’t do it unless it was actually beneficial to the party, but if her family kept deciding that they wanted her dead, it would be fairly easy to make the argument that killing them was beneficial. Not all of them, either, just the worst twenty or thirty percent, which included all her current enemies. These were not terribly mature thoughts, she would readily admit that, but it did make her feel better to think that if she could get Juniper back, their combined firepower might be high enough to wipe out these people arrayed against her.

There was one welcome and familiar face on the War Council, a recent addition: Lisianthus. She didn’t so much as look at Amaryllis, and Amaryllis let her eyes quietly pass over Lisi. It was hardly a secret to anyone that Lisi was close to Rosemallow, but it was better that no one knew how close, as that could impact how Lisi’s contributions to the proceedings were perceived.

Phlox was one of the last to take her seat, which was right next to Onion’s. The two of them were one of the reasons that the War Council wasn’t a preferred place to hold the trial. Onion wore the same full plate and many rings he’d worn the day before, but Phlox was dressed more elegantly, in a rich purple dress that came halfway up her neck and covered her arms to her wrists. She also wore an eclectic selection of jewelry, some of which were probably entads, the others there for symmetry or to make a statement about what she thought of austerity. She was in her late seventies, hair grey and with more than her fair share of wrinkles, and beyond that, she moved slowly, with less of the poise and grace that Amaryllis remembered her having even ten years ago. Some of her royal bearing had been worn away by time. Still, she wasn’t to be underestimated. She and Onion were second cousins and thick as thieves.

Phlox banged down her gavel, and after a few words the session began in earnest.

The first two witnesses were just to establish that a crime had, in fact, taken place. The first was a member of the Finance Council, who spent a few minutes speaking about that first trial and sentencing, which thankfully didn’t go on all that long. The second witness was a member of the Host, a man who had both overseen the drop and waited patiently at the base for any survivors. He talked briefly about the historic importance of the trial by adversity, which Amaryllis didn’t feel was needed, but otherwise stuck to matters of fact, including how long it normally took survivors to complete their trial, their entry into the Host, and some discussion on when they had given Amaryllis up for dead.

After that, Amaryllis was called. She walked into the center of the room, steeling herself, and stood at attention. She was wearing a tastefully conservative dress rather than armor, in service of projecting the right kind of attitude. Many members of the council would have made up their mind before things began, but there were votes to be won, and Rosemallow still seemed to think that public opinion was a concern, even if the council had made up their minds. The War Room had an upper balcony where the public was allowed to sit, warded so that they could make no sound, and even given the expedited trial, it was packed.

“Amaryllis Penndraig, for the crime of desertion, how do you plead?” asked Phlox.

“Mu,” said Amaryllis. It was a word that Uther had coined, often used in cases like these to challenge assumptions. Invoking it here was unlikely to work, but it had to be tried.

“Clarify, please,” replied Phlox.

“Madame Chairman, the wording of the directive signed when I was sentenced to trial by adversity gave a concrete definition for when the trial was to be considered completed, which was the trigger condition for my entry into the Host,” said Amaryllis. “The precise wording used was that when I ‘reached the edge of the exclusion zone’ I would be considered to have completed the trial and would join the Host for a period of two years. As I left via entad from Silmar City, I never reached the edge of the exclusion zone, and am thus not subject to that trigger.”

Onion stood from his seat beside Phlox. “Madame Chairman, I move that Amaryllis’ suggestion that her trial by adversity has not yet ended be quashed under the obvious chicanery rule.” He sat back down as soon as the sentence was out of his mouth.

“Second,” replied a distant cousin.

“Council, are you ready for the question?” asked Phlox.

But obviously, the council wasn’t ready for the question, because in a council as large as this one, only a completely pro forma motion could be dismissed that quickly. People took their turns standing, making their own arguments or requests for information, which eventually looked to be leading down a rabbit hole when Onion took the floor again.

“Madame Chairman, I move the previous question,” he said.

“Second,” replied the same distant cousin, Willow. Her role here was, clearly, to second anything that Onion said. That wasn’t strictly necessary, given that Phlox was chair, but it did give a thin veneer of impartiality to Phlox.

“Is the council ready for the question of whether Amaryllis’ plea of ‘mu’ be rejected in this instance under the obvious chicanery rule?” asked Phlox. Another member of the council stood, but Phlox waved him back down. “We’ll first vote to end debate on the question, requiring a two-thirds majority.”

Amaryllis was starting to get a read of the room and the particulars of each member. She knew all their names, though some she hadn’t really met. She had two stalwart supporters, Iris and Lisi, both of whom had been trying their best to get this relatively hopeless gambit to work, but they’d said their bit already. Then there were two family members who seemed to just be in it for wanting something to say, Sorrel and Camellia. The rest hadn’t spoken, and while Amaryllis knew as much as Rosemallow had been willing to share about their loyalties, Amaryllis wasn’t counting anyone out quite yet.

The vote to end discussion easily passed, but the question of whether her ‘mu’ answer was ‘obvious chicanery’ came much closer than Amaryllis had thought it would: there were forty-one members present, and the vote only had twenty-five ayes. Obviously a ruling that her desertion wasn’t a crime because she’d never finished her trial would put her in an awkward position (necessitating a return to the Risen Lands, perhaps), but if the vote had gone her way, she would have taken it.

“The ayes have it,” said Phlox. “Amaryllis, do you have a new plea?”

It was tempting to say ‘mu’ again, but the other methods of claiming there was no crime were on even shakier areas of technicality, not worth trying when she was trying to maintain the pleasure of the council. “I plead not guilty by reasons of necessity and duress,” said Amaryllis.

“Necessity and duress are two separate defenses,” replied Phlox. “As a point of order, you will need to choose between the two.”

“A defendant is allowed multiple affirmative defenses if the nature of their defense requires such to cover two or more different areas of the crime,” said Amaryllis. “As desertion is an ongoing crime, covering the entirety of the time when I did not report, I believe it qualifies by the standards used to set precedent.”

Another round followed, with the motion first put to a vote, which required more interjections, clarifications, and considerations, and then a real vote once enough time had passed and Phlox’s gauge of the room was that they would close further comments. The chair had an extraordinary amount of power within the council, as they chose what would be brought to a vote and who would get the floor (among other things), but they were constrained by the need to follow procedure, else they face the consequences. Of late, those consequences had been rather lacking, in part because it was difficult to enforce fairness. Beyond that, the attack at Caledwich Castle had shaken Amaryllis’ faith that others would follow even the rather permissive informal rules.

The vote went in Amaryllis’ favor, this time by a wide margin, which she was thankful for, even though it never should have been up for a vote in the first place, given how solid her legal ground was.

“Then proceed, Amaryllis, and put forward your argument for why your desertion was both necessary and under duress. I’ll remind the council that the argument of duress requires the defendant to prove beyond a reasonable doubt that they were coerced by force or threats, and the argument of necessity requires passing a burden of presenting clear and convincing evidence. The floor is yours. Will ten minutes suffice?”

“I’ll do my best,” replied Amaryllis. “Esteemed council, when I was initially sentenced to trial by adversity, I had every intention of doing my best to complete the trial and join the Host for two years of service. However, when I landed in the Risen Lands, I was attacked by a number of young men who had also made the drop, which is quite unusual for the trial. From the coloring of their hair, I took them to be members of the Fuchsia Coterie. It was only on my return to Anglecynn that I learned the matter had been seen and settled, implicating a number of low-level officials, though I don’t believe it was discovered who had paid them. At the time, I believed it to be an assassination attempt, and rather than going toward the edge of the exclusion, I went toward Silmar City, where I had an entad that would allow me to leave. At this time, I’d like to enter into evidence the entirety of the proceedings over the matter of the Fuchsia Coterie being dropped into the Risen Lands, which I don’t think I need to mention constitutes a violation of the special exemption Anglecynn enjoys with the Empire.”

No one was actually going to read the thick stack of papers, given that the facts weren’t in dispute, but it was still good to have evidence ready, and to make a show that it was in your possession. Rumor had it that Uther had bluffed his way through a number of meetings by presenting stacks of blank paper, as if daring his ideological opponents to spend the effort wading through it all.

“Point of evidence,” said Onion.

“I yield the floor,” Amaryllis replied, because Phlox would have made her yield anyway.

“The Fuchsia Coterie are paramilitary,” he said. “How many of them did you see there?”

“A dozen,” replied Amaryllis. “But that’s a guess.”

“And what were they doing?” he asked.

“I saw them kill a number of the others involved in the trial,” said Amaryllis. “It’s speculation on my part, but I believe they were killing witnesses.”

“And they attempted to kill you?” asked Onion.

“They did,” replied Amaryllis with a nod.

“You have no military training, is that correct?” asked Onion.

“I trained briefly in self-defense after my mother’s death, and received special instruction at the Athenaeum of Quills and Blood,” replied Amaryllis. “Other than that, no, I have no combat or military training.”

“How did you survive?” asked Onion, which was likely the point of that questioning.

“Initially, I hid, and then I was fortunate enough to come across someone I thought I could trust. He was familiar with me from the Future Leaders of Anglecynn campaign and wanted to help me,” said Amaryllis. “There was, frankly, a large amount of luck involved. With his help —”

“This would be Juniper Smith?” asked Onion.

“That’s correct,” replied Amaryllis, watching him. He gave nothing away, not that she’d expected he would. “With his help, I was able to remove the souls of the dead and use them as fuel for a soulcycle I’d repaired, which we used to make the trip to Silmar City. Once we were past the landing zone, we didn’t encounter anyone else, and the only difficulty was in getting past the undead and finding provisions.”

“What weapons did you use?” asked Onion, not bothering to ask again for a point of evidence.

“We used whatever we could find,” said Amaryllis. “Comfort was largely picked over from the evacuation, later looting, and the trials. Based on the quality of their weapons, I assume that the attackers had a cache dropped or teleported in prior to the start of the trial, though that’s not clear to me.”

“Did you use void weapons?” asked Onion.

“Yes,” replied Amaryllis. “I was able to make a crude void rifle from leftover parts. I will preemptively say, for the benefit of the council, that while use of void weaponry is prohibited by Anglecynn law, it is customary for trial by adversity to include a suspension of legal consequences. Uncle Onion, I believe you’re well aware.”

“I am,” replied Onion, not smiling. “You may continue.”

“The endpoint of the entad was in a family home near Barren Jewel,” said Amaryllis, continuing on. “It was supposed to be a secure redoubt, and we were able to recover some entads that had been left in storage there for dire circumstances, but a local criminal gold mage had placed additional wards to trap anyone who entered. He took me hostage and interrogated me with a revision mage, until I was rescued by Juniper and two others he had recruited. At this point it would be prudent to enter into evidence a news report from Barren Jewel detailing the deaths of a number of people in the upper floors of a building called Trifles Tower.”

“Point of evidence,” said Phlox. “Once you were in Barren Jewel, you had the opportunity to send a letter back to Anglecynn explaining your predicament. Why didn’t you?” Her voice still managed to be sharp, despite her age, and sitting there, she’d regained some of the bearing she’d been lacking when she’d first entered.

“During the time I was in Barren Jewel, I was held hostage, given food and water but otherwise not allowed to write letters. After I was freed from the gold mage, it was a matter of minutes before we used a second entad obtained from the family home to go elsewhere.”

“And it’s your contention that during this entire time, you were acting under duress?” asked Phlox.

“Yes,” replied Amaryllis.

“In terms of timeline, this would bring us up to when, exactly?” asked Phlox.

“Nineteen days after the trial began,” replied Amaryllis.

“I believe it would be a waste of this council’s time for you to recount how you spent the entirety of your time away from the Court,” said Phlox. “Let it be known that for a number of months you were living on the Isle of Poran as a citizen of the Republic of Miunun. At that time, were you under duress?”

“No, Madame Chairman,” replied Amaryllis. “But my plea was duress and necessity, and at the time, I believed that return to Anglecynn would be a greater evil. The reason —”

“When did you feel you were no longer under duress?” asked Phlox.

“Mu,” said Amaryllis. “I have always felt that return to Anglecynn would represent a threat to my life, and the lives of my companions. Further, I’ve felt that mere knowledge of my existence by certain members of the Court would inevitably result in either threats of violence or outright attacks.” She held up a hand to forestall objections. “I’m not claiming that for the past few months duress was a compelling argument informing my decision not to report in to the Host, only that duress was present.”

Phlox let out a sigh. “Then at what point did you feel that the overriding concern was necessity, rather than duress, and what is the nature of necessity you’re claiming?”

“Approximately twenty days after I left the Risen Lands, I was attacked in the streets of Boastre Vino by Larkspur Prentiss and a few people accompanying him, with no attempts at diplomacy or warning on their part,” said Amaryllis.

The council erupted into conversation at that, which was almost immediately shut down by the two vibration mages.

“I suppose you have some evidence of this bold claim?” asked Phlox.

“Little enough,” said Amaryllis. “I’d like to enter into evidence a police report from Boastre Vino, including witness testimonies, a secondary report from Uniquities detailing the events of that fight prior to Larkspur’s unfortunate death, and a report from Anglecynn’s Foreign Security Office, included primarily for the sake of completeness, as it details Larkspur’s movements in the days prior to his death.”

“You’re smearing a dead man’s name,” said Onion.

“Point of order,” Amaryllis replied. “Onion is speaking without having been granted the floor and not following the rules of procedure for the trial.”

“Onion, request the floor if you have something to say,” replied Phlox. “I think it would go without saying that Amaryllis is making extraordinary claims, and that the only person who could possibly offer a solid rebuttal is deceased, thus beyond questioning.”

“I’ll leave it to the council to decide,” replied Amaryllis. “It should be clear to everyone here that Larkspur would have had motive to —”

“This line of comment is finished,” said Phlox.

“Point of order,” said Amaryllis, voice firm and slightly raised. “The chair cannot close a line of comment except with a two-third majority of the council, so the matter should be put to a vote.”

Phlox was clearly unhappy with that, but she was in a procedural bind. Council meetings of this size Followed the Rules, and a chair who shut down her enemies would find herself booted fairly quickly. At worst, the council could rebel against their chair and declare a mistrial.

“Continue on,” said Phlox, not wanting to risk a vote she must have assumed would go against her. “Show respect for the dead.”

“I meant no disrespect,” replied Amaryllis. “Larkspur’s actions in and around Boastre Vino are suspect, even in the report that comes from his former office. When I speak to motive, I don’t mean to imply that he was lacking in character, only that there was a clear and obvious reason for him to want me dead, whether that’s what he wanted or not. In the event of my death, my entads would have passed to him and his wife Hyacinth, representing somewhere in the region of thirty million obols a year income.”

“That’s enough,” said Phlox. “You’ve made your point. When did you learn of Larkspur’s death?”

“I left Boastre Vino shortly after we escaped,” replied Amaryllis. “I didn’t read about his death in the news until more than a month after it happened.”

“Point of inquiry,” said Onion. “You didn’t answer the question.”

“I apologize,” said Amaryllis. “I did not learn of his death until I read it in the news more than a month after it had happened. Until that point, I was under the impression that I was evading magical detection.” It wasn’t good to make a bald-faced lie in front of the council, especially not when three of your companions had recently been kidnapped and were presumably being pumped for information.

“Point of information,” said Onion. “At this moment I have in custody one Juniper Smith, one Oorang Solace, and one Pallida Sade. Mr. Smith and Miss Solace have testified to your involvement in Larkspur’s death.”

Again there was a roar of conversation from the council, which the vibration mages immediately shut down.

“As a point of order, this is a trial on the charge of desertion by Amaryllis Penndraig,” said Phlox. “Whatever other crimes she is guilty of, they fall outside the purview of this current council session, and likely outside the jurisdiction of the War Council. They will need to be dealt with at a later date.”

“I will naturally be needing a transcript of the interrogation,” said Amaryllis. She felt like ice was running through her veins. “I’ll also need to know the legal basis for the arrest of —”

“The three who were arrested were suspected of crimes against Anglecynn,” Onion replied. “Their arrest is a matter for the kingdom. You’re owed nothing.”

“I am a citizen of the Republic of Miunun, as are the others —” Amaryllis began.

“Your so-called nation is not recognized by Anglecynn,” replied Onion. “Juniper Smith has not made a formal renunciation of his citizenship. The other two claim no citizenship aside from Miunun. This matter was cleared with members of the Intraimperial Council and the Legal Council.”

‘Members’ was a weasel word, meant to be skipped past so that people might think he’d put the matter through the councils, which almost assuredly hadn’t happened. And there was something else he’d said that was almost certainly a slip: neither Pallida nor Solace actually claimed citizenship in Miunun. It wasn’t clear proof that he was full of shit, but Amaryllis’ heart began to soar at the first hint that Juniper wasn’t actually tucked away at a black site somewhere, and that this questioning wasn’t so dire for her as it appeared.

“Reporting testimony secondhand is hearsay,” said Amaryllis. “You’ve removed a dear friend and valuable ally from me, then reported on what he said with no method of confirmation by this council or chance for cross-examination. Given the severity of the accusation leveled against me, and that this is a resolvable matter of fact, I move for the trial to be adjourned until the witness, Juniper Smith, can be produced.”

“Second,” came Lisi’s voice.

“Point of order,” said Phlox. “The revelations and accusations regarding Larkspur are a sideshow, and while it’s clear that we won’t be able to come to a vote on the matter of desertion, we might still be able to drive further to the truth of the matter regarding Amaryllis’ actions and her alleged desertion. With that point established, we can go to a vote.”

Amaryllis would dearly have loved to stall for another day, but the vote didn’t go her way, again by a slim enough margin that it suggested she had more supporters than she would have suspected.

Phlox cleared her throat and straightened her notes, and it was obvious that she was savoring a victory. “With the matter of Larkspur tabled for the time being, I believe, for the purposes of this trial, we need to establish the necessity element of your defense. You may proceed.”

“As I said, I’ve felt elements of duress during my entire time away from Anglecynn, owing to the multiple attempts on my life,” said Amaryllis. “Necessity came when I met two individuals in the course of our travels who each provided overriding concerns, above and beyond a return to Anglecynn and fulfillment of my obligation to the Host. The first was Raven Masters, the last of Uther’s Knights, who came with a prophetic warning. While I had the opportunity to return to Anglecynn then, given that she had taken a role as my protector, we felt that such a return would hamper our group, given both the cost and time required for travel, and the likelihood that I would be detained, possibly even permanently. The first of the directives that Raven gave us was to go to Li’o, where she feared a monster of incredible size and strength would appear. When it did, we needed to be available to kill it, which is precisely what we did.”

“A bold claim,” said Phlox.

“Raven is available,” said Amaryllis. “I can call her as a witness. More definitive proof of what happened in Li’o will be difficult to come by, but there are numerous eyewitnesses to the entad we used, and the aid we provided to the citizens of Li’o, and I don’t believe that this matter of fact is in question.”

“Then your testimony is tabled for the time being so we can call in Raven Masters,” said Phlox.

That wasn’t entirely unanticipated, but Amaryllis didn’t particularly want Raven to be speaking to the council, not when she would have to talk her way around the truth. They exchanged positions smoothly, with Amaryllis returning to the gallery, where she was finally able to drink some water and rest for a moment.

“State your name,” said Phlox.

“Raven Masters,” replied Raven. Unlike Amaryllis, she was in full battle gear, the better to demonstrate her position of privilege and power. Her normally hidden banded armor was in full display, as was her sword, which was a slice of frozen time. She was impressive and imposing, save for her height and age.

“You claim to be the same Raven Masters that served as one of Uther’s Knights five hundred years ago?” asked Phlox.

“I do,” replied Raven. She was looking over the assembled War Council. She seemed bored.

“What have you been doing these past few hundred years?” asked Phlox.

“That’s classified,” said Raven.

“Classified by what authority?” asked Phlox.

“Uther Penndraig,” replied Raven. “And by classifying authorities that must themselves remain classified, for the good of Aerb.”

“How and when did you come to travel with Amaryllis?” asked Phlox.

“That’s also classified,” replied Raven. “All I can say is that after Uther left, it fell to the rest of us to ensure that the world was safe for civilization.”

“Madam Chairwoman, may I have the floor?” asked Bartholomew. He was one of those rare commoners who had married into the family, and one of the even more rare commoners who had been given some measure of rights as nobility by his wife. On matters of legislation, they shared a vote. This was a fairly recent change as far as the Court went, part of an effort to appear more egalitarian, if you considered being able to marry into nobility egalitarian.

“You may,” replied Phlox.

“Miss Masters, what were you doing during the time of the Second Empire?” he asked.

“I don’t think that’s relevant,” replied Raven.

“Of course it is, it speaks to the truth of what you say,” replied Bartholomew. “If you were out saving the world, which accounts for your absence, then what were you up to during the time of tyranny and genocide that was the Second Empire?”

“I was a public figure then,” replied Raven. “I’ve been accused of a lack of action in several of my biographies, which I largely agree with. All I can say in my defense is that I didn’t have the same resources then that I do now.”

“Resources which you will maintain are classified by some nebulous classification authority?” asked Phlox.

“Yes,” replied Raven.

This wasn’t good. Raven was looking like a crank or a liar. She was meant to be bringing the full gravitas of Uther’s legacy to the proceedings, but she was treating the council as though it were beneath her. They simply hadn’t had the time to prepare everything properly beyond the broad strokes that had been in place from the night before, and Raven had very little coaching aside from the outline of the story she was supposed to tell.

“Elaborate,” whispered Amaryllis, using vibration magic to amplify her voice. The intent was to create something like tight-beam communication, but there was still some risk that they would be found out, not that it was strictly against the rules. The biggest risk was that the warders would see the vibration magic, or the vibration mages would feel it, but it was small and subtle magic, hopefully below what they would feel the need to raise an alert about.

“Much of what Uther did was secret,” said Raven. “Some of it was secret because it would have been bold and controversial at the time, and other actions were dangerous simply by their nature, beyond the fear of mass hysteria or rebellion if they were found out. Especially toward the end of his time on Aerb, operating in silence became the norm for us. Anglecynn was his kingdom, but Uther and his Knights were beyond it, tasked not just with the kingdom, but with the First Empire, with Aerb, and with the planes beyond. After Uther left, I tried my best to find him and bring him back from wherever he went, but when I failed, I was adrift. To answer the question about my involvement in the Second Empire, I was a citizen, nothing more. They wanted my endorsement, so they could pretend that there was some element of continuity, but I never gave it. I had some knowledge of what they were doing, both from the propaganda they put out and the things that were whispered to me by people in the know, but I didn’t join the resistance movements. I lived my life. When the Second Empire fell, there were tools and weapons that fell with them, and it was only then that I decided that I really should be honoring his legacy. I took those tools and weapons, some of them immensely dangerous, and used them to keep rogue threats in check, threats that this council cannot know. For that purpose, I sought out Amaryllis and Juniper.”

Amaryllis allowed herself a sigh of relief. Raven still had a look of contempt, but at least the words were more or less right. Amaryllis would have cut out everything that undermined Raven’s position as the actual heir to Uther, but that couldn’t be helped.

“Why those two?” asked Onion. He was eyeing up Raven as though trying to decide how hard it would be to kill her.

“I’ve met a great many Penndraigs over the years,” said Raven. “Of them all, Amaryllis is most like Uther. She has his decisiveness, intellect, and compassion. The only thing she’s lacking is his artistry and grace.” There were faint murmurs following that high praise, which the vibration mages allowed to go.

“And Juniper?” asked Onion.

Raven hesitated. Amaryllis had seen, as soon as Onion said his name, that this would be trouble. Objections from someone outside the council were forbidden though, so she had little choice but to hope that someone would speak up on her behalf. “Juniper is special,” she said. “Uther had the ability to pick up new abilities in a frighteningly short amount of time. Juniper has the same ability, if a bit more limited.”

Amaryllis suppressed a groan. Once Juniper had been brought up, it was necessary to explain him, at least a little bit, she understood that, but Raven could have leaned on similarities to Uther, or a personal connection, or something like that. If people knew about Juniper, they would want to test him, and the nature of his character sheet meant that there were some tests that he couldn’t pass. This testimony meant that people could potentially find weaknesses to dig their fingers into, both literal and metaphorical.

“More bold claims, used to support other bold claims,” said Onion.

“If you have him in a prison somewhere, you should already know he’s making these claims,” Raven replied. “He should be brought forward as a witness, given how heavily he’s involved in this.”

The questioning went on for some time after this, but Raven stonewalled them, primarily because for most of the questions, she would have to reveal the existence of the Infinite Library. In typical fashion, a number of members of the council didn’t seem to accept that there really were things that they weren’t meant to know. Onion had a few pointed questions for her about the Second Empire, but Raven was sticking to the awkward truth, which was that she had friends on both sides of the ideological schism that had happened in the wake of Uther’s disappearance. Some of those friends were instrumental in the founding and operation of the early Second Empire. The digressions were mostly to call into question Raven’s credibility and character, which they weren’t terribly effective at: the Second Empire had left its scars on Aerb, but the zeal against it wasn’t what it once had been.

“I think that’s enough,” said Phlox, twenty minutes later. “If the witness cannot or will not answer, then the rest we’ll get is mostly background or historical curiosity. We’ll now vote on the closing of questioning this witness,” said Phlox.

This proceeded without much further deliberation, and Amaryllis once again stood before the council.

“It was interesting testimony, I will give it that,” said Phlox. “As an argument for necessity, it requires an extraordinary amount of faith in both you and Raven, faith that I personally find somewhat lacking at the moment.” This kind of soap-boxing was skirting the rules of decorum; it wasn’t fit for the chair to extemporize on the issue at hand, especially during a trial. “You said that it came down to two people. Would you like to call your other witness now?”

“No,” replied Amaryllis. “My other witness is Oorang Solace, who is currently being held by Anglecynn for unspecified crimes.”

“And what was her role in keeping you from your duty?” asked Phlox, frowning slightly.

“She found me through a powerful predictive magic,” said Amaryllis. “Once she did, she revealed what she knew to me and swore me to secrecy. Part of the reason that we’d been trying to stay hidden from scrutiny was protecting that secret. It was of vital importance. It’s a secret which Onion by now surely knows.”

Onion was stone-faced. “The princess is surely aware that I can’t speak to matters of national security,” he finally said.

“Solace is the last living druid,” said Amaryllis. “She has, on her person, an entad which contains a locus in its extradimensional space, one which survived the Second Empire. I might be turning her against me by revealing this now, but I fear that if I say nothing, she and the locus might disappear forever.”

Of all of the gambits she was employing today, this one was the most dangerous. It wasn’t clear that Onion actually did have Solace, and revealing the existence of the locus was, of course, likely to make Solace upset. But on balance, this seemed a better path to go down, not just because it enormously complicated and improved her necessity defense, but because it would help to raise her stature as heir to Uther.

Once the vibration mages had quieted everyone down, Phlox spoke.

“Amaryllis has made yet another bold claim,” said Phlox. “This one, however is not a matter of opinion or testimony, but instead, a matter of fact. I propose that Oorang Solace be brought before this council by tomorrow, when this trial can continue. I will stipulate that she be brought with her entads, the better to ascertain the truth of this matter.”

Onion didn’t look happy, but he rarely did. Amaryllis had some hope that this was a sign of dissension in the ranks, or at least a lack of coordination, but she wasn’t going to hold her breath.

After a fair amount of discussion, the vote finally took place, and the War Council decided that it would adjourn, meeting again tomorrow with both Solace and Juniper present before the council to give testimony, to the extent that they were willing to cooperate with the needs of the trial.

It felt like a victory, but Amaryllis wasn’t sure that it would hold. There was one big, obvious question still on her mind: where was Juniper?

She got her answer later that night.

Common Law

We finally reunited at that awkward time when you’re not sure whether it’s late at night or early morning. I’d done a values ping on Amaryllis, and she’d responded back, rapidly moving values in the low-level range so that we could have a crude channel of communication that wouldn’t be too disruptive. Our method basically allowed a single letter at a time, which was painfully slow, but it was enough to communicate our respective locations, that we were all okay, and after that, to organize the meet up.

Amaryllis came in with the teleportation key, targeting a section of railroad tracks and bringing Grak with her. If we were going back to Caledwich with the key, that meant either Raven or Grak had to stay behind, and Amaryllis had made her choice, picking the utility of warding over raw combat prowess. Part of the reason that we had to meet so late was that it took us time to book it over to where Amaryllis had a path in, which involved a long car ride and then a brief stint where Solace turned us into wolves.

“What happened?” asked Amaryllis, once she was recovered from using the key.

“Can I say, first, that I’m extremely glad both of you are alive?” I asked.

“Pleasantries later,” replied Amaryllis.

“We’re happy you’re all safe,” said Grak.

“Is Raven alright?” I asked.

“She’s fine,” replied Amaryllis. “We’ve already linked back up. She said that it was two members of the court that took you. How’d you escape from wherever you were?”

“I woke up in a cell,” I replied. “Your cousin Yarrow was apparently a secret soul mage, and when he peeped at my soul, he went catatonic. Your other cousin, Zinnia, went ape shit trying to figure out what was happening and get me to undo it. She brought in Solace and shot her in the head, then brought in Pallida and started torturing her, and when I finally reversed the damage to Yarrow, she left to go speak with him, presumably about him soulfucking me or me soulfucking him. I was in entad manacles, used Essentialism 60 to slip out of them, then the same thing to get past the wards, and we broke out. I killed half of the people and the rest surrendered. Pallida killed them when I was out of the room.”

“He soulfucked Yarrow, then Zinnia,” said Pallida. “And he was going to leave them alive and planning to release them back into Anglecynn at some point.”

“Everyone at the black site is dead?” asked Amaryllis. “You killed a prince and princess of Anglecynn?” For whatever reason, she was directing this at me.

“Pallida killed them,” I said. “I was going to try to figure out a way to let them live.”

“If you soulfuck them, then letting them live isn’t a good idea,” said Amaryllis. “But everyone there is dead, those two included?”

“Yes,” replied Pallida.

“Fuck,” said Amaryllis. “Either Onion doesn’t know, or he’s bluffing well.”

“He doesn’t know, or he didn’t this morning,” I replied. “I have an entad in my ear that I can use to talk to him. He thinks that Yarrow still has it. We were supposed to teleport him intel and didn’t, so he knows something is up, not sure if he’ll have sent people to the black site yet.”

“Fucking Christ,” said Amaryllis. “We’re in the middle of my desertion trial. Onion was going to bring you and Solace in as witnesses.”

“Wait, we were only gone a day, right?” I asked. “Day and a half, depending on how you want to count it. You’re on trial?”

Amaryllis nodded. “They rushed it,” she said. “That doesn’t mean that it’s not going to work out for them.” She turned to Solace. “I told them about the locus. I’m sorry, but it was the firmest and most verifiable out.”

Solace shrugged. “I suppose the time was right.”

“You’re not upset?” asked Amaryllis, eyebrows knit.

“Not particularly,” replied Solace. “I won’t, of course, be submitting to any kind of trial, nor will the locus be poked and prodded to satisfy your courts.”

Amaryllis winced. “Understood, though that does make things more difficult.”

“What do you need from me?” I asked.

Amaryllis bit her lip. “Right now, I need you to disappear.” She shook her head. “Fuck, if I had known you’d escaped, I would have done things completely differently. We could have used you to feed false information back to Onion and Phlox. Now they’re going to try to pull you out of the black site and find everyone there dead.”

“Actually, no,” said Pallida. “We took the bodies with us, they’re in the bottle.”

“And I cleaned what blood I could find,” said Solace.

“There are probably traces that we were there,” I said. “But we did take some time to cover our tracks.”

“I don’t think it passes a sniff test,” said Amaryllis. “Onion knows that you were taken during the altercation, he knows where you were taken, so if he goes there and finds — Jesus, everyone, a whole crew of guards?”

“Like I said, about half of them surrendered once their mages and superiors were taken out,” I replied. “Er, less than that, call it a third left alive.” I’d been forgetting the ones in the hallways.

“Onion had some legal pretense,” said Amaryllis. “I don’t think that it will hold, given that it’s got to be a fabrication, but I don’t know that we have enough leverage to call him on it, and it feels like the kind of thing that would get tied up in court for months if not years.”

“Unlike a desertion trial,” I replied. “Which can apparently happen in the space of a day.”

“They’ve been planning it for a while,” said Amaryllis, shaking her head. “I think that it was a measure they were keeping in their back pocket, and when things spiraled out of control, they wanted something that would soak attention and political capital. The trial might not go their way, but it seems likely that they’re going to try forcing me into the Host.”

“So which people are left to kill?” I asked. “Hyacinth is a given, Onion is a given, who else? Phlox?” I hadn’t met her, but I hadn’t heard good things. “That look you’re giving me seems to suggest that we’re not at the point of assassination just yet, for some unfathomable reason.” Amaryllis gave me a hard stare. “They kidnapped me, tried to torture me, tried to kill me, shot Solace in the head —”

“A druid acts from the heart, not the head,” said Solace with a happy smile.

“These people are monsters,” I finished. “I don’t give a rancid shit about the legal pretenses or the state of political capital. I’m out for blood.”

Amaryllis grit her teeth for a moment. “I understand your feelings. But at this point, putting Onion to the sword would be tantamount to calling the entirety of the Court down on you.”

“And together, we can take them,” I replied. “Not a ton of combat mages among the Court, the Armateurs are mooks, the most that I would be worried about are powerful entads, hidden research projects, secret memetics and whatever else is hiding in dark corners, and okay, now that I say it out loud, it might be a problem.”

“And it wouldn’t just be the Court, it would mean making an enemy of the Empire,” said Amaryllis. “Unless we can do it in a deniable way, we’re not slicing our way through the Court.”

“Okay,” I replied. “So I call in Bethel.”

“Juniper, no,” said Amaryllis.

“She could and would do it,” I said, folding my arms. “We probably wouldn’t even need to talk with her about it, and then she could fuck off back to wherever Val is keeping her stashed..”

“I understand that you’re feeling angry about how things happened,” Amaryllis began.

“Yeah, sorry if I’m a little hard done by about being drugged, robbed, and tortured,” I said. “I guess I’m just being wildly irrational about the whole thing.”

“There are rules for staging a successful coup,” said Amaryllis. “You need to target all the right people so there’s no resistance, you need international acceptance, and you need the appearance of legitimacy.”

“I don’t give a shit about that,” I replied. “We’re not taking over Anglecynn, we’re just killing a few people who need killing and then moving on.”

“You’d be fine plunging Anglecynn into a civil war?” asked Amaryllis. “Forget for a moment that people would come after us, you’d be fine with the shockwaves that it would send through both Anglecynn and the Court to know that there’s someone out there just killing high-level members of the government?”

I clenched my hands into fists. “Alright,” I said, letting out a breath. “Fine. You have a point. I’ll even accept that you have several points. We should probably not actually go in guns blazing and shoot all the people that I want to shoot unless we know that we can get away with it and that Anglecynn isn’t worse off than when we got here. But if you’re still here talking about having your day in court, we’re on such different planes of existence that I’m going to have to unlock star magic to reach you.”

“Har,” replied Amaryllis. Either she was losing her patience with me, or she thought showing some anger was a better tactic. “You understand you’re not invincible, right? You talk about getting knocked out and tortured, and then in the next breath you talk about going up against the full might of the Court.”

“I was serious about bringing in Bethel,” I replied.

“Val is trying to fix her, because we might need her,” said Amaryllis. “And one of the things Bethel fucking hates is being used like she’s some pistol to be pointed at someone. You’d be tearing apart all of the hard work that Val has been doing on so many different levels. Not like this. Not over a grudge, not because Onion is fucking awful and killing the people who held the blade didn’t give you the satisfaction you thought it would. That’s childish.”

We’d moved closer without really meaning to, just the result of shifting our footing or getting in closer to make a point. I felt like Amaryllis was about to hit me, which would have done fuck all, and might have been the reason she wasn’t trying to knock sense into me. She definitely seemed like she wanted to.

“Then what’s the plan?” I asked. “You go to court, get your ass handed to you, and I have to break you out, or kill a bunch of people anyway?”

“Yes,” replied Amaryllis. Her fists were clenched at her sides. “If it comes to that, yes.”

“Except nothing will have changed,” I replied. “We can play within the system and still get fucked. You know why I got knocked out by that entad? It’s because I thought we’d be fine. I thought if they were dumb enough to attack me, I would fight back with everything I had, and at least I would have followed the rules, at least I could say, after the fact, that I hadn’t breached trust. Trying to do it that way got me fuck all. I’m done being reactive. Once we’re finished in Anglecynn, — I don’t give a shit about killing Blue-in-the-Bottle, and I don’t think he’s going to be that much easier to kill than a dragon would be. And really, I don’t even think that we should bother with any of it, because we know that Fel Seed is our destination.”

“Let’s talk grand strategy when you’re less pissed off,” said Amaryllis. “In the here and now, assassination is off the table. It’s my side quest, we’re doing it my way.”

“We don’t even have a quest,” I replied.

Quest Accepted: Full Court Press - Amaryllis never wanted to return home, but now she finds herself once again embroiled in court politics, propped up on one side by her mother-figure Rosemallow and the interests of Uniquities, and set against a coalition of relatives who would really rather have her be dead. Help her to secure a future for the both of you in Anglecynn. (Companion Quest)

“You just got one,” said Amaryllis.

“Now?” asked Solace.

“What does it say?” asked Grak.

“No,” I replied. “This fucking — no, this doesn’t matter, my life isn’t going to be dictated by quest text.”

“Juniper, we’re partners,” said Amaryllis.

I hesitated for a moment. “Alright,” I replied, then read the text for her.

“That says nothing,” she said when I was finished. “If it was going to be that vague, why not give it to us months ago?”

“Comedic timing,” I replied. “Or who knows.”

“It implies a future in Anglecynn,” replied Grak. “You are unlikely to have one if you assassinate someone.”

“So … it’s a hint,” said Pallida.

“It’s a push,” I replied. “I did it when I was DMing. If two players are getting into an argument about the game, I would sometimes offer some clarification about what the quest actually was, or what they knew.”

“Then the quest is to find a place for ourselves,” said Amaryllis, frowning.

“Regardless of what the quest is, I’m not going to go through with this trial bullshit just because the Dungeon Master says that it’s possible, because first off, he’s a fucking liar, and second, he’s not my real dad.”

Amaryllis gave me a raised eyebrow, the kind that I knew from long experience meant I was speaking a bit too much Earth for her.

I sighed. “It’s this thing in Earth sitcoms and movies where there’s someone trying to be a father figure, and the kid will yell something like, ‘You’re not my real dad!’ and then storm out in the middle of an argument, I was just — he can’t tell me what to do, he can only force me to do things.”

“That’s a cruel thing to say to a surrogate father,” said Grak.

I stopped and looked at him. “I … I would have thought we were all in agreement that the Dungeon Master isn’t actually a father figure to me?”

“I meant in the abstract,” replied Grak. “As a trope.”

“But it’s a joke?” asked Pallida. “A common enough joke that it’s a thing on Earth?”

“Uh, yeah,” I replied. “Feels weird saying Earth, because it’s really just America, but yeah, the nuclear family is dying a slow death, there are lots of marriages ending in divorce, and so it comes up a lot. More as a meme than in reality, I guess. Not really on topic though.”

“Do you want to go back to arguing?” asked Amaryllis. She had cooled off, same as I had, and she was standing there with a questioning look.

“Not really,” I replied. “But that leaves us with the question of what we’re going to do.”

“You think the court is bullshit,” said Amaryllis. “I do too, it’s just a question of degree. So long as people are willing to vote mostly on the basis of evidence, so long as there are consequences for bias, there’s something to be redeemed there. If we could get Anglecynn on our side, which is a realistic possibility, then we might actually have the support necessary to assault Fel Seed and skip the rest of the quests. Plus, there are a billion obols on the line, which I can virtually assure you aren’t going to be had through a few strategic killings.”

“Alright,” I said, taking a breath. “Coming at this with a mindset of compromise … how likely do you think you are to win your trial?”

“Without Solace or the locus to present as proof of necessity, my odds are hurt,” said Amaryllis.

“I refuse to have any part in it,” said Solace.

“I know,” said Amaryllis. “I wasn’t trying to make my case, I wasn’t pleading with you, I was just saying — it is what it is. When I thought that Onion would bring you into the Court, it was a much better strategy. Now, the question of necessity rests on trust and belief in myself and Raven. We’re only trying to convince the middle, not those who have been bought or otherwise compromised on either side, but if the trial isn’t a complete farce, then we’re depending on them, and I’m not sure we have them. If Onion knows that you’re out, we’re in an even worse position.”

“So we bring me in,” I replied. “I can testify for you.”

“You’re a wanted criminal twice over,” said Amaryllis. “Once for desertion, once for whatever charges Onion was using to justify Yarrow and Zinnia taking you.”

“So then I’m a surprise witness,” I replied. “You call me forward, I say whatever you think it’s best I say, and you have more leverage. They’d let me have my say, wouldn’t they?”

“I don’t know,” said Amaryllis. “It would go to a vote. Most likely enough people would want to hear what you had to tell them that you would get a chance to speak. And after you were done testifying, you would immediately be arrested.”

“No,” I replied. “Once I was finished, I would use the Ring of Upward Bliss and nope out of there, unless everything goes more smoothly than I think it would go. I’d at least be doing something. And I would also be on hand in case things went south for you during the trial.”

Amaryllis considered this for a moment. “It’s reckless,” she finally said. “And it might be better to try securing you a pardon. But … okay. And if they attack you, or me, or they even seem like they’re going to be engaging in foul play, that’s when you either bail out or impale them.”

I got a new message from Onion right at the crack of dawn. I’d kept the marble in my ear, for no real reason than because Onion might let slip what he knew, but it was almost surely going to be trashed after that, a piece of evidence that I didn’t want to be hanging onto for too long.

«Charon is empty. Where are you? Name color seventeen.» He hadn’t even used all fifteen words. (I assumed the punctuation that should have been there.)

“That’s Onion,” I said to Amaryllis. “He knows something is up, it’s a challenge that we don’t have a response to.” I repeated the message back to her, and she nodded.

“Better not to respond,” said Amaryllis.

“No,” I replied. “Better to throw him off as best we can.” Val would have known what to say.

“I don’t think you can faze him, but you’re welcome to try,” replied Amaryllis. “Run it by me first to make sure you’re not breaking opsec.”

I ran my first thought by Amaryllis, and she rolled her eyes, but decided that it didn’t break opsec, even if it did give him a hint as to what was going on.

«It is me, your nephew Yarrow, who is completely alive and safe. Do not worry.»

“I don’t think that’s going to rattle him,” said Amaryllis. “If he’s smart, he won’t respond. Once you’re finished, we’ll dig a hole and place the marble in it, then have Grak ward it, then bury it.”

But Onion did respond, and with considerably more venom than I had imagined.

«Your bones will be dust your skin flayed your blood curdled your soul eternally damned» came his response. I almost laughed. It was some internet tough guy bullshit.

«That is a very rude way to speak to your beloved nephew who is alive» I replied.

I was hoping that would get his goat. Onion was supposed to be a smooth operator, cool as a cucumber and fully in control of a monstrous bloodthirst, but my guess was that he had limits, and if I could get him nice and steamed before the trial, all the better. Amaryllis didn’t think much of this plan, but I was hopeful.

I sat on a bench with some other people, in my full armor, waiting for the trial to start. We had gone back to the hotel and done some planning and strategy discussion there, with our need for sleep offloaded to the tuung. So far, I hadn’t had another terse conversation with Onion via the entad link between us, but I wasn’t sure why, since the entad should have been recharged. We’d elected not to try faking up some (late) transcripts to send over. Without Yarrow or Zinnia, it was hard to know what kinds of questions they would ask, what kind of format it should be in, and a whole host of other questions, aside from the fact that teleporting it over would be some concrete evidence that we’d been fucking with Onion.

I watched the council be seated, and after a bang of the gavel and some opening words by an elderly woman whose name plate informed me was Phlox, the trial was once again in motion. Amaryllis had given me the short version of the trial, but it still felt like I was coming in on a new series starting on the second episode. Amaryllis went to take her place in front of the council, and I watched her carefully. Stripped of her armor and other offensive gear, she looked a lot less deadly than she was.

“The matter of desertion from the Host by Amaryllis Penndraig is hereby resumed,” said Phlox. “Onion, have you obtained the witnesses requested at the last council session?”

“No,” replied Onion. “Further discussion on the matter is classified, but it wasn’t feasible to transport them.”

“Are there full or redacted transcripts?” asked Amaryllis.

“You’re out of order,” replied Phlox with a frown. She turned to Onion. “The question stands.”

“It is not possible to produce transcripts at this time,” said Onion. He was tight-lipped. Surely this was something that the two of them had talked about beforehand, and this was the part where they ripped the band-aid off in front of the council, revealing that more information wasn’t forthcoming. There was some light rumbling from the council, but no one made a motion.

It also let me know that Onion knew what was up. I wondered whether he’d been to the black site himself, or whether he’d sent someone.

“Then I would like to call forward a witness to corroborate,” said Amaryllis.

“Very well,” replied Phlox. “You may call your witness.”

“I call Juniper Smith,” said Amaryllis.

That was my cue, and I stood up and walked forward to stand in front of the council, replacing Amaryllis, as the council erupted into conversation that was quickly killed by the vibration mages.

“Motion to dismiss the witness,” said Onion.

“Second,” came a voice I didn’t recognize, even after looking at her. There sure were sure a hell of a lot of Penndraigs, and I was finding that the flower names were making it hard to keep them separated in my head.

“Then we’ll bring it to a vote,” said Phlox.

“Point of information,” came another voice, this one from a man who was half-standing to be recognized.

“Proceed,” replied Phlox.

“Why would we dismiss the witness?” he asked.

“Juniper Smith was arrested under the TRAITOR Act two days prior,” said Onion. “On top of that, there’s an active arrest warrant against him for the crime of desertion.”

Amaryllis came forward from the stand. “Juniper Smith has not been informed of any of that,” she said. “Per the language of the TRAITOR Act, the arresting officer or deputized individual should have informed him of the evidence against him within twenty-four hours of his arrest, which was not done. Regarding his active arrest warrant, Mr. Smith is just now being informed of it, but as he’s not a member of the Court, that’s an issue for the city guard and the Host, not for this council. Both authorities are subordinate to the council for purposes of testimony.”

“We will take the propriety of this witness to a vote,” said Phlox, but she didn’t seem very happy about it. Amaryllis and I stood there awkwardly while yeas and nays were counted, and when we handily won the vote, she retreated to her place in the galley.

“I’ll take the first question,” said Onion. Phlox nodded to him. “How did you escape custody?”

I knew enough of the American legal system to know that this was the point you’d say, ‘objection, relevance’, but I also knew enough about how Anglecynn did law that this kind of thing was accepted as a matter of course. At most, you could object and ask to know where a line of questioning was going, but in this case it was pretty clear that if I was a witness, they could ask all kinds of irrelevant-to-desertion questions in order to determine whether I could be trusted.

“What makes you think that I was ever in custody?” I asked.

“Don’t play coy with me, boy,” replied Onion. “Refuse to give a straight answer to the council at your peril.”

I thought that was pretty fucking laughable, given that I was already guilty of desertion and apparently under the authority of some no-doubt draconian national security bill. “I was never brought into custody,” I replied. “Two days ago I was in a room at Caledwich Castle, waiting for Amaryllis to finish up a meeting, when two other members of the Court, Yarrow and Zinnia walked in. After we talked for a bit, Yarrow pulled out an unknown entad and used it, which put two of my companions to sleep. Just after that, when I was going to defend them, Zinnia released a monster called a skent, which we ended up fighting. In the middle of it, Raven and I got separated. I stowed my gear and then hid out, and I didn’t reconnect with Amaryllis or Raven until this morning. I was never in the custody of anyone, nor was I told what I was supposed to be taken into custody for, which you’re apparently still not going to tell me.”

“You’re a liar,” said Onion. “I have solid information that you were captured by Yarrow and Zinnia, then taken —”

“Prove it,” I said. “If you’re going to call me a liar, show some evidence that I’m lying.”

Onion grit his teeth, but before he could continue, Phlox intervened. “This is all beside the point,” said Phlox, clearing her throat. “It’s also a rather poor introduction to this witness.” She said this without casting a look at Onion, but it was clear that it was meant for him. “Tell us who you are and where you come from.”

“My name is Juniper Smith,” I replied. “I’m originally from Sporsan, Anglecynn, a small town that largely deals with agriculture. A few months back I was arrested for assault, admitted guilt, then got put in prison. Once there, I had a few altercations and was fast-tracked for trial by adversity. Down in the Risen Lands, I met Amaryllis, and I wasn’t here yesterday, but I believe she told you the rest. I’ve been by her side pretty much non-stop since then.”

“Tell me more about the assault that led to your arrest,” said Phlox.

“Ah,” I said. “Well, there we have a problem, because I don’t know for certain. My memory was wiped clean. I’m dream-skewered.” I paused for a moment, not sure whether I needed to explain. “I’m one of a group of people who are afflicted with complete memory loss and false memories of a counterfactual place called Earth. It’s a rare condition. We’re typically identified and then transferred to Speculation and Scrutiny, where they have a dormitory for dream-skewered patients.”

“And when did this affliction occur?” asked Phlox. “What do you remember?”

“I have vivid memories of a life lived on Earth, though I doubt that would interest the council,” I said. “My first memory on Aerb was of being strapped in place on a plane, shortly before being dropped into the Risen Lands. I can tell you anything that happened beyond that point.”

“This is ridiculous,” said Onion. “Do you have any proof of this supposed affliction?”

“I’ve spoken with Speculator Masters at the Athenaeum of Speculation and Scrutiny, who runs the Cerebral College,” I said. “He confirmed the affliction through use of an entad.”

“And would he be any relation to Raven Masters?” asked Onion.

“He’s her father,” I replied. I could see that didn’t sit well with the court, for obvious reasons.

“This affliction aside, you have a full recollection of everything that happened with Amaryllis?” asked Phlox.

“I do,” I replied. “And I’ve been with her almost the entire way. I’ll confirm everything she said about attempts on our lives by Larkspur, about our attempts to fight off threats to Aerb, including in Li’o, and about a desire to safeguard the last remaining locus.”

“I want to talk for a moment about your arrest and your time in prison,” said Phlox.

“Again, I don’t remember any of it,” I said. “It might as well have happened to a different person. All I know is what I’ve been able to find out after-the-fact, which hasn’t been much.” That was one of the reasons to admit to being dream-skewered up-front. I didn’t think that it would be possible to lie my way through things I knew nothing about.

“This is primarily for the council’s consideration,” said Phlox. She picked up a file and leafed through it. “You were a middling student until the age of seventeen, when you assaulted another boy. Following a short trial where you pleaded guilty, you were put into prison, with a term of three months, after which you would have been released in time to take your senior year of schooling over again. Instead, you acted belligerent in prison and racked up a number of infractions, including more fights, which culminated in you killing another inmate. The warden deemed you a good candidate for a trial by adversity, on the theory that if you were able to survive, your violent impulses might be tamed by the Host.”

I stood there and said nothing. Only a little of that was news to me. I’d punched the same guy in the face back on Earth, but the timelines were a little different, and on Earth, nothing had come of it. On Aerb, it was enough for a light prison sentence, which probably escalated due to how bad a place I would have been in emotionally. I was a little bit surprised that I would have been able to attack anyone while clinically depressed, but I didn’t have that good a handle on the Aerb version of myself.

“You claim to remember none of this?” asked Phlox.

“That’s what I’m saying, yeah,” I replied.

I got some more questions after that from the rest of the council, some of them softballs (including one from Lisi), some honest inquiries about dream-skewering and Earth, and a few from people who just wanted to smear me.

“Why didn’t you report to the Host?” asked Onion.

“Oh,” I said. “I had no conception of Anglecynn or the Host. The Risen Lands weren’t the best introduction to Aerb, as far as figuring out where I was or what I was supposed to be doing. Plus a bunch of people were trying to kill me, and some of the other people in the trial had said they were affiliated with the Color Riot, which I guess I thought was the same as the Host. They died before they could clarify. By the time I’d teamed up with Amaryllis and we had a chance to sort things out, we were halfway to Silmar City.”

“You use the name Juniper Smith,” said Phlox. “Why, if you have no memories of that life?”

“It’s what it says on my passport,” I replied with a shrug. That got a laugh from a few people, but I knew it wasn’t a great answer. The real answer, ‘oh, that’s also my name on Earth’, was bat shit insane. “It’s what one of the others called me. I think we might have known each other.”

Once we were through with the dream-skewer stuff, we got back on more solid ground, places where I actually knew the answers.

“When and where did you learn magic?” asked Onion, his eyes narrowed.

“I studied at the Athenaeum of Sound and Silence, shortly before the exclusion there,” I replied. “I was fast-tracked thanks to abuse of a special clause. After that, I trained in a time chamber.”

“Yet those aren’t the only two you know,” said Onion.

“No,” I replied. “I’m a registered soul mage, and I have some faculty with blood magic, bone magic, skin magic, water magic, passion magic, ink magic, air magic, and gem magic.”

Gods did I love the silence that followed that. It meant giving up some strategic advantage in exchange for political and legal advantage, but part of the reason that I was on board with coming clean like this was just seeing the looks on their faces. Some of them didn’t believe me, but I could see that many of them did.

“I have the feeling you’re not taking this council seriously,” said Phlox, frowning.

“I can give demonstrations,” I replied. “It’s a matter of fact. If I can have the council’s leave?”

Phlox nodded, suddenly not seeming too sure of herself.

I went through small demonstrations of each, leaving aside ink magic, because it took too long, water magic, because it needed more room, and skin magic, because it was excluded.

“Given you have no registration in any of those magics, you’ve just committed a number of serious crimes in front of this court,” said Phlox. “Your disregard for —”

“Point of law,” said Amaryllis, rising from her place on the bench. Phlox paused, then gave her a curt nod, probably knowing that the council would vote for her to speak anyway. “Under the revised MAC Act, it’s illegal to possess unauthorized materials teaching about magic, it’s illegal to sell or buy such materials, it’s illegal to use those magics for commercial activity, it’s illegal to teach those magics, and it’s illegal to be taught them. To my knowledge, Juniper has done none of those things.” She sat back down, smoothing her skirt, with not a trace of the smug satisfaction I knew she was feeling.

“How did you learn so much, so quickly?” Phlox asked me.

“I don’t know,” I replied. “Part of it is diligent training within a time chamber. The other part is a mystery.” I would naturally refrain from saying that I was Uther reborn. Better to have them connect the dots themselves, and see it by implication. “In terms of the charge of desertion against Amaryllis, my gifts are relevant only insofar as it was likely one of the things that attracted both Raven and Solace to us. Both were possessed of powerful magic that helped divine our location, and both had things for us to do which a visit to Anglecynn and potential incarceration wouldn’t have helped.”

“That it would be inconvenient does not save you from your duty,” said Onion.

“What happened at Li’o could have been much worse,” I replied. “It wasn’t a matter of inconvenience, it was a matter of hundreds of thousands of lives, maybe more.”

“Are you saying that it wasn’t coincidence that you were there?” asked a man.

“No,” I replied. “It wasn’t. We didn’t know what would be showing up, just that there would probably be something. As it turned out, we were right.” This was a tangent that could probably be mined for hours, but it would almost certainly do nothing but make us look good. After all, we’d saved the day.

Phlox cleared her throat. “And when you went to Headwater, stole a tuung woman away, then killed hundreds of tuung in a mad quest to create your own island nation, was that out of necessity?”

I frowned at that. Those were dots that I was hoping they wouldn’t connect, but Miunun was a nation of tuung, and there were only three places in the world where the tuung could be found. If you were trying to figure out where our little nation had gotten its native population from, you didn’t have to look around all that much, and even if you didn’t have a solid timeline, it wouldn’t have taken too much looking through newspapers to see our fingerprints.

It was, unfortunately, not something that I was adequately prepared for.

“To answer that, I would have to tell you what we accomplished, and it’s classified, for good reason,” I replied. “If I said it, I would be risking the lives of everyone in this room.”

“So you admit that in the course of establishing the Republic of Miunun, you committed a number of crimes?” asked Phlox.

“Yes,” I replied. “Though not, I think, any Anglish crimes.”

“I have no further questions then, and will open it to the council, but I’m ready to vote on an end to witness testimony now,” said Phlox.

There were, naturally, questions. I was Advisor on Culture for Miunun, and there were aspersions cast about this being a position gained through nepotism, as I had no qualifications that would have warranted it, the delicious irony apparently lost on the nobility. I was asked about my ability to learn new magics, which I tried my best not to answer concretely. I gave answers on Solace and the locus, on Larkspur, on that first altercation we’d had at the library in Cranberry Bay, and a whole host of others. It was exhausting, but in a way that was familiar from my DMing days, being the focus of attention and having to deliver considered answers about a wide range of different topics. In the corner of my eye, my mental resources were slowly draining, and I was sure that if I had a meter that showed social resources, it would have bottomed out a half hour in.

I was waiting for another hammer to drop. The questioning was going on for a long time, that made sense given all the ground there was to cover, and that the trial had specifically been maneuvered by Amaryllis to have components of ‘what were you up to while you were gone’. But on the flip side of that, all those questions were grinding me down, and there was a good possibility that I was going to make a mistake. If anyone had a big bombshell to drop, the time to do it would be right at the end, when I was exhausted.

Eventually, someone called on a vote to end questioning, and Phlox must have thought that the vote would pass. “Before we do, there’s one last thing I’m curious about, if the council will indulge me. We’ve heard a fair amount today about what you’ve done, some of which we’ll no doubt speak to Amaryllis about in determining whether her necessity defense holds water. But the final question I wanted to ask was what you knew about a half-elf named Fenn Greenglass.”

“She was … a traveling companion,” I said. “A friend of mine. She died, not too long ago.”

“She was a part of your Council of Arches, wasn’t she?” asked Phlox.

“Yes,” I nodded.

“So you would say more than a friend?” asked Phlox.

“A loyal friend,” I replied. I loved her.

“How did you meet?” asked Phlox, leaning forward. She was using a calm, gentle voice, which was setting me on edge.

“We met in the Risen Lands,” I replied. “She was in Silmar City when we got there.”

“And what was she doing there?” asked Phlox.

“Initially she said that she was looting,” I replied. The gears in my head were grinding against each other. “We found out a little more than a month later that she had been a convict, like us, not part of the trial by adversity, but pulled out of prison to serve as a guide. Her conviction was for looting the Risen Lands, something she’d apparently done for a few years. She knew the place well. All she really knew about her circumstance was that the people she was with, Fireteam Blackheart, had gotten separated from her, and she took that opportunity to make a run for it. From what she said, she didn’t think that her odds of leaving the exclusion zone alive were good.”

“She thought her odds were better alone?” asked Phlox, craning forward slightly.

“Er, no,” I replied. “She thought that whatever they were up to, they were probably going to kill her once they were finished. Their legal authority for being in an exclusion zone was, uh, unclear.”

“And you traveled with this individual since meeting them in Silmar City?” asked Phlox.

“Yes,” I replied. I felt myself tensing the muscles of my jaw, and willed myself to stop.

“Where is she now?” asked Phlox.

“She’s dead,” I replied. “Buried on the Isle of Poran, though she died elsewhere. The rest is classified.”

“I see,” replied Phlox with a demure smile. I wanted to punch her right in her fucking face. “And of the traveling companions we’ve spoken of, there is one we haven’t mentioned, isn’t there?”

I frowned. “Grakhuil Leadbraids?” I asked.

“No,” said Phlox. “Fallatehr Whiteshell, an elf.”

Fuck. “The name doesn’t ring a bell,” I replied, but how in the fuck had she found out about Fallatehr? And what in the world was I supposed to say about him? I resisted the urge to look over at Amaryllis, and wished that we had a telepathic link of some kind so that she could tell me how to play this. More than that, I wished Valencia were around to signal to me whether or not this was a fishing expedition.

“I’m going to enter a fair number of things into evidence now,” said Phlox. “The first is a brief dossier on Fallatehr Whiteshell, who was a noted soul mage during the Second Empire. He was fortunate enough to have dodged the calamity at Manifest, but unfortunately for him, he was imprisoned in the Amoureux Penitentiary, a sentient prison built on Sulid Isle, which was then under the authority of Anglecynn. Members of the council are welcome to look at the dossier during our next recess, but I believe one of the most relevant pieces of information is at the end: Whiteshell was never stripped of his ability to practice soul magic, in part because certain members of the Lost King’s Court, now long-dead, wished to keep him on hand in the event he was needed.”

That … hadn’t been what Fallatehr had said. It had been subjective months since that whole terrible ordeal, but I would have remembered if he’d mentioned it. I had no way to know whether it was true or not, but it would explain things. It also had the mark of the Dungeon Master on it, as it would allow questlines to lead to each other. If we hadn’t gone to Fallatehr, then he might have shown up as an antagonist later on, pulled from the penitentiary by Hyacinth or someone else, if he hadn’t gotten out on his own.

Phlox continued, “The second piece of evidence I’d like to enter into the record is a report from an expedition to Sulid Isle, one sent out by the Zorish, who now control the land and the penitentiary. It’s brief, but the primary takeaway is that the expedition found evidence of a battle between the surviving prisoners and the prison itself, with the prison reporting that no one was left alive. Conversation with the entad prison is apparently troublesome, but it reported that Fallatehr Whiteshell was seen leaving the penitentiary, accompanied by,” and here, for dramatic effect, Phlox flipped through a few pages to read from the physical document. “‘Amaryllis Penndraig, a dwarf, another human, a half-elf, and most curiously, a bound non-anima’.” Phlox looked up at me.

“A building told you this?” I asked.

She didn’t dignify that with a response. “Why did you take Fallatehr Whiteshell out of prison?” asked Phlox.

“I didn’t,” I replied.

“Was it because you needed a teacher for soul magic?” asked Phlox. “Or because you had some plans for him?”

“Mu,” I replied, finally remembering what Amaryllis had said.

“Motion for a recess —” came Lisi’s voice from the council, but it was shut down by the vibration mages, and Phlox continued on without acknowledging it.

“You have claimed that your soul cannot be inspected by anolia, for fear of a memetic threat,” said Phlox. “What, precisely, are you hiding?”

I stood there in stony silence. “I decline to answer further questions,” I replied.

“Very well,” said Phlox. “We can then vote on whether to keep you as a witness, but I believe our lines of questioning have been exhausted.”

The vote was close, maybe because Phlox had decided to leave so much on the table as far as questioning me went, but I had been up there for a long time, and I could sense that people were getting restless.

Unfortunately, that left the other business.

“Bailiffs, arrest that man,” said Onion.

“Wait,” I said, holding out my hand. “I demand a trial by combat.”

Onion actually laughed, the kind of laugh you sometimes see a person do right before they get violent. “We’d still have to take you into custody,” he replied. “But trial by combat isn’t allowed for any but a member of the Court.”

“Well then,” I replied. I wondered how much more trouble I would be in if I tried to kill Onion with a lucky throw of my weapon. It was insanity that I was allowed to speak in front of the council with a weapon on me in the first place, but they probably weren’t so insane as to not have wards, even if they had poor enough security that I’d been able to get into the War Room with only a little bit of help. My hand moved down to the Ring of Upward Bliss, and I prepared myself to be a mile up. Then, I paused, and turned to the side. “Amaryllis, will you marry me?”

“Yes,” replied Amaryllis, almost as soon as the question was out of my mouth. “Per the Decency Acts, Juniper and I have been cohabiting for the past three months and qualify to waive the wait time. I need a witness to vouch.”

“I — I vouch,” said Lisi from her place on the council.

I don’t know why Phlox didn’t say anything before that point. Maybe she was too stunned, or more likely, she was trying to work through the political calculus of this stunt. But just as Amaryllis began speaking again, Phlox called out, “Silence them.”

I wasn’t good enough at vibration magic to out-compete both of the vibration mages at the same time, though I sure gave it my damnedest. Fortunately, Amaryllis was prepared, because she started rapidly signing in Gimb.

Repeat after me, I, Amaryllis Penndraig, — I started signing along with her and very briefly contemplated a joke, but decided on swapping in my name for hers — take you, Juniper Smith, to be my wedded husband by the terms of the Decency Acts of FE 512, and confer onto you, by the Reconciliation Acts of FE 334, partial power of nobility and full status as member of the Court. I was pretty sure that I didn’t need to sign that too, but I did it anyway.

While all that was going on, Phlox was shouting increasingly less composed orders, either because she saw this for a political masterstroke, or because she just wanted to stop us from doing something we were trying to do. She called for the bailiffs to arrest me, but they were slow to act, maybe because of everything I claimed to have done, or maybe just because it was chaotic. I honestly didn’t have a good grasp of who was doing what and why, but I focused my eyes on Amaryllis, and when she finished … well, she didn’t look happy, but she had that set look that she sometimes got when something was done.

“Point of order,” called a voice from the council. It was Bartholomew, a guy that Amaryllis had pointed out to me as technically minded. I didn’t know if he knew Gimb, or was just guessing. “Juniper is a full member of the Court now.”

“And he’ll still be taken into custody,” said Onion, voice firm.

“I request to be remanded into the custody of Rosemallow Penndraig,” I replied. I would have cited the specific act, if I knew it, but I did know it was possible, because Amaryllis was in custody under the same terms.

In an ideal world, we would have walked out of the council room with our heads held high, but there followed a quite lengthy discussion by the council on whether or not what we’d just done was in any way legal or binding, and if it was, what the next steps were. As it turned out, Amaryllis was on the Legal Council, as of two days ago, just before her trial had begun. That gave her a special status, and allowed her proclamation to carry more legal authority than it otherwise would have. After a solid hour of intense argument, it was finally decided that yes, we really were married, and I was a member of the Court.

And then we walked out of the council room with our heads held high.

Overwhelming Violence

At first I thought it was a revision mage, undoing the fight, which would have been manifestly unfair, given that it was to the death, but maybe a bit understandable. If everyone admitted that I was the winner, well, I would take it. But no, it wasn’t a revision mage at all, that would have looked completely different to what I was seeing, which wasn’t the reversal of physics, but instead, the pieces of a man being repaired by — his armor, I could see it coming back together too, assembling him.

I ran forward to attack this work in progress, and was brought to my knees by a glow of green magic that shrieked in my skull. It didn’t stop until Onion was back together, gasping within his armor, whole once more, even the fingers that I’d cut off back on his hand. The only difference was that one of the three green lights on his chest was burned out.

“I won,” I said. “You fuck.”

Onion’s sword was in his hand, its form the same as it had been at the start of the match. I was waiting for him to counter, to say that it was to the death and he wasn’t dead, or for him to ask whether I thought he was stupid enough not to clear it with the referee first. Instead, he just attacked.

There was something savage in the way he went after me, though it was hard to pick up on it, because there was nothing uncontrolled about his impeccable swordsmanship. Instead it was the way he would attack any opening, and naked aggression that wasn’t without its risks. He hadn’t expected to die. Now, he wanted this done.

I was a better swordsman than Onion. I’d known, going in, that would probably be the case, since if we were evenly matched, then my advantage would be sky-high skills, and his would be high attributes.

I moved in close, wielding my cloud of sword at one of the openings he’d left for me, and he wasn’t able to bring his blade down in time, not until my blade had already touched his armor. His own version of the probability blade made some absurd shape when he got it into position, a curved hook that might have been a bastard cousin of a kopesh. He managed to stop my blade before it had penetrated more than a few inches, but that should have been enough to wound him so badly that he would be easy to finish off for a second time.

Unfortunately, when I lost the contest of strength, Onion seemed completely unfazed, and resumed his attacks with the same speed and fury that he’d used before. We got into a third riposte chain, but I elected not to take my attack after my second parry, worried that I was going to get sliced up by the inevitable counter-riposte.

He was moving slower, more cautiously, and if his wound wasn’t stopping him, then it had been a wake up call. He was back to what he’d been doing before, testing out swords and generally finding them wanting. If he was concerned about a second hit like the one that had killed him, he wasn’t showing it in any way, which was a shame, because having him prepare for an attack that I wasn’t going to make would probably have been helpful.

This was all going on for longer than sword fights were supposed to go on, and I was getting weaker by the minute. My best guess at what was happening on a game-mechanical level was that the tuning was somehow off, and at very high levels of all the relevant skills, defense trumped offense, almost certainly because of how sky-high parry could get. We’d had it happen in a few of our sessions, where round after round would pass with no one seeming to be able to hit each other. Usually, I would try my best to fudge it, since it always sucked the tension from the combat to have miss after miss, but I didn’t think the Dungeon Master actually cared. Needless to say, D&D was a lot better balanced than the jank I was saddled with, the jank that underwrote the entire universe I found myself in.

After another minute of back and forth swordplay, with Onion occasionally trying out a different entad ability for his sword, he either happened on one that he had been trying to find, or one that he was lucky to come across. My world went dark, but only for a moment, because I dodged out of the way, not knowing what I was dodging or where I should be moving, somehow coming up from a sideways roll with all my vital body parts intact. Onion was standing beside a sphere of pitch black about twenty feet across, which he ducked into as soon as he saw that I’d moved outside it.

I sat there, tensed, waiting for him to come out, but he stayed in the zone of darkness. I didn’t know what he was waiting for, if anything, just that I couldn’t see him. Surely he hadn’t figured out that time wasn’t on my side? Surely he wasn’t going to while away a half hour in pitch black?

When his sword came flying out of the darkness at me, I parried it straight back into the darkness at him. I had only seen it for a fraction of a second, but it wasn’t the same black sword that had created the darkness, it was something else, a flaming sword whose heat I’d felt even through the armor. I tried to work out what that meant, and realized that the sphere of darkness was staying there even though he’d switched which entad the sword was copying, which meant that the darkness was probably a permanent or ongoing effect. That was bad, real bad, because it meant that he could safely cycle through different possible entads, secure in the knowledge that I didn’t actually know where he was. It was worse than him stalling.

The next attack from the darkness was with multiple blades, which I frankly found insulting, because a bladebound could parry bullets pretty much as a novice. I parried them back at what I thought was his location, based on the arc of the weapons, but they kept coming out, as though he thought he could tire me out, or somehow score a hit.

The last sword to come out of the blackness was followed by Onion himself, his black armor providing a bit of camouflage that didn’t particularly stop me. Rather than going at me head-on, he ran off to the side, circling around me and forcing me between himself and the bubble of darkness. I wasn’t about to get pushed into it, but assuming that he could see while inside it, it was an interesting asymmetry he’d created, where I had a physical obstacle that he didn’t.

Unfortunately, that was only half the story, because at the same time he attacked me, slashing forward with his probability blade, I felt a prickle at the back of my neck and caught sight of a second attacker in my periphery.

I pulled a sword from Sable, completely non-magical and unbound, and parried the attacker from behind at the same time as I parried Onion in front of me. Unfortunately, the non-bonded blade wasn’t infinitely sharp, and couldn’t properly block the sword behind me, and I felt the bite of a blade before “dodging” ten feet away, my movement far more like teleportation than actual movement. The sword I’d been using to parry with had been sliced in two, and I dropped it to the ground, with the probability blade held in front of me. There very much appeared to be two Onions in front of me. I couldn’t tell what had happened with the one that had been in front, and was now on my left. I was fairly certain that our swords hadn’t touched. They were moving out of sync, which put limits on what could possibly be happening with whatever entad had been used, but I had no clue, it was a fucking entad, it could be anything.

I finally decided to take a chance and pull a piece of untried, untested gear from Sable, which was on my left hand. Both of the Onions saw the weapon just as it came out, and moved away from the nozzle as I held it down, ducking away from the chlorine trifluoride. I managed to get both of them in the spray though, their parries ineffective (thank the gods), and the one on the right burst into flames straight away, then melted and dissolved into mud. The one on my left, the real one, made a change to his sword, causing it to be wreathed in shimmering frost, which attacked the fire on him.

(I was deathly afraid of the metal Super Soaker I’d used, in part because I had been the one to create it, as well as the one to synthesize the death fire inside of it. It was way beyond my skill level in Alchemy, and for how little time I’d had to produce the stuff, there had been an awful lot of nearly disastrous consequences. Aerb had all kinds of materials that weren’t available on Earth, some of them magical, some of them ‘not’ magical, and we’d done three tests with different Aerbian materials, all of which had been a bust. There was a gel made by an aquatic plant that firefighters would smear themselves with before running into a fire, and chlorine trifluoride set it on fire at the moment of first contact. It was impressive, seeing chlorine trifluoride burn through a piece of starmetal, which was supposed to stop dragonfire, but it really made me think that I was playing with something way beyond my paygrade.)

I held my breath and moved as far away as I could, because the arena floor was on fire where the chlorine trifluoride had come out, and that fire was producing fluorine gas, which was a severe irritant. Onion was still trying to put himself out with his sword, which was spreading frost across his armor now too, except where the fire juice had hit him. While he was working on that, I threw my sword at him, the probability blade once again a cloud in the air, and while he saw it, and turned his sword into a probability blade of his own to parry it back to me, that meant that he no longer had the frost weapon. The flames started up once more, burning his armor, and when I caught my sword, I threw it again, forcing him to parry. This time he tried to turn my sword away, to parry it and pin it to the ground, but it returned to my hand all the same, courtesy of my virtue that made it a returning weapon.

It was a slow death, until it wasn’t. He was burning, and to stop it, he needed the same entad that he was using to fend off my attacks. Eventually, the fire burned through the thigh of his armor, down into his leg, and he dropped to one knee. He parried my sword, then parried it again, but on the third time, he waited too long trying to fight the fire, and the probability blade cleaved straight through him, from the top of his shoulder down to the meat of his hip on the other side. My sword was back in my hand before his armor started rebuilding him again.

I waited and watched, wondering how many times I was going to have to kill this fucker. His armor had three jewels on it, and the second one cracked and went dim once he was back on his feet, but did that mean that he had one life left, or two? By videogame rules, it should have been three times.

I was at two thirds of my full HP. Normally HP wasn’t really a consideration, because I would use my bones to heal my wounds before it would even matter, and tracking how much more punishment I could take was really a matter of tracking bones, not the number on the bar in the corner of my vision. That was standard for a lot of games, where there were two health economies, and one of them was irrelevant most of the time. In D&D, once you got to a certain point, you paid a lot more attention to how many healing spells the cleric had, rather than how much the party members died. Now, in this arena where bone magic was warded against, I was back down to actually paying attention to that bar and what it was doing, since I’d turned pain way the hell down and my virtues meant that afflictions didn’t actually provide maluses.

I started round three with another squirt from the flame soaker. I was really hoping, in my heart of hearts, that it would drench him in flames and that would be the end of it, but all narrative logic said otherwise, and I had to believe that he’d been thinking about the problem for the entire time he’d been burning to death. When the gout of flame came toward him, his sword transformed, becoming a creamy white, and the liquid flame diverted around him. I let off the trigger, whipped my probability blade at him, and then mashed down on the trigger again, hoping that he wouldn’t be able to defend against both attacks at once. Instead, the cream-colored sword he was holding pulsed slightly, and the probability blade went flying off to the side, the attack diverted, before returning to my hand.

Well, fuck.

Once he’d acquired a sword, or whatever the fuck his actual limitation to copying was, he didn’t seem to have trouble using it a second time, and he switched fast enough that he didn’t seem to have a problem using it as a defense. This new cream-colored sword he was using would mean that future liquid attacks would be pretty much harmless, unless I could get in with my actual weapon at the same time, but I didn’t have dual wielding as a skill anymore, and I had to imagine that I was suffering some kind of penalty for doing it without: I could certainly feel that I was less effective with my weapon.

I crossed over to Onion, still holding the fire soaker. The dome of blackness was still there, and now half of the arena was on fire, the floor not at all impervious to the fire, not that I’d expected it to be. There were fumes in the air, already stinging my eyes, and I was trying my best to avoid the smoke. I idly hoped that the audience sitting above him, which I’d been completely ignoring, had adequate defenses against what we were throwing around.

I was actually a lot worse at swordfighting while holding something in my offhand, and not just because I was really worried about the fire soaker suffering some malfunction or leak that would end up fucking me. I had made the thing as fast as humanly possible, and definitely not had as much time for testing as I’d wanted, even though we’d had access to a facility that Rosemallow had procured for us.

When I was within melee range, Onion changed his sword to one that was red and pitted with rust, and lunged toward me, forcing a parry. I squirted the fire soaker at him, but he dodged to the side and switched back to the cream-colored one that repelled the fire. I wasn’t entirely sure what he was playing at, but I knew that if he was taking an overly cautious approach, that probably wasn’t good for me. I didn’t have a good gauge for how long the battle had been going on, but I was sure it had been a few minutes, maybe even double-digit minutes, which meant that I was appreciably worse.

Onion came in again for a quick strike, which I parried, and this time I could see that his rusted sword had done something to my sword where they made contact, a spot of rust that disappeared as soon as the probability blade was back to its old blurry self. I materialized it once, seeing if the rust spot was permanent, and Onion attacked again, bouncing backward from me when I squirted the fire soaker at him.

The liquid fire was coming out slower now. The tank was pretty small, and there was limited pressure. Once it was out, I could switch to the acid soaker, and some other tricks, but I was having trouble pushing the offensive while dual wielding, and time wasn’t on my side.

Onion came in a third time, and this time our blades stayed in contact for longer. The rust spread fast, more of a splotch than a spot, and I let the probability blade go immaterial, hoping to cut straight through him. Instead, I found myself dodging out of the way as our swords followed through at each other, another strictly impossible dodge made just as his blade touched my armor.

I had gotten him with the fire soaker in that exchange though, a glancing blow to his side that had nonetheless set him on fire. I smiled a bit, thinking that I was well on my way to killing him, but then I saw my probability blade flicker once before materializing into a rusted, pitted sword.

I cursed as I watched Onion put out the fire with his frost sword. I had other swords in Sable, of course I did, but I wasn’t bonded to them, which meant that I wouldn’t get the benefits, which meant that if we went sword-to-sword, I would almost certainly die. The place where he’d cut into my armor showed no rust at all, and I swore at what complete bullshit it was that my sword wasn’t actually inviolable like my armor was. I had the Diamond Blade virtue, but it only said that my sword would never break or dull, and apparently two degrees of reasonableness wasn’t enough for me to argue the point. As I looked at the rusted out probability blade, it hadn’t actually broken, and the cutting edge was as sharp as ever, it was just that whatever magical effect had been applied to the blade, it had stopped it from doing its probability thing.

I was getting really annoyed by entads.

Onion put out his fire with the frost sword and began to approach me again. My eyes were watering, but I could see just fine, because physical injuries were no longer a great concern. I still wasn’t sure how I was going to win this though, if the probability blade was stuck in one shape.

I decided to take a gamble. My armor had been struck by the same rusting attack, but it was unaffected because it was inviolable. However, the inviolability only applied because of my skill with heavy armor, and in theory, that meant that I could use my, er, ‘skill’ to let that magical effect continue on, if it was sticking to the armor. With that thought, rust raced through my armor from the point where it had been cut, and the metal flaked and fell off in pieces until it was completely gone. Once that was finished, I tossed the probability blade and the fire soaker to the side.

You see, when I’d been carving out skills from souls, I hadn’t just taken exactly what I’d needed, I’d been thinking about contingencies, and really, it seemed unfair that Onion was the only one to have multiple phases.

Unarmored 30, Glancing Blow: While unarmored, add a bonus to injury rolls equal to your unarmored skill. While unarmored, you can ignore one physical injury affliction, changing which is ignored whenever you would like.

Unarmored 50, Ghost Body: While unarmored, attacks which hit your body no longer make physical contact for the purposes of contact damage or effects, whether magical or otherwise, even if those attacks still do damage.

Unarmored 70, A Body in Motion: Attempts to net, ensnare, grapple, or otherwise restrain you have a 50% chance to fail (after dodge attempts), and are twice as easy to escape if they don’t fail. For purposes of dodging, you move twice as fast while unarmored.

Unarmored 90, Bodily Stasis: You heal from injuries and wounds at one hundred times the normal speed. You need one hundredth the water, air, and food you normally would.

Unarmored 100, Perfected Body: Your skin is as hard as steel. While unarmored, you gain a twenty percent bonus to all defensive rolls, including dodge, parry, entad defense rolls, and magical defense rolls. If this would result in a total defense bonus below fifty, raise it to fifty instead.

Unarmed Combat 30, Hardened Fists: You suffer none of the usual durability, pain, or injury penalties for using your hands, feet, elbows, etc. in combat, even if they are not your primary weapons. You will never suffer any affliction from attacking using your body, though you may still suffer afflictions while defending.

Unarmed Combat 50, Penetrating Punches: Armor, including natural armor, is half as effective against your unarmed attacks. When attacking objects, you may consider your unarmed attacks piercing, bludgeoning, or slashing, though not more than one at a time.

Unarmed Combat 70, Weapon Emulation: Your unarmed attacks may be considered weapons when it would be beneficial for them to be so. Also, your unarmed attacks may be considered short-range melee weapons (e.g. daggers) for the purposes of entads, magical effects, or pseudomagical effects, even when this would be unreasonable. Further, your unarmed attacks may be considered specific weapons, even exotic ones, even when this would be completely unreasonable.

Unarmed Combat 90, Ghost Hand: Your unarmed attacks no longer require direct physical contact, instead working even when executed up to several inches away from the target. You take no penalties for not actually touching your target when using unarmed attacks. This effect can be used to completely negate armor, including natural armor.

Unarmed Combat 100, Pressure Points: Your unarmed attacks can be used to strike directly at the soul, disabling body parts on a critical hit. In lieu of dealing damage to an opponent with an unarmed attack, you may instead damage their soul. This effect bypasses any abilities that would normally prevent damage.

Combo Virtue, Monkish Master: While unarmed and unarmored, you no longer suffer falling damage, can run on water, can run on walls, jump twice as high/far, and double your effective SPD. You instantly master any unarmed fighting styles or maneuvers you spend five uninterrupted minutes watching.

Combo Virtue, Monkish Grandmaster: While unarmed and unarmored, you may use your Unarmed or Unarmored skill, whichever is higher, for any roll that would use PHY or a PHY attribute. Double your effective PHY.

Combo Virtue, Monkish Ascendant: While unarmed and unarmored, your body, soul, and spirit are inviolable, except as necessary to carry out useful or beneficial functions.

The capstone monkish virtue was fucking worthless, given that I knew Onion’s sword was capable of cutting through inviolable material. I was still hoping that I would be able to fuck him up though, especially since Parry and Dodge both worked equally well whether I was using a sword or my fists. By my calculations, the monkish approach was numerically worse, but it was worse in a different way, and all I really needed was a single strike to land, which would damage Onion’s soul and almost certainly render me the victor. I wouldn’t have bet on it, but I was hoping that if I damaged his soul enough, I wouldn’t have to potentially fight him a fourth time.

I hoped that beneath his helm he was looking at me like I was crazy. His sword flickered for a moment, then settled on flame, which was so cliche that I grimaced. He came at me cautiously, as though he was worried I was going to pull out some kind of insane trick that he’d never seen before, which, in fairness, didn’t seem so insane given how the fight so far had gone.

He swiped at me with his flaming sword, but I parried it with my hand, slapping it to the side.

I really wished I could have seen his face. Unlike blade-bound, monks (or “monkish”, as the game inexplicably termed them) weren’t really a thing on Aerb, presumably because they didn’t get good enough, fast enough. For all I knew, I was the best martial artist in the world.

I moved in on him, kicking his blade hand to the side and then shifting my weight to punch him straight in the chest with a clenched fist. It should have broken my hand, but instead he staggered backward, reeling, though I’d been focusing on making the damage pass through into his soul, leaving his body untouched. It had been surprisingly easy to land a hit: maybe I had made a miscalculation in the numbers, or maybe having multiple implements to strike with was more of a boon than I thought.

“What was that?” he asked me.

“I punched you,” I replied. “That’s allowed by the rules, I checked.” I was so happy that with my helm gone he could see my shit-eating grin. All I had on were the underclothes that went beneath the plate and Sable, and I was sure that I looked a lot less badass than I felt, but goddamned if I didn’t like having my skills pushed as high as they could go.

Onion gripped his sword tight, then dashed off back into the black void that was still standing there.

“Oh come on,” I said. “You’re going to hide, you miserable coward?”

His sword came flashing out of the blackness, trailing lightning, and I batted it aside, careful not to touch the infinitely sharp blade that could cut my inviolable hand.

“Are you seriously going to make me come in there?” I asked. I said it with a weary sigh, but I really didn’t want to go in there, because I really didn’t trust my ability to fight blind against someone who would be able to see.

Thankfully, for all that Onion was a master of the blade, he wasn’t terribly skilled at throwing one, probably only in the top hundred in the world. I parried a second sword thrown at me, then a third, each of them different in its effects. The risk was that he would throw out something that I couldn't actually handle, and I was certain that I hadn’t seen the totality of copyable entad effects in the area.

He threw out a volley of swords, and I parried them all with punches and kicks, scattering the replicas across the arena. I was getting irritated with him and the way he was choosing to play this, not that I expected him to kneel down and let me slit his throat.

Of course, there was another risk to letting him sit in that bubble of black for too long, not the risk that he would find some sword that would save him, but the risk that he was building something up in there.

A beam of white light pierced out from inside the bubble of darkness, popping it entirely and revealing Onion standing there with his sword raised up and pointed at me like a rifle. It went out like a lance, too fast to dodge, but I didn’t care about things like ‘too fast to dodge’, and I found myself moving even before I could have known it was coming — and still not quite making it.

My left arm flopped to the ground, lifeless, and I stared at it for only a moment before I had to contend with Onion again. He was on me in an instant, and I was fighting one-handed, severely hampered in my ability to deal with him. I didn’t know if he couldn’t use the rusted probability blade with his meta-entad sword, or was just choosing not to, but I thought I was pretty much fucked if that came out, because there were only so many times you could make strictly impossible dodges, and I would have no way of parrying the probability blade, not when it could materialize only millimeters from my skin.

I didn’t have the mental bandwidth to deal with my missing arm, I was just ignoring it, because I was allowed to. It was charred at the shoulder, missing meat and bone in a half-moon, and leaking blood slowly enough that I would probably be dead to something else before it was a real problem.

He switched swords again, this time to what was clearly Amaryllis’ flicker blade, and let the blade disappear as he swung at me. There was fuck-all that I could do about it aside from trying to dodge, but I could tell that I wasn’t fast enough, and right at the point when the hilt was pointed at my heart — nothing happened. Onion’s helm tilted down as he looked at the sword, only for a moment, and that was when I struck, using my remaining hand to drive straight forward, fingertips all aligned right at his heart.

Critical Hit!

Onion’s left arm went limp and he dropped his sword hilt, which almost immediately leapt back up into his right hand as he backed away from me. He morphed the sword again, transforming the non-functional hilt into something more useful, this one a blade of quicksilver, mercurial in how it moved. We were both fighting one-armed though, his deadened by me severing a connection in his soul, mine completely gone. I had the advantage though, because he was fighting with his off-hand and I had more than just a fist, I had my entire body, feet, elbows, and knees as well. Even lacking an arm, I was making more attacks than he could effectively parry, and it was only a matter of time before I landed something proper.

Critical Hit!

His other arm went dead, and his sword dropped to the ground again, this time not moving from where it landed.

Onion tried to keep fighting, right up until the very end. I killed him with a lightning-quick punch, delivered straight to his helm, an attack that should have broken every bone in my hand, but didn’t. Blood flowed freely from his perfectly intact helm as he fell to the arena floor, and I waited, tensed, to see whether his armor would restore him for a fourth round.

Instead, he just lay there, blood pooling under his head.

“You’re leeking,” I called to him.

With a shudder, the third green gem in his armor smoked and cracked, and then the black metal that had been on him this entire time began to twist and buckle in on itself, twisting and squeezing the meat and bone instead with sickening sounds as it collapsed in on itself. It looked like an angry god was crushing a can of soda until there was no possible room inside. I kept my eyes on it though, waiting for one last trick.

Onion Penndraig defeated!

Quest Updated: Full Court Press - With the trial-by-combat complete, you are now a member in good standing of the Lost King’s Court, obligation to military service aside. Congrats! You are also now the undisputed best swordsman in all Anglecynn, with many suspecting that you’re the best in the world. Amaryllis still has her trial ahead, but now the Court knows which way the wind blows.

Level Up!

The golden glow lifted me from the ground, with none of the pleasure that had once been attached to it, the modifications I’d made to my spirit still doing their work. I hadn’t really been paying attention to the crowds watching down from above the arena walls, but I was very aware of them now. My wounds were healed, my hit points went back to maximum, and most importantly, my missing arm completely regrew — and regrew was the operative word, because the old one was still sitting there on the floor of the arena.

The level up had been witnessed by about a thousand people, and I was guessing that was going to complicate things.

Cooldown

“I’m worried about you,” said Raven.

We were back at the Erstwhile Manor, where Amaryllis was planning out how the next day would go. The War Council had planned to hold session, but it was up for debate whether it actually would or not, given that one of their members had died in the course of a trial by combat. It was supposedly Phlox’s call, but we didn’t have a handle on whether she would want to push ahead and get things over with, or punt for as long as possible. There were pros and cons to each, and I really just couldn’t find it in myself to care. The fight with Onion hadn’t actually been that long, but it had been exhausting, and I was sure that as my skills went down to baseline, it would become even more so. I’d begged off to just decompress, and Raven had asked me if I wanted company, which I had, on the condition that it was a light and comfy company. That had lasted all of ten minutes.

“Why?” I asked. “And worried how?”

“You’re being a bit erratic,” said Raven. She folded her hands in her lap. “Part of it is being impulsive, the other part is disregard for other lives.”

“Hrm,”  I replied. “I’m going to try to not be angry or flippant about this, because I think that’s probably what you’re talking about, but the last week or so hasn’t really been all that great for me.” I took stock of what I was about to say, making an attempt to phrase it like I wasn’t an asshole. “Bethel forced herself on me,” I said. “That feeling of fear and powerlessness, of confusion … it kind of fucked with me. I’m not using that as an excuse, just trying to explain my mindset. It wasn’t long after we exiled her from the group that my mom showed up, which was its own thing, an unwelcome blast from the past —” I paused, waiting for her to tell me about some ancient civilization that had some kind of future cannon aimed at the present, because that was exactly the kind of thing that Raven would bring up when I used idioms. She just sat there, listening attentively. “Those dragons showed up to threaten us, and I found myself just having so much contempt for them. I mean, from what I heard, it was the same for you at the trial, with the court. That feeling that it was beneath you.”

“Heard from Amaryllis?” asked Raven.

“Yes,” I replied. I stretched out and ate from the plate of food I’d requested from the kitchen. It was mostly traditional Anglish fare, a bit bland for my tastes. “Confirmed with Grak, because while I trust Amaryllis to be impartial, I trust him more in this case. Contempt was exactly how he described it.”

“I have contempt for the Lost King’s Court,” Raven admitted. “Not that Uther would have ever wanted his stamp on something so vile. To follow the flower metaphor, it’s a garden filled with weeds. I’ve seen Anglecynn in hundreds of futures, you have to keep that in mind, so some of this is informed by other timelines, not by the present. They’re a low-grade tyranny, a dysfunctional family that will close ranks just enough to defend themselves from outside threats, beset with all the problems that any modern nation has, except with arrogance and a mistaken reverence of tradition layered on top of that.” She looked at me. “I shouldn’t have shown so much contempt before the council. And it doesn’t have that much bearing on what I’m trying to say to you.”

“You think that my contempt for the people who kidnapped me is misplaced,” I said. “Oh, and I hadn’t even gotten to that, the whole being kidnapped and tortured thing.”

“I think that contempt is what it is,” replied Raven. “It’s a valid reaction to seeing people doing what they’re doing. But when you have your sword to someone’s throat, it’s a bit different.”

“I killed about a dozen people in the past few days,” I said. “Maybe a bit less, maybe a bit more, I didn’t count that closely. In none of those circumstances did I realistically have the option to show mercy. And when I was able to show mercy, Pallida killed them all for me, as she should have. She called me out on it, actually.”

“I know,” replied Raven. “Pallida and I have been on speaking terms, more or less, since Mome Rath. A bit less than more. Do you think that Pallida was happy about slitting the throats of a bunch of defenseless guards?”

“I don’t know,” I replied. “I guess not. You think that I would have been?”

Raven lifted the cup of tea beside her and sipped at it. “I don’t think poorly of you. Like I said, I’m worried about you. But yes, I think that for some of them, you would have felt good about killing them. A warm glow at ending someone’s life, rather than any measure of guilt and pain over the necessity.”

“That’s how Uther would have played it?” I asked. “He laid his enemies to rest with all the pomp and circumstance that he could muster?”

“In a sense, yes,” replied Raven. “He was cold about it, sometimes, but I always had the sense that it took its toll. If he’d had his way, he wouldn’t ever have had to kill anyone. He would have been a poet, a playwright, a bard, rather than a warrior. And you … from what I know about you, you’re more a creator than Uther ever was, but there’s this anger in you, and you’re letting it free.”

“Yeah,” I said, slumping back. She was right about me. It was something that I had known about myself for a long time.

There was sometimes this sense among hunters that you were supposed to care about the deer, or feel reverence and gratitude when you took their lives. When I’d killed my first deer, I’d felt kind of disgusted because of all the blood and guts, but holy hell, I didn’t feel an ounce of appreciation for the deer itself. For a while, I felt like I must have been a sociopath or something, because I’d gone on the internet and read about what the red flags for sociopathy were, but eventually I just decided that maybe I was a bit more vicious than other people, kept in check by threats from authority and some amount of moral reasoning, rather than moral feeling. Except that as I grew older, I realized that I did actually have empathy for others. Thinking that you’re a sociopath is just something that fourteen-year-old edgelords did, and I considered myself lucky to have learned that by seventeen.

“I wanted to kill Zinnia,” I said. “I was angry with her. I didn’t actually know her, but everything that I had learned about her painted her as this horrible cunt who the world would be better off without. It was like … like a fly buzzing around, doing nothing but irritating me, but worse than that, because she did worse than that. And I’m sure that some perfect person would try to capture the fly and release it into the wild so that it could live its own life without irritating them anymore. But for me, I don’t feel bad about smooshing a fly, I don’t give a little speech about how I deeply regret killing it, I just … I want to kill it, and then I don’t kill it, because I’ve been taught not to, and convinced not to.” I sighed. “So when Pallida comes along and murders Zinnia, I’m put out, but I’m not that put out.”

“And Onion?” asked Raven.

“I mean, if you want to talk about horrible cunts,” I began, smiling at her and seeing her not smile back. My face fell, and I decided to take this seriously. “Back when I was suicidal, people tried to help me, and I just pushed past them, telling them that I was fine, that it was fine, not to worry, let’s just get on with things. I think I’d be demonstrating a real lack of intelligence not to learn from that. So I’m trying here, with you, to listen, to accept help. I can see that your heart is at least in the right place. But … Onion? In the last few days I have heard so many stories about Onion, and absolutely none of them make him look good in the slightest. Supposedly, when he was in the business of killing people in ‘self-defense’, there was this strategy he employed a few times of seducing someone’s wife, daughter, or significant other, and then in this really patriarchal display, use that as a way to bait some dude into fighting him. And by seduce … it’s really not clear that consent was involved.” I stared at Raven. “I’m saying that it’s entirely possible that Onion raped some young woman so that he could bait her father into a fight.”

“Unsubstantiated stories from his political enemies,” said Raven. “Not that I think they’re untrue stories, necessarily, but it’s easy to make a person hateable if you’re allowed to say whatever you like about them, if no one actually knows the truth but those involved. There are many, many stories about Onion, but he was one of those men whose stories multiply and grow.”

“Even if you discount the rumors,” I said. “What’s redeemable about Onion, in your view?”

“You’re asking why you should have felt anything other than glee at ending his life?” asked Raven.

“See, you put it like that, you make me sound like a psychopath,” I said. “But sure.”

“Then I don’t know,” said Raven. “But there were people who liked Onion. Did you see Phlox?” I shook my head. “She was in shock for a bit when he was killed, but then she started crying, and they had to help her out of the arena.”

“Sounds like theater to me,” I said.

“That’s what Amaryllis said too,” replied Raven with a frown. “I find it more likely that Onion wasn’t universally hated by everyone in the family. There are people like that, I don’t doubt, but he seems — seemed — well-regarded by the Host. Many people consider him to have fought his personal demons through a lifetime of effort, and won. You knew he had a wife, two sons, and a number of grandchildren?”

“I did,” I replied. “There are a lot of shitty parents out there.”

“And that might be true for Onion,” said Raven. “Or it might not be.”

“You don’t think it was wrong for me to kill him, do you?” I asked. “This is about my attitude toward killing these terrible people, rather than the actual object level outcomes?”

“It is,” replied Raven. “That’s what I’m worried about, the attitude.”

“But so long as I kill the people that proper moral reasoning dictates I kill, and don’t kill anyone else, then why does it matter?” I asked. “I spared Zinnia. I spared the guards, or at least the ones that I could. I knew that it would feel good to just murder them, but I didn’t do that, because I also knew that it was … maybe not even wrong, because there were legitimate rational arguments in favor of killing them.”

“Your attitude matters,” said Raven. “Even if I agree that you did everything right over the last three days —”

“Do you?” I asked.

Raven paused, pursing her lips, and took a drink of tea. “Perfectly right? No, of course not, but … From the incomplete picture that I have of everything you went through, it would be unfair of me to second guess you. But I do think that you jumped to altering Zinnia’s soul far before it was necessary, and in the end, you gained almost nothing from it. And you did that because you felt nothing but contempt for her, because it made you happy to warp her, to hurt her. That’s what I worry about, anyway.”

“Yeah,” I said.

I tried to put myself back in my shoes, to look over what my exact mental state had been while I was in the process of doing it. I remembered noting the vaguely troublesome sexual imagery of holding a woman down and forcing myself on her. And I remembered thinking that she deserved to get the pain stick a few times, just to even things out, that she should have felt as much suffering as I could inflict on her, just for a bit, because fuck her for what she’d done. I had wanted the visceral satisfaction of crushing the life from her. And instead I had gone with snark and pretending like it was wholly and entirely necessary to soulfuck her, which it only sort of was. It had gotten our stuff out of her handbag, and let us know that no one was immediately coming, but that was about it. She just hadn’t known that much. It was easy to say that in hindsight, but maybe it would have been easy to say in foresight too.

“I didn’t actually care that much about Onion,” I said. “I mean, he was a shitbag, and he was behind the idiotic kidnapping shit — alright, it was a little bit personal, I guess. But the fight with him, it was more about taking out all my frustrations. I made jokes. I rubbed it in. It feels so good to do that. To hurt a person that I’m completely justified in hurting, completely allowed to hurt, and then add onto that with words … I think for him, his taunts had purpose. He said something to that effect while we were fighting. A taunt is a tool in the arsenal that you’d be foolish not to use, I think that was his opinion. But for me, it was trash-talking, it was about making myself feel good, sometimes preemptively, sometimes after the fact.” I sighed. “But here’s where I’m asking, was that actually wrong?”

“It was wrong, wrong in the sense that in that arena, people were watching,” said Raven. “They’ll come away with certain opinions of you.”

“So if I’d felt the same way and then done a better job of masking it?” I asked. “That would be fine?”

“It would be better,” replied Raven. “It would show some measure of introspection and ability to resist your base impulses. You think that other people don’t take joy in snappy one-liners? There’s a reason that they show up so much in plays and books. It’s just that doing that is a sign that something, somewhere, has gone wrong for you. And knowing you, you planned those lines out.”

“I wrote down a bunch of them, yeah,” I replied, frowning.

“Do you think that it’s hilarious that Phlox cried because you cut an onion?” asked Raven. She was completely deadpan.

“Assuming that it’s legitimate grief and not some act, then no, it’s — it’s funny in a dark humor way, and I usually don’t laugh at dark humor, even if I find it funny,” I replied. “And it’s not that I’m just feeling shame, it’s that when you frame it that way, it kills my high.”

“It’s probably good for you to do whatever it takes to kill that high,” said Raven.

“Sure,” I replied. “Even if it makes me miserable? Even if it’s a way of coping with all the bad shit, all the stress, all the killing that I’m probably going to have to do one way or another?”

“I don’t know,” said Raven. “I don’t think it’s particularly healthy, from a mental standpoint, to be using humor and trash talk to cope. But you know yourself far, far better than I know you. We’re still practically strangers, though I’m glad we’re talking more.”

“I am too,” I replied. “Even if it’s a downer.” I was thinking about Onion’s kids, who were probably, what, in their forties? Thirties? It was hard to imagine Onion smiling with his grandkids. Heck, it was hard to imagine what Onion’s wife must have been like, or that he’d been a loving husband, or even just one that wasn’t abusive.

“I used to be more fun,” said Raven. “I’m not even talking about the decades I spent slacking off, though I was a little too fun then. I used to have this exuberance, and it just got filed away over time with the weight of responsibility and the endless grind of having things to do.”

“Huh,” I replied. “When you say too fun, you mean … ?”

“Irresponsible,” replied Raven. “I indulged myself without regard for the consequences.”

“I was looking for specifics,” I replied. “Not some generalities about regrettable behavior.”

Raven sighed. “Because of prurient interest?” she asked.

“I think if you speak with regret about the things you did, people will assume the worst,” I replied. “And I don’t want to assume the worst about you. So give me a day in the life of you at your most regrettable.”

Raven paused. “It went in cycles,” she said. “It wasn’t a non-stop string of things I would later regret. I would get drunk — this takes an enormous amount of alcohol for an ell, and lasts for a very long time — and sometimes take harder drugs, smoke boscleaf, rub on terrablend, never anything that would risk me being permanently damaged, but not a great way to spend a month. Sometimes I told people things that I shouldn’t have, leaking out secrets in the hopes that someone or something would stop me. Nothing that would kill anyone, but there are secrets that keep themselves, and like a fool, I would go talk about them at bars while drinking my three hundredth glass of wine, sometimes getting up on a table and shouting them, when I was out of it enough for that to seem reasonable.” She paused. “I had hollow, meaningless sex. Like the drugs, I enjoyed it in the moment, but when it was done, I felt disgusted with myself. Sometimes more than others.” She let out a breath she’d been holding. “There, does that satisfy you?”

“Yeah,” I said. “Not so bad, all things considered.” The part of me that still saw her as Maddie, the part that still thought of her as seventeen or younger, was a little uncomfortable about hearing her talking about sex, but this was a stupid thing to feel, on several levels, and I had asked, so I did my best to recalibrate. I wanted to know how many people she’d slept with, but I also didn’t want to know, and fuck if it was any of my business. She wasn’t Maddie, and even if she had been, it wouldn’t have been anything for me to worry about. “Hey, at least you didn’t kill anyone.”

“Oh,” said Raven. “I killed a few people. I spent about a decade as a very lazy vigilante.”

“You … were a superhero?” I asked.

“As I understand them, yes,” replied Raven. “I had a secret identity and everything. I was trying to recapture some of the magic that I’d had with Uther, but I never really put in the effort, it was all,” she waved her hand. “Regretful. Embarrassing.”

“Sorry,” I said. “I need to wrap my head around this, what was your superhero name? What crimes did you stop? Like … did you get recognized?”

Raven sighed. “At least this shows you can take some joy in things other than killing. During the day, I sat around my apartment, reading through the latest trashy novel or listening to music on my wax player. I was rich enough to live off the interest, and the Second Empire didn’t touch my money because of who I was. Then when night came, I would put on my cloak, a magical mask, and all my other gear, and go out looking for trouble. I called myself Night Light.”

“Holy shit, that’s amazing,” I said. “And you just … killed people?”

“Never by intent, no,” replied Raven, looking a bit pained. “But in the heat of battle, it was hard to work within the constraint of merely maiming people, especially when so many of my best entads and magics were lethal.”

“Well, that doesn’t sound good,” I said. I was thinking of the tuung that I’d thrown off the train, what felt like a lifetime ago.

Raven shrugged. “Killing only happened in exceptional circumstances. Six times over ten years. I don’t really want to go into it.”

“No, I suppose not,” I replied. She didn’t seem happy. She rarely seemed happy anyway, but in this particular case, she’d taken a turn for the morose. “Magics?” I asked. “As in … library magic?”

“Oh, sometimes,” replied Raven. “It extends outside the Infinite Library, though mostly you’d use it for finding the right book, and it’s not too much better than a card catalog. Sometimes a sufficient collection of files will create the right circumstances to use it. But no, I had two magics under my belt, both now excluded.” I waited, and she continued. “Dibbling and groove casting. They had a nice synergy. Both gone now, all that training made utterly useless.”

“I don’t even know what groove casting is,” I said. Dibbling was similar to warding, though much more short term, much faster, without the metamagic aspects, and some secondary abilities that wards couldn’t replicate, all drawing on rather abstract concepts of ground and earth. None of this had been in her biographies, which I had read before we’d met her.

“It was a form of energy shaping, building up personal magical constructs through repeat castings, a good school of magic if you’re an Ell, but otherwise a bit niche,” said Raven. “I would work the grooves while I was reading.” I resisted making the obvious joke. “Unfortunately, I chose dibbling over warding and groove casting over runes. The synergy was good. You could dibble for energy and divert that energy into the grooves, there were many possibilities.”

“Huh,” I replied. “I do wonder what it was like after the collapse of the First Empire, when there was so much magic still around, so many exclusions yet to happen. All that stuff in motion though, not just a world like before the First Empire, when the magics were mostly separated, a time when it was just all … together. Even with what we have now … it’s so much sheer stuff that I would never have included it all in a single campaign.”

“It was a mess,” said Raven. “But we can talk about it later. I wanted to go see how Amaryllis was doing with her trial prep.”

“Sure,” I replied. “But she’s standing outside the door.”

“She is?” asked Raven.

“Yup,” I replied. “I’ve been keeping us on mute. Nothing that I care about her hearing, but it seemed polite. She’s waiting for us to finish up, I think.” I tapped my head. “Multithreading.”

“And she probably wants to talk to you, not me,” said Raven. “Okay. Good luck.” She took her cup of tea with her.

Raven stopped once she was just outside the door, and had a brief conversation with Amaryllis, which Amaryllis muted. I had better vibration magic than her, but didn’t try to figure out anything sneaky, because I didn’t begrudge them a private moment. I hoped the topic of conversation was whether or not I needed another dressing down, and that the answer was no.

“How goes it?” I asked Amaryllis as she came in and sat down next to me.

“Very uncertain,” Amaryllis replied. She was still wearing the dress she’d been in at the arena, a very pink thing that seemed a bit too girly for her, at least so far as I could gauge such things. She still looked fantastic in it. “Are you ready to come help?”

“I don’t think I did very well in court yesterday,” I said. “And Raven’s given me some stuff to think about.”

“I still value your input,” said Amaryllis. “Even if your political instincts are complete dogshit. Even if you’re a bit murder-happy at the moment.”

“Please, please don’t tell me that killing Onion wasn’t a win for us,” I replied. “I don’t think I could take it.” When I got back to the staging area, there had been a look in her eyes, and while she’d said all the right words about how I had done well, how she was relieved, there was something that rang false about it.

“It’s a win,” said Amaryllis. “It’s so much of a win that there’s barely even a point in continuing on with this trial. The quest text said it, and it wasn’t a clue I needed: they know which way the wind is blowing. Rosemallow got more than a few calls. The news coverage is nothing but beaming, and not just because Rosemallow controls a lot of the news. There are certainly a lot of people who are very angry about the outcome, but Juniper, a lot of people are thinking that it would be suicidal to stand against you. Once everything with the trial is concluded, after we’ve slithered our way out of military service, we have an opportunity for real change. Rosemallow is talking about the next steps, and it looks like there’s going to be a Second Grand Reconciliation after all.”

“Does Rosemallow like me now?” I asked.

“She’s pretending to,” said Amaryllis. “You could be a little less casual around her.”

“Well, if it’s good, then why is everyone so intent on being a bummer?” I asked. “Aside from Pallida, who genuinely seemed happy for me.”

“I don’t know about the others, but I wasn’t prepared for what that fight would look like,” said Amaryllis. “Not just how fast it was moving, but all the absurd, impossible things that went on. And I was just sitting there, helpless, not able to do anything but watch.”

“I heard you got into it with the referee?” I asked.

“I did,” said Amaryllis. “I argued that the meta-entad was a violation of the rules. It was outside magic. Obviously that didn’t go our way.”

“And you did something with the flickerblade at the critical moment,” I said, though that was more of a guess.

“Grak did,” said Amaryllis. “He was watching the match through his temporal plate, the only one really able to keep up with what was happening, and then only barely. He made the ward around the flickerblade, something special, I didn’t get the details. Oh, he says the probability blade is unrecoverable. Sorry.”

“It’s fine,” I said. “We’re coming into a truckload of entads soon, right?”

“We are,” said Amaryllis. She paused, then moved toward me and took a piece of food from my plate. “Juniper, we might legitimately be in the endgame.”

“You’re thinking that I’m right about going after Fel Seed?” I asked.

“I am,” replied Amaryllis. “I don’t know how much higher you can actually go. This escalation —”

“I still need to fight a dragon,” I said. “And there are at least thirteen opponents that I can name pretty easily.”

“So you don’t want to be at the end?” asked Amaryllis.

“I do,” I replied. “But I did almost die today, and I was kind of cheating. I need to grind up Grak’s loyalty, the doe’s loyalty, your loyalty. And … any run at Fel Seed would require Bethel one way or another, not to mention Valencia.”

“You’re sobering up,” said Amaryllis.

“Maybe,” I said. “I’m still so fucking angry with your family though. And unless Phlox strokes out and Hyacinth kills herself, they’re still going to be there, plus however many other people were actually involved. If the new world order we’re dealing with is fighting them tooth and nail over public policy, them trying to subvert us, or kill us … you’re thinking long term for Anglecynn and Miunun, on the scale of years. Dealing with these same horrible people for years, in all their permutations? Yeah, it really makes me want to take all of our resources and pour them into going after Arthur, whether that’s through Fel Seed or not.”

“Sorry my family is terrible,” said Amaryllis. She gave me a soft smile. “But they’re your family too now.”

“Am I taking your name, by the way?” I asked.

“Did you want to?” asked Amaryllis.

“Not really, no,” I replied. “I just thought it might be politically helpful or something. Shows that I’m a team player, maybe.”

“I’ll be taking your name,” said Amaryllis. “It’s Not Done, but we can do things that are Not Done now, and the more of them we do, the more people will expect and understand that the rules are different for us. We’re going to have a wedding, naturally, something more than jumping a broom.”

I had no idea what ‘jumping a broom’ meant, except from context, but wasn’t really in the mood for a lesson on Aerb idioms. “I guess that will be fine,” I said. “You think that the rest of the trial is going to be a breeze? And we’re out of the woods, so to speak?”

“I would never say that out loud,” replied Amaryllis. “But I think that we’re set up well for the long term, with only a few threads left to be closed. And once they are, it’s possible we’ll have a little bit of downtime. If I do get declared innocent of desertion, I’ll have my funds and entads out of trust, which will give us some power. Military service … it should be easy enough to dodge, I hope. Obviously I’m angling for the long term, plans that will take years to implement, but if you decide on Fel Seed … we’ll find a way. And it might be the right course of action.”

“Yeah,” I said. I let out a breath and ate a bit more. Amaryllis made no move to leave, nor to fill the silence. I was thinking about Fel Seed, and everything that I knew about him, and how bad of an idea it probably was to go there, whether Uther was there or not, whether that was the path to godhood. “So you’re not worried about me?”

“No,” said Amaryllis. “Not more than usual. You’ve been handling your emotions better than you normally do, no offense. The marriage was impulsive, and the trial by combat was impulsive, but I can’t say that your instincts were entirely wrong, and even if you really viscerally wanted to murder Onion in particular, you went about it by training and working through plans. Maybe I’m biased because I’m your wife, but I think some of the concerns from the others are overblown.”

“And who among our shadowy cabal is arrayed against me?” I asked.

“Grak is concerned,” said Amaryllis. “As I understand it, he’s drawing some parallels to his own actions in the aftermath of his dwarfhold perishing. In his defense, you did mention murdering many, many members of the Court in cold blood.”

“Sure,” I said. “I’ll talk to him.”

“Solace thinks that you’re too wrapped up in yourself,” said Amaryllis. “But the travel isn’t all that good for the locus, and practically a whole day without sunlight wasn’t either, it’s understandable that she’s on edge.”

“I’ll talk to her too,” I replied, though I was looking forward to that conversation a lot less. Grak was a friend, if a perpetually dour and self-doubting one, but Solace was … well, like how I imagined a co-worker being, but a better frame of reference was probably someone I’d gotten stuck on a group project with.

“Pallida wishes that you were more like me,” said Amaryllis. “More ruthless, more pragmatic, more in control of your emotions. But I don’t think she’s worried, because she sees Uther as being considerably worse. From what I understand, there’s a disagreement between her and Raven over whether Uther was cold-bloodedly manipulating the narrative as he saw it, or whether he was simply insane, or some combination of those.”

“Huh,” I said.

“And of course Gemma is extremely disappointed in you,” said Amaryllis.

I let that one sit for a bit. “Please tell me that’s a joke.”

“It’s a joke,” said Amaryllis. “Sorry, I thought you would find it funny.”

“I’ve said like three sentences to her,” I replied. “I legitimately thought that she might hate me for some reason. Like the fact that she was on board with killing me when she thought that I was the next Uther, which, uh, is kind of the party line now?”

“No, you’ll like her,” said Amaryllis. “If and when you get to know her, anyway. Don’t feel pressured. She wants to help, not to be your friend.”

“Okay,” I said, relaxing slightly.

“Sorry,” said Amaryllis. “Do you want me to go get Grak?” she asked.

“I mostly want to sit here and not think,” I said. “But sure, maybe Grak and I can sit here and not think together. Actually, I’ll go into the bottle, if we have it in sunlight?” The sun was still out.

“Solace would appreciate that,” replied Amaryllis. “We’re going to need to talk about the marriage soon though, because there will be some interviews, not just the official ones, but a few for the radio and newspapers as well. Pre-scripted, pre-recorded, softballs, and through outlets that we control, but I’d still like some prep.”

“I bet you would kill for the time chamber right now,” I said. I gave a faint smile that faded quickly.

“Not worth the costs, not at the moment,” said Amaryllis. There was a hardness in her eyes, more so than normal. “I hate to pile social obligations on top of you, but after everything that’s happened, it would probably be nice for you to send Valencia a letter, if you have time.”

“Sure,” I replied. I sighed and sank into my chair a bit. “Thanks for everything, by the way.”

“Of course,” replied Amaryllis.

“Sorry I blew up at you and said we should kill your whole family,” I said.

“It’s not a problem, Juniper,” replied Amaryllis. “I would hope that if I got heated, or lost my cool, you would try your best to be patient and understanding with me. We’re partners.”

“I hope I can live up to your rosy picture of me,” I said, feeling a bit sad, because I knew that didn’t sound like me.

“Oh,” said Amaryllis. “I wasn’t registering a prediction. I was saying what I hoped, not what I thought would actually happen.”

“Ouch,” I replied. “But fair.” I gripped the armrests, then pushed myself to my feet. “Alright. Bottle time.”

“Before you go, can I do anything for you?” she asked. “I know you’re coming down off the high of victory and having so much raw power, and I doubt that Raven was gentle about calling you out, but I don’t want you to crater.”

“No, no risk of that,” I replied. “All I need is time, and so long as the only things that I get pressure on are relatively low stakes, I should be fine. Going a week without a kidnapping, torture, et cetera would probably do wonders for me. I’m not going to say that we’re out of the woods, because I don’t want to tempt fate, but I’m hopeful that we have some downtime soon.”

“Soon,” agreed Amaryllis. “But not that much of it. Perisev gave us a deadline, and there have been fairly consistent reports of a gold dragon circling Caledwich, so Tommul has his eye on us.” She hesitated. “I’m just trying to set expectations for how much of a rest we’ll have.”

“I don’t suppose that Rosemallow knows of a regular, non-stupidly-powerful time chamber that we could use?” I asked.

“She does,” said Amaryllis. “I’ve talked to her about it, and she sometimes uses it in conjunction with the entad she showed us. It’s small and cramped though, little more than a capsule hotel. There are larger ones that we might rent, but they’re expensive, and typically small. We can though, if you’d like. Pallida made some interesting bets.”

“Interesting how?” I asked. “She was supposed to put money on me winning.”

“You can talk to her about her negligence,” said Amaryllis. “But I will guarantee that she knows bookmakers better than you do. I know one of the bets was that you would win after getting an arm or leg cut off. Another was a bet that the match would last longer than ten minutes. I also think she bet you would win without a sword. Many of her bets were losing bets, but they were at such high margins that she had to threaten a few of the bookmakers in order to collect.”

“So you’re saying that we’re richer than we already were, which was quite rich,” I said.

“I know it doesn’t really matter, I just thought it might help to hear,” said Amaryllis. “And I wanted to point out that if your mental wellbeing is on the line, then to the extent that problem can be solved by throwing money at it, we can definitely do that. Obviously with the cat out of the bag, we’ll be offering protection to those who want or need it as well.”

My mind went to my parents and the alternate versions of my friends. “Good,” I replied. “I’m going to, at the least, write a letter to … fuck, Craig, Maddie, my mom, my dad, Tiff … not looking forward to all that.”

“I can write them,” said Amaryllis. “I know that you sometimes find the social aspects draining.”

“You don’t need to do that,” I replied. “I mean, you are better at it, and I really, really don’t want to do it, but I feel like it’s something that I should do as a responsible person.”

“We can work on it together,” said Amaryllis. “One of the things that I agree with Pallida on is that you often do things because you think that you have to, rather than because they make sense to do. Working together will be a compromise, so you can have some of the load taken off while still fulfilling your sense of obligation.”

“Sure,” I replied, twisting my mouth into a small frown. “You’re not overworked?”

“Only in the sense that there’s more work to do than there are Amaryllises to do it,” replied Amaryllis. “I really should get going though, and I think some time in the bottle is in order. You did well in the arena today, spite aside. I wanted you to know that.”

Grak had come into the bottle earlier and removed his armor. After a moment’s thought, I switched Alvion’s Vambrace over and then stowed it in a small bag at my hip, as close to unarmed and unarmored as I normally got, kidnapping and frantic last-ditch efforts aside.

The bottle was on a table in the terrace of the Erstwhile Manor, warded to the gills and in direct sunlight. It felt late, given all the plotting and planning we’d done, the run-up to the fight, and the fight itself, but it was only around dinner time, and the light was still coming in strong.

Grak was with the locus, patting its flank and speaking softly into its ear, but Solace was nowhere to be seen. He was wearing one of his almost painfully mundane outfits, khakis and a salmon-colored buttoned-down shirt. It was about as far away from his traditional dwarven outfits as you could have gotten, agkrioglian to its core, and a bit more stylish than he normally wore. I decided to take that as a good sign.

“How are you doing?” I asked him, speaking Groglir. I figured that it didn’t matter to the doe.

“I did something novel at the arena,” Grak replied.

“Oh yeah?” I asked.

Grak nodded. “I made a split ward, only half of an entad’s function altered.”

“It might have saved my life,” I replied with a nod. “Are there any tricks that it will lead to?”

“Many,” replied Grak. “I’ll have to speak with Mary about it. There are surely some cursed entads we could use safely and others we could use without their associated costs.”

“What, seriously?” I asked. “We can just … I don’t know, use the clonal kit without paying it back?”

“I don’t know,” replied Grak. “It’s possible. I have never heard of anyone doing what I have done. I don’t know if it’s possible for others.” He ran his hand over the doe’s soft fur. “We conceptualize magic as being two dimensional, with blocks being given over to different magics. The entad block is large, but each entad is noted as essentially a point, however wide the spectrum is. But that’s not true.”

He was always so much more eloquent when he spoke in Groglir. Whenever we switched over to Anglish, it felt like listening to him through a straw that only allowed a small part of his personality.

“I appreciate it,” I said.

“I had been working on a way to kill Bethel,” said Grak. Groglir had lots of words for killing, and the one that Grak had chosen was rinhelonidiki, a complex word that was typically used for death-through-alteration, almost (but not quite) exclusively by the hands of a soul mage.

“You were looking for a weapon to use against her,” I said.

“No,” replied Grak. “A weapon would be an annihilation ward. That would be simple enough. This technique was for base alteration of who she was.” He looked rather grim about it. “If it’s necessary, I can do it.”

“Alright,” I said. I wasn’t sure how I felt about that.

“You would need to lure her into the ward,” Grak continued. “And then I would need to anchor it to her. From there the work would begin. To bring her back to a level of usefulness would take days, perhaps weeks of trial and error, altering her.”

“That’s nothing that we need to worry about just yet,” I replied.

“I worry about exclusion,” said Grak. He wasn’t looking at me, instead keeping his attention focused on the doe.

“For that?” I asked.

“I’m pushing the edges of what’s possible with warding,” said Grak. He had a faraway look in his eyes. “I can see some of the possibilities. There are ways to wedge things open. But if warding is excluded, millions will die, and I will become nothing.”

“I am against millions of people dying,” I said with a nod. “But if you lose warding, whether through exclusion or not, you’re still a member of this party. You’re still our friend. It doesn’t get you out of doing your best to live a good life. If you wanted to leave the team, I would understand — I’d understand even if there weren’t an exclusion — but you’re not defined by your worth as a warder. Not to me, and if that’s how you view yourself, you shouldn’t.”

Grak took a moment to look at me. I hoped that I hadn’t said something wrong, that it was okay to tell him that we would survive without him. It was hard to read his expressions.

“Thank you,” he finally said.

Loyalty Increased: Grak lvl 20!

Companion Passive Unlocked: Warded (Grak)!

“Huh,” I said. “Loyalty up.”

“Was that why you said it?” asked Grak, furrowing his brow.

“No,” I replied. “How shitty of a person would I have to be to tell a friend that they were only worthwhile because of the valuable service they were providing?” I frowned at the message. “I do want to talk more about that, but you didn’t get Symbiosis. Would you rather I read it, or wait until we’re done talking?”

“You can read it,” said Grak.

“We do value you,” I said. “And you are our friend. I know that the last few days have been, frankly, insane,” I dipped into Anglish for ‘frankly’, as there didn’t seem to be a suitable replacement in Groglir, “but we should have some downtime coming up, and that means that we can talk about things that don’t have any relationship to the fate of the world or the machinations of its god.”

“Read the virtue,” said Grak.

“We’ll play some Ranks, eat some meals together, have a movie night — alright, alright, I’ll read it,” I said. He had been giving me a look, like I was doing a bit that he didn’t appreciate, which wasn’t what I’d been going for.

Warded: Grak is slowly coming to an understanding of di era and da nad place within the world. Grak can create wards around da nad own body which follow the contours of da nad skin as easily as if it were a cube of equal volume, and anchor them to di era as easily as da can anchor to Aerb. If warding is ever excluded, Grak’s ability to make wards will not be affected. Grak no longer needs a wand to make wards.

“It’s powerful,” said Grak, after I finished reading it to him. “It’s not Symbiosis.”

“Yeah,” I replied. “I’m not sure which I would have preferred, from a strict utility standpoint, but it does mean that you’ll be one of the safest people on the hex. Ward up against everything, then … I don’t know, are you invincible? I mean no, obviously not, but pretty damned close.”

“I will need to think about it,” said Grak. He lifted his hand from the doe, which he’d been rubbing, and looked at the tips of his fingers. “With annihilation wards I could kill with a touch.”

“Maybe,” I said. “Blood and bone … but you would need to be able to extend the wards a fair bit beyond your skin, and —”

“I wasn’t speculating,” said Grak.

I pulsed vibration magic to give me my crude warder’s sight and saw Grak wreathed in wards. The one around his hand extended three inches from his fingertips. It was almost definitely enough to kill someone with.

“Yikes,” I said. Grak had done his fair share of killing, but he wasn’t a killer, not like Amaryllis was, and certainly not like Pallida.

“I had been wondering what being a multimage would be like,” said Grak. He flexed his hand. “This is good too.”

“So long as you’re not disappointed,” I replied. I didn’t mention the obvious suspect timing, especially since it didn’t really matter, and I didn’t know whether it had been fudged for or against me, if it had been fudged at all. Maybe it wasn’t the timing at all, but rather the way that the passive seemed to respond to Grak’s direct wish, though the virtue outright stating that a warding exclusion was on the table was troubling.

We spent the rest of the day with the locus, testing out the limits of Grak’s new powers, and generally trying to keep up a good mood. I kept going back to what Raven had said about Onion, and whether it was possible that he wasn’t uniformly bad, which didn’t at all make me regret killing him, but did make some of the jokes I’d made feel a little sour. After two hours or so, the light started to fade, and Solace finally came back from tending to her flowers to join us. I slept in the bottle, in the old nook that I’d used to share with Fenn, and in the morning, we went to the trial.

Coda I

The remainder of the trial was an anticlimax. Onion was dead, and Phlox was hospitalized, which was a particularly bad sign for her given that she had access to so much magical healing. With the chair incapacitated and the vice chair dead, the War Council still had to move things along, and their first business of the day was not to deal with the trial, but to do some rearranging of the council’s structure. This took quite a bit of time and a lot of procedure, but eventually Onion’s position of vice chair was filled by Camellia, who I understood, from Amaryllis’ quick signing, to be a relatively impartial compromise who had leaned in our direction even before the realignment. Phlox would have a week to recover enough, and then Camellia would become chair, with the vice chair going to someone else. Once all that was sorted, the trial itself was resumed.

With the two main players removed, there was very little opposition. What was someone like Willow, a distant cousin of Amaryllis, going to do? Take up the attack? I felt a little bit bad for Amaryllis, because she’d wanted this trial to be a legitimizing one, not just in the sense that she would be cleared of the crime, but in the sense that she would demonstrate herself as an upstanding member of the court who could both follow the written and unwritten rules, as well as win within them. A win was a win, naturally, but this was less of a win than it could have been. With the outcome of the trial virtually assured, there were still a few matters left to clear up though.

“Motion to question Juniper Smith a second time,” said Bartholomew.

“Point of information, for what cause?” asked Camellia. She wasn’t as fast on the draw as Phlox had been, and not nearly as confident, but I had to imagine that she hadn’t at all been prepared for filling this role.

“Juniper Smith’s display in the arena yesterday raised a number of questions,” replied Bartholomew. “His marriage to Amaryllis Smith née Penndraig and the nature of their relationship raises more. It is my belief that the declaration and acceptance of trial by combat happened at a pace that did this trial no service, and while I sympathize with the council’s desire to close this matter quickly, it shouldn’t be done without exhausting the lines of inquiry.”

Bartholomew Penndraig was a bit of an odd duck, and I only knew anything about him because he was a relative rarity: someone who had married into the family and actually gotten some measure of political power out of it, through the same system of elevation and joint voting right that I now enjoyed with Amaryllis. When I’d heard that, I’d expected him to be some kind of cutthroat social climber, right at home among the Penndraigs, but it turned out that he was just really into governance, a policy and legal wonk, and his wife was as close as a princess typically got to apolitical. In the here and now, he was reminding me of a kid that raises his hand after class and tells the teacher that they forgot to give out homework.

Only in this case, while it was pretty clear there was nothing more to come from the trial itself, there were plenty of people really wanting some hot gossip about the cool new kid from out of town.

I stood before the War Council in my space plate, sleek armor that revealed my face even though it was solid throughout. I was only a little bit more decked out in entads than I had been the last time, having gone through what Rosemallow could supply, and having acquired the inks that I needed to make a few of my own custom pseudoentads, pushing as hard as I could to make them not be second-rate. I wasn’t expecting shit to go down, but by the gods I would be ready for whatever came my way. The Ring of Upward Bliss was on my finger, not even requiring a switch to a different loadout with Alvion’s Vambrace, and I had a bandolier of bones and fairies as well.

On my hip was a loaner sword from Rosemallow, one of the few investable entads that she didn’t have tied up in contracts or other concerns. It wasn’t anything too special, a sword that had a mild illusory effect, its visual appearance to other people trailing behind its actual position by two seconds. It had a very fancy sheath though, and an impressive hilt. I had an amulet around my neck (short-range bug manipulation) and a cloak (which could light up on a dimmer switch), both of them incredibly minor entads, also loaners, whose purpose was more to look impressive than to actually do anything. The hope was that people would remember what I had done against Onion, then see me in full entad gear and fall in line.

I got a lot of questions about the particulars of my power, and stonewalled almost all of them, trying not to display my contempt for what was supposed to be a trial to determine whether or not Amaryllis was guilty of desertion.

“I’m sorry that I’m electing not to answer so many of these questions,” I eventually replied. “I very much expect my life to be in near constant danger from a variety of sources into the foreseeable future, and revealing too much has the potential to expose weaknesses. Even if it doesn’t, people will try novel methods, some of which I already know about, and others that might have a chance of hurting me or the people I care about.”

That slowed down the questions, but didn’t stop them entirely.

I got questions about my relationship with Amaryllis, which I answered as honestly as possible, and questions about dream-skewering, which I answered mostly with the truth, leaving out the part where there was an alternate of Sporsan back on Earth with a lot of the same people, the part with all the advanced technology, and the part about my complicated relationship with Aerb’s creation.

“And there’s no magic on this ‘Earth’?” asked Lisi, who, if I had to guess, was asking just to help exhaust the council’s desires for questions or eat time.

“No, there’s no magic,” I replied. “On Earth the term ‘magic’ means something other than what it means here. It’s used as a shorthand for things that are unexplained. Before I came here — which is what happened from my perspective, though that’s not the opinion of the Cerebral College — I didn’t have any idea that some of the things I’ve seen on Aerb were actually possible.”

“Including your own impossible feats?” asked Camellia.

“Including those,” I replied. “Like I said, in the months that I’ve been on Aerb, I’ve been picking up a lot, and it’s taken special effort to stay within the laws regarding magic as Amaryllis has outlined them.” That was fucking laughable, and it was a good sign that no one laughed.

“I want to put forward a number of questions about citizenship,” said Bartholomew.

“Motion to close questioning,” said Lisi.

“Point of order,” said Bartholomew, but before he could elaborate, Camellia raised a hand.

“The motion to close questioning is due to our time constraints,” said Camellia. “I’m sure that we would all like to have this ongoing trial closed quickly enough so that we’ll have time this session to speak on the matter of who will replace Onion as the supreme commander of the Host. Bartholomew, do you anticipate that your questions on citizenship will have a large impact on the trial of Amaryllis, especially given that the question of Juniper’s innocence has already been settled?”

“I do,” replied Bartholomew. “Both Juniper and Amaryllis claim dual citizenship, which is only a non-problem insofar as the Republic of Miunun isn’t recognized as a polity by Anglecynn. Their testimony, on the other hand, has been hampered by claims of classification which rest within the authority of Miunun, and prevent us from having the full picture, which is necessary to establish the validity of both the duress and necessity clauses that Amaryllis has put forward.”

“There are things that I could tell you that would instantly kill you,” I said, which was only a little bit of a bluff.

“You’re out of order,” Camellia said to me, but it was only a mild rebuke.

“I would appreciate a clarification on what that means,” said Bartholomew.

“As a point of order, we’re still on the motion to close questioning,” replied Camellia. “Do we have a second?”

“Second,” came one of the council members, one of the ones whose telepresence was a rabbit.

I was thankful that the motion passed and I was able to sit back down, no longer waiting for the next attack on the one hand and trying to give as little out as I could on the other. I’d told a few lies, most of them to paper over the stories we were telling, but nothing that anyone had jumped on, and I definitely did get the sense that this was all pro forma, without the intensity of grilling that I’d gotten two days before.

Amaryllis had to go before the council again, to answer a bevy of questions in the same way that I had, some of them following from my testimony, some from those few council members that had actually read through some of the documentation and evidence provided to prove various claims. She was asked about Sulid Isle and the testimony of the entad prison there, about the non-anima that was claimed to be with us (which had to be handled very carefully to avoid outright perjury, given the evidence that might someday come to light), about the origin of the tuung, and all kinds of things, for which she had largely satisfactory answers. There was some implication from a few members of the council that these other issues would need to be brought up with either the Empire or in closed-door council sessions, but that was all for another day.

On the issue of desertion, it was fairly clear-cut. Did Amaryllis avoid reporting in to the Host for reasons of necessity and duress?

“The nays have it,” announced Camellia. “By the authority of the War Council, Amaryllis Penndraig is declared not guilty of the crime of desertion. Her assets, which were held in trust, will be returned to her. Her term of military service with the Host, which was to be two years, stands, but that matter is beyond the current purview of the War Council.”

I waited for the quest to update, and frowned when it didn’t.

Amaryllis seemed legitimately happy and relieved, with a wave of emotion washing over her. She looked at me with bright eyes and then gave me a kiss on the lips, which was when I began to question whether this was all just a performance for the council and the people watching from the upper tier of the War Room. I kissed her back anyway, deciding that there was no harm in enjoying it.

We left the War Room not long after that, not waiting to see who they ultimately decided was going to be the next head of the Host. The discussion and negotiation wasn’t likely to conclude in a single day anyway: last time this had happened, when Onion had taken the spot, there had been three weeks of intense political argument.

Hyacinth was standing just outside the doors to the War Room, waiting for us. She was wearing black, mourning garb, without any of the entads I had seen her with in either Boastre Vino or Li'o. I boosted vibration magic for some warder’s sight, and the only magic I saw on her was the pendant around her neck, not something that had shown up in soul sight, the pure black gem in the center made of obsidian or something like it, the metal of the chain likewise black. It fit in really well, I would give it that, but coordinating entads with outfits seemed dumb to me.

“You won,” she said. Her eyes were red, and her face was puffy. She’d been crying, or arranged it to look like she’d been crying. She wasn’t wearing makeup, which contributed a bit to the effect: I had only seen her a handful of times, but she had always been wearing a fair amount.

“You should have taken the deal,” said Amaryllis. “You could have had ten percent. Onion would still be alive right now.”

“He killed Yarrow and Zinnia,” said Hyacinth, talking about me like I wasn’t there. “He killed Larkspur.”

“These are strong accusations without any proof,” said Amaryllis.

No one else was around us, just the Armateurs. There were bailiffs, but they were inside, and the members of the public who had come to watch the open session were a floor up from us, which had a little more lax security. There was a part of me that just wanted to admit to everything, not necessarily to rub it in her face, but just to have some kind of proper conclusion. The quest wasn’t over, and that meant that there was some kind of dangling thread. I was pretty sure that Hyacinth was it.

“You’re going to get away with it,” said Hyacinth. “You know we would never have done what we did if we’d known what you were. It’s all just so,” she stopped and choked back a sob, putting a delicate hand to her mouth.

“And what did you do?” asked Amaryllis. “Are you willing to admit to your crimes?”

“Not here,” said Hyacinth, shaking her head. “Somewhere else, somewhere private. With Phlox poisoned, I’m the only one left, and I’m willing to throw myself at your feet. But not here.” Phlox being poisoned was news to me, but it might have been more theater.

“I have a policy of never moving to a second location,” I said.

“He’s right,” said Amaryllis. “We’re not going anywhere with you.”

“I lost the baby,” said Hyacinth. Her hand was touching her stomach. Tears had started running down her face. “This morning. Was it your doing?”

“No,” I said. “And whatever happened to Phlox, it was probably more about her age, the shock, the stress, not poison. We don’t poison people.” That was if anything had actually happened to Phlox at all. Faking a sickness wasn’t impossible.

“Juniper,” said Amaryllis, placing a hand on my arm. “Allow me?”

“Sure,” I replied. Hyacinth was looking between us, tears still flowing.

“Hyacinth, this wasn’t a game to be won or lost,” said Amaryllis. “We were never trying to hurt anyone. When we are attacked, we will defend ourselves, but that doesn’t mean that we can’t be allies in the future, if we can have any kind of assurance that your word means something.”

“When he killed Onion, was that in self-defense?” asked Hyacinth, clutching her hands into fists. “Was that so pure and noble?”

“It was allowed within the laws of this kingdom,” said Amaryllis, eyebrows drawing together. “Our uncle volunteered —”

“Uncle,” spat Hyacinth. “He was nothing to you.”

“He was family,” said Amaryllis. It was sometimes frightening how good she was at lying.

“When my father died, Onion did his part to raise me, to guide me,” said Hyacinth. She had her teeth clenched, the muscles on her neck straining. If this was all an act, then I had no idea what she was trying to get out of us. There was no way that either Amaryllis or I were going to go somewhere with her, no matter how upset she seemed, no matter what she said. I’d been burned in the really, really recent past. “He put me together with Larkspur, he helped me to reach my potential, he cared about us, not as pieces to be moved around, which is all Rosemallow cares for you, but like actual family.”

“I’m sure that his death has hit you hard,” said Amaryllis. “What you need now isn’t to be talking to us, it’s intensive counseling. With everything that’s happened, the recent deaths, it’s no wonder that it’s taken its toll on you.” She was so perfectly calm and understanding that I was getting a knot of tension in my gut. I was sure that I wasn’t doing nearly as good at cloaking how I felt, which was a combination of guilt and anger. Understanding and compassion were there too, buried somewhere, hidden by distrust.

“I will not allow you to take this kingdom,” said Hyacinth. My hand went to my sword, almost involuntarily. Clearly she wasn’t planning to throw herself at our feet. “To have you come in, — there was a time when I would have stood aside and allowed our institutions to crumble, looking out only for myself, too meek to stand against you. I was a shy a la buff, Shia—”

I clamped down on her with vibration magic at the same time I dashed forward and pressed my fingers against her collarbone, stilling her in place. She was trying to move her throat, I could feel it, and I was stopping her. I’d been too late. The summon had gone out, it was just a question of whether it would be answered.

The Armateurs turned on me at once. I might have been married, but I wasn’t a Penndraig by most magical accountings, and I had definitely laid hands on Hyacinth. The automatons attacked, six of them converging on me at once, and more of them running from down the halls. I only had a split second to consider whether I wanted to do this fight pinned in one place by keeping Hyacinth stilled, and decided against it, blasting her with concussive force from vibration magic, and tearing the entad from her neck, which I tossed to the side. The last thing I did, more on impulse than through calculation, was to stab her through the throat so that if she woke up, she wouldn’t be able to get any words out.

And then I was fighting the Armateurs, rather a lot of them at once, using a sword borrowed from Rosemallow and as much magic as I could handle through multithreading. I’d been working on that for some time now, and it was difficult, but I was outputting more offensive power than before, blasting away one Armateur with gem magic, another with a big blast of vibration magic, coordinating my movements burning blood and bone, not quite going all-out, because I had my bandolier, and a few special bones in it that I was hoping I would be able to save for —

I spotted him from the corner of my eye, a fully naked man walking down the hallway. He had a thick beard and a serious expression. He was just walking, but still moving fast, the kind of way you do when you’re in a hurry to get somewhere, or just about to break out into a run.

It was Hollywood actor Shia LaBeouf.

Quest Accepted: Where’s the Beef?

Even just fighting the Armateurs was hard enough. The last fight I had been in was the one with Onion, and it had been completely different, my skills hitting the roof of what was possible, my magics locked out so there wasn’t so much to think about. Now it felt like I was moving at a glacier’s pace, and thinking about so many things at once that I needed at least another ten threads to process it all.

The problem with the Armateurs was that most of my attacks were fucking useless against them. As a normal blade-bound, my sword wasn’t sharp enough to cut straight through metal, which meant that it was only good for the parry. Close range gem magic hit hard enough to crumple armor, just from the sheer force of all the projectiles hitting at once, but it still left them in fighting shape, and I couldn’t even do it too many times before being drained.

I tried passion magic, a few varieties in the span of seconds, and the cutting force of anger was clearly the one to go for, but it was hard to force while still trying to parry swords.

And Shia LaBeouf was still coming, almost to me.

Amaryllis had been busy herself, not helping me to fight the Armateurs, but using Sable to slap a breathing mask onto Hyacinth and store her away in extradimensional space. Once that was done, which must have been an agonizingly long ten seconds for her, she began going after the Armateurs, not with violence, but with Sable, ten seconds on each of them. One of the drawbacks to Sable was that anyone put into it could instantly push themselves back out, but that didn’t apply to entads. She had two of them gone at around the time she spotted the Actual Cannibal.

“Horror movie rules,” I called to Amaryllis. I tried to maneuver the fight as she sucked up more of the Armateurs, attempting to position myself so that I had them between the Cannibal and myself. I had no idea whether he would go after them, or if they would buy me some time, but I had no idea what else to do.

“Teleport out?” asked Amaryllis as another Armateur was sucked into Sable.

It was an option. Hyacinth had called down Actual Cannibal Shia LeBeouf, not us, and he didn’t always kill absolutely everyone when he came, there were sometimes survivors who would walk out of the wreckage in a blood-soaked daze. There were two main problems (that I could not at all focus on), the first being that he might come after us anyway, because that was definitely within his ability to do and in keeping with horror movie rules, and the second being that we were in a big building chock full of people, and if anyone could actually incapacitate the star of Transformers: Dark of the Moon, it was us.

“Paper bag,” I called to her.

But as always, she was a step ahead of me, throwing me the brown paper bag even as the words were still leaving my lips.

This one probably takes some explaining.

“What is this line here?” asked Reimer. “Why can we not take a paper bag?”

I had printed off the rules to Actual Cannibal Shia LeBeouf in advance of us playing, using the school’s printer, and Reimer was going over them with a fine-toothed comb, which really wasn’t what a one page roleplaying system needed. The first time we’d been playing without any rules but what I told them, not that the single sheet of rules had that much more. There was, however, a single line that had caught his attention.

The item in your possession can be virtually anything with the exception of the following:

A working cellphone or other communication device.
Large quantities of ammo.
Items that immediately and completely resolve the situation.
Paper bags with which to trap Shia Labeouf.

“The rules imply that if you have a paper bag, you can trap him,” said Arthur.

“But … why?” asked Reimer.

“Doylist or Watsonian?” asked Arthur. It was a dichotomy that we used with some frequency, though I didn’t really like it. Watsonian was in-character, Doylist was outside it. I had no idea why you would use those terms when diegetic and non-diegetic existed.

“Doylist is easy,” said Craig. “Because it’s funny.”

“Didn’t he wear a bag on his head?” asked Tiff.

“Who?” asked Reimer, smiling a bit.

“Nice try,” said Tiff. For our second session, we’d instituted a rule, a rap on the knuckles if you said his name, which had the obvious consequence of people trying to trick each other. “It was to an awards show or something, a year or two ago. Full suit, paper bag on head.”

“Alright,” said Reimer. “But in terms of the game, does that actually work? And can it be any kind of bag, or does it have to be paper?”

“In theory,” I said, trying to work this out. “In theory, your character wouldn’t know one way or another, so it would be moot, but,” I had recently been reading up on improv theater, and a game of ACSLB was far far more improv than any other kind of roleplaying game we normally played, as I’d learned the first time. “You’ve heard stories. Myths. Some of them true, some obviously not. One of them goes like this: a group of teens had gone to an old, abandoned insane asylum to hang out and get high, as the youths often do. None of them came home. Eventually the police got involved, and it was early in the morning the next day, before sunrise, that the grisly scene was discovered. All the delinquents were dead, their blood painting the walls, but standing in one of the rooms, with corpses surrounding him, was a completely naked man, unmoving except for the rise and fall of his breath, with a paper bag over his head. They tried to arrest him, to put handcuffs on him, but when they took the paper bag off, he attacked, killing them all. That’s part of the legend, anyway.”

Reimer had more questions, naturally, and I told him that all he knew was what his character knew, an urban legend that was purported to be backed up by video, though he would never have actually seen it.

I was on the fence about whether or not it would actually work, but a half hour later, it was just him and Tiff left, and it felt dramatically appropriate.

Yes, you could trap Shia LaBeouf with a paper bag.

We had paper bags in Sable, just like we’d stashed them everywhere we could, that was just sensible prep, given what we’d known. I had no idea whether it would work on this version of the Cannibal, but I was hopeful, because if it couldn’t, then there was a good chance we (and everyone in Greychapel) were fucked.

The first action the Cannibal took, aside from ominously walking toward us, was to punch one of the Armateurs. He did it hard enough that it went flying against one wall of the hallway, hitting hard stone and crumpling enough that it didn’t move. With that, the Armateurs finally acknowledged him, a few of them peeling off of me. I tried to move backward, to manipulate them into fighting him, but it didn’t matter, because he tore through them like they were made of paper. The metal would instantly tear beneath his fingers, and he threw them with gritted teeth, their obvious weight not bothering him at all.

When he got to me, I was ready, the paper bag unfolded and my sword tossed to the ground. I moved forward to slip it onto his head, but he moved like lightning, punching straight through the bag and tearing it open, then grabbing my wrists and head butting me hard enough that I lost consciousness, still magic the only thing that might have slowed him down enough that he didn’t kill me outright.

I came to an indeterminate amount of time later, head spinning, and slammed on the healing as hard as I could, which brought me to a state of clarity.

The Armateurs were all crumpled, sheared apart, or otherwise disassembled, and Amaryllis lay on the ground, unmoving, with blood seeping from her head. Her left arm was missing, with her shoulder a raw and ragged mess. I couldn’t see the Cannibal, but I could hear screams coming from inside the War Room. I lurched to my feet and went to Amaryllis, touching her for just long enough to confirm that she wasn’t dead, that her soul was still firmly attached to her. I gave her healing even as I was making sure she was alive.

“What,” said Amaryllis as she began to stir. She looked me over, then down at her missing arm, which I’d stopped from bleeding. I was sure that my face was smeared with blood. “We lived.” She turned her head toward where the screaming was coming from, then looked back at me. “Time to bail.”

“He could come after us,” I replied, picking my sword up from the floor and sheathing it. “Horror movie rules, you run away from the massacre and put yourself in a bunker, you’re fucked.”

“Juniper,” said Amaryllis. She was weak and woozy, having lost who knew how much blood. I had moved a half-step toward the door of the War Room.

“We’re the only ones,” I replied, before she could even make an argument. The only ones who know what might deal with him, the only ones who will try to stop him, the only ones who can. “I need another paper bag.”

She wordlessly popped a paper bag out from Sable and handed it to me. It was one from Earth, though we had a variety, a plain grocery bag that said ‘SuperOne Foods’ on the side of it. Once she had given me one, she popped one out for herself.

I skipped the conversations we might have had and dashed in through the doors of the War Room, with Amaryllis, missing an arm, following quickly behind me.

There was rather a lot of fighting going on in the War Room. The Cannibal was up among the stadium seating of the council, having worked his way through a fair bit of it already. There were bodies laying on the open floor where people gave their testimonies, and a few people had clearly been thrown, since the fresco on the enormous domed roof was cracked and bloodied at a few places that had suffered obvious impacts. Most of the people had cleared out, or were in the process of running away, out through the back doors that the council came in through. All of the Armateurs were destroyed, and probably had been within the first seconds.

I wasn’t sure whether the Cannibal had ever been unleashed on this scale before. I wasn’t sure who his targets were. I knew at least some of his patterns, the ways that he would kill, how he would eat parts and pieces, leaving people alive until he could circle back, half from how I’d played him, half from what Amaryllis had told me. Most of his targets would die in the first hour, but he would just keep going after the initial strike was done, up to days later, finishing off the people he’d only maimed, chasing them down alleyways or popping out of closets, appearing behind them when they looked in a mirror — like I’d told Amaryllis, horror movie tropes, played to the hilt.

We weren’t the only ones he’d left alive. There were people stumbling around, clearly injured, and others who were screaming on the floor, missing limbs. I saw a woman stumbling around with a bite taken out of her shoulder, and realized with a start that it was Camellia, the vice chair.

I ran for the Cannibal, who was, true to his name, eating someone alive. Most of it was obscured by the Cannibal’s head, but the man was screaming and pounding his fists against the Cannibal, trying to get away. Eventually the man succeeded in getting away, but only because the Cannibal had removed his leg at the hip.

Shia LaBeouf, holding the leg in one hand, turned to look at me.

He was still fully nude, but with lots and lots of blood all over the front of his body, soaking his beard and covering his mouth. He still held an expression of quiet intensity, like he was an athlete about to go for a world record. I really needed to get him away from these people.

He tossed the leg he’d been holding to the side and lunged at me, moving ungodly fast, and as soon as he had grabbed onto my wrist, I tapped the ring on my hand three times, then began burning a unicorn bone.

Almost at once we were a mile in the air, the Ring of Upward Bliss having done its work. Caledwich was below us, splayed out for our view, and beyond it, the rest of Anglecynn. It was a crisp and clear day, the visibility impeccable, and then Shia LaBeouf punched me in the face.

I was woozy, having trouble seeing straight, let alone thinking coherent thoughts, but I let him have it with everything I had, a short-range blast of gem magic, a concussive blast of vibration magic that used nearly all my breath, and as much in the way of cutting force as my anger would allow me, which wasn’t very much, because I was mostly scared shitless. He took most of it without flinching, even as his physical body was battered. When I was finished, he punched me in the face a second time, and the loop restarted.

With raw force having failed, I tried antimemetics in the second loop, using a bone from one of the Momenagerie to get that effect. It lasted an incredibly short time, not much longer than the unicorn loop itself, but to my surprise it was effective, and the Cannibal and I fell together, because I couldn’t get his iron grip off of my wrist. I tried desperately to get the bag over his head with only one hand free, but we reached the end of the loop, and I wasn’t willing to die for the chance.

The third time through, I used passion magic to slip away, fear letting me move without having to cover the distance, and his grip on me instantly released, since it wasn’t synced up with my own movement. I burnt the mome bone as I did that, in theory cloaking me. I had no fucking clue what he was going to do about it, given that there was nothing for him to push off of, but what I didn’t expect was what happened, which was that he dropped, leaving me standing there, immobilized by my still magic.

I watched and waited, wondering what the catch was, whether he was going to start flying, or some other bullshit, because that was part of his thing. If you watched a horror movie, the protagonist could never just fly up ten feet off the ground and be safe. It didn’t work like that.

But as I stood there in the sky, a mile up, breathing thin air, I waited and watched him falling. For a normal person it would be a death sentence, but I fully expected him to survive with no problems, walking out of a crater he would make on crash landing, or bouncing back and forth off buildings to slow his fall, or something equally ridiculous.

The unicorn loop was being strained, and I let it reset, this time with a plan. I slipped from the Cannibal’s grip with passion magic again, but this time I reached for him at the same time I began to burn the mome bone, and stilled him in place rather than letting him fall. He really, truly didn’t seem to realize I was there, even though I was the only thing around. I didn’t waste any of my precious seconds, and slipped the paper bag straight over his head.

I dropped the antimemetic effect and waited to be punched right in my fucking face again. Instead, we just stood there in the air, with him not moving at all, the words ‘SuperOne Foods’ written upside down. I let the unicorn loop end and stood there in mid-air, holding him still, waiting for the other shoe to drop, because he wasn’t moving, or doing anything at all. The tension had gone out of him entirely.

Holy shit, it actually worked.

I wouldn’t have said that it was easy, but fucking Christ I had expected worse. I’d expected that I would literally die and go to the hells, because we knew that was a possibility. It was always in the back of my head as something that could happen. The Cannibal wouldn’t have been a complete blindside, given that we were in Anglecynn, but the fucking arc was supposed to be done, and — and this turned out to be one last complication, a coda to the adventure, not the little horror show that I had expected it would be. People dead, people maimed, Amaryllis maimed, but it was over.

I let out a long sigh of relief.

Then I realized that the quest hadn’t updated.

Then I saw the dragon.

Nearest and Dearest

The marriage inspector was the last thing we needed to deal with in Anglecynn, with the caveat that the Amaryllis clones and thirty of the tuung would stay behind in order to manage everything within the kingdom. The clones were hilariously bad at anything related to combat, and couldn’t use magic or entads, but the tuung would be their security service, and we were hoping that Amaryllis’ remote updates, along with a share of the Fourfold Flask, would allow us some early warning in case there was something we absolutely needed to deal with there. The clones didn’t have souls, per se, which meant that they couldn’t be soulfucked, and weren’t vulnerable that way, but there were other vectors of attack to be worried about, like memes. Still, it was clearly what the clones were meant for, to the extent that the Dungeon Master had meant them for anything, and we were hopeful that they could handle things that needed handling. (Honestly, I might have held too high an opinion of her, or been blinded by affection, but I felt like a single Amaryllis would have been able to handle the kingdom on her own.)

The plan was to return to the Isle of Poran and then go deal with Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle. We took perfectly legal trips via teleportation key, bought and paid for rather than using the illicit key, mostly because of the number of people we had with us and the desire to leave a paper trail. There was no touchstone on the Isle of Poran though, so we went through the Ha-lunde city of Ludhad, then took a flying ship across to the Isle.

It was The Underline, the same ship that we’d used through the Warrens when we’d first gone to Anglecynn, but the biggest difference now was that we owned it outright, and Captain Bonny and her crew were our employees. She seemed perfectly pleased about the arrangement, which seemed to at least partly be because she was under the impression that I had punched out the gold dragon that had been following us. It might also have been that we were paying her good wages, though I wasn’t handling matters of money.

When we got back to the Isle of Poran, Grak and Solace started setting up for getting the locus out of the bottle.

Over the months we’d all been together, we’d come up with a lot of plans for how to get the locus out. The problem was, there were very few of these methods that we could safely try, and Solace was understandably reluctant to, for example, smash the bottle, ward against the bottle, have Bethel eat the bottle, or do anything that had a decent chance of killing the locus outright.

(I’d offered to do all of that and more while in a unicorn loop, which would mean that I would have six seconds to see whether it had worked or not, but Solace hadn’t been willing to agree to it, even in principle. The way I saw it, I probably wouldn’t know the outcome after five seconds, but it would get us some data we didn’t have, and the risk was very low. The way Solace saw it, this was all pretty dumb, and if ‘smash bottle, get locus’ was a viable plan, they wouldn’t have been driven to us through increasingly less specific augeries.)

Now though, with Grak’s warding what it was, and his partial entad warding, he thought that he had a good chance of being able to do some manipulations to what the entad bottle was, which might allow the locus to be safely, gently plopped out onto the Isle of Poran. The rite that had brought Solace to us, Zorisad Yosivun, hadn’t specified that it was me that would free the locus, meaning that it could just as well have been any of the four of us that had been there, but if this worked, and the spell had really been finding Grak, well … Solace seemed to like the plan, but I was skeptical.

We had picked out a spot on the Isle of Poran ages ago. We controlled Miunun, more or less, and if the locus was going to have its domain anywhere, best for it to be a place where we could theoretically control the borders. Poran had a few other things in its favor, like the fact that it was an island, which would make it far more difficult for anyone to get to, and the closeness of allies like the Ha-lunde. Solace didn’t seem to think that biome mattered all that much, so long as there was life, which there always had been on Poran, even if the crops were poor. And the locus would expand out into the water, so that didn’t seem to be a problem either, though if it ever became a problem, then things were going really well.

I wasn’t convinced that getting the locus out of the bottle was going to be the end of it. We’d gotten the Second Empire research from the Infinite Library, and it was really, really grim. No locus with three or less druids had ever grown back. No locus with less than ten square miles to its name had ever grown back. Solace didn’t put much stock in anything the Second Empire had to say. While I didn’t fully trust their research, given it was done by people involved in an extermination campaign and grossly unethical, I couldn’t just ignore it. I knew a lot of the research done by the Nazis and the Japanese was just torture in science drag, not just unethical, but worthless in terms of scientific value, but from the books we had, it was hard to tell whether this was the case with the locus stuff. The more I had learned about them, the less I saw the Second Empire as being fantasy Nazis; they were their own kinds of evil, their genocides seemingly rooted in utilitarian calculation rather than outright malice, though there were definitely some blurred lines there.

I held my tongue. I wanted this to work.

Grak created a ward a mile wide, and I walked with him as he made it.

“Did you like being a dwarf?” he asked.

“It was only for a few seconds,” I said. “But, uh, sure? Did you like being a human, way back when? I never asked.”

He gave me a look. “Circumstances were difficult.”

“True,” I said. He’d been human only briefly, after we’d been poisoned, when I had needed to get his soul back to a good state but hadn’t had backups at the ready. The brief period he’d been a human had been right after Fenn had died, which I could imagine really put a damper on any sense of adventure or experimentation he’d had. “Do you ever think about being human?”

“Often,” replied Grak. He held his hand out to the side, using it in place of a wand. I had the Crown of Eyes on, and could see what he saw, which included warder’s sight, thanks to the Six-Eyed virtue. Grak himself was practically glowing with wards, while the ward he was creating was incredibly faint. Single-entad wards were some of the easiest and cheapest wards you could make, which was good, given the size we might end up needing.

“Does being human appeal to you?” I asked.

“Of course,” replied Grak. “The world is not built for dwarves.”

“Yeah, I noticed that in Anglecynn more than other places,” I said. “But at least you’re the second most common species.”

“We are second most populous,” said Grak. “Not second most common. I don’t care for dwarfholds.”

“Not even the more modern ones?” I asked.

“Those are better,” he replied. He kept on walking, not seeming to pay all that much attention to what he was doing. I wasn’t about to say that he could have done this in his sleep, but it really was a very simple ward, it was just that it had a perimeter of three and a half miles or so.

“So the thing that appeals to you about being human is just fitting in?” I asked. “Or having a world that’s not designed around a form different than your own?”

Grak kept walking for a bit, mulling it over. “People treat me differently,” he said. “There is an unpleasant friction. Some of it comes from my upbringing.”

“Some of it is language,” I said.

“I am fluent in Anglish,” said Grak. It was the language we were speaking in, more out of habit than actual design. I hadn’t switched to Groglir, and he hadn’t either.

“You’re fluent,” I replied in his native tongue. “But you’re more fluent in Groglir. Everything you say comes out more natural.”

“Then maybe I should say that I think about having been born human,” said Grak. “Or at least a more conventional of the mortal species.”

“How do you define conventional?” I asked. I’d meant to pad the question, but Groglir was bad at padding, and it came out a little more blunt than I’d intended.

“We have only one gender,” said Grak. We took another few steps before continuing on. “We are short. We breed differently. Dwarves are less like humans than many other species.”

“You mentioned gender first,” I said.

Grak hesitated, then nodded. “It, or its lack, is an essential element of being. It is custom across Aerb to speak of us in terms of he and him, but that is not actually what we are. I understand the reasons for it, but it chafes sometimes.”

“What are the reasons?” I asked. I was slightly puzzled. “We had this conversation before, when you were first teaching me Groglir. But I think I would have remembered your answer.”

Grak replied before I could recall the specifics. “I told you it was tradition,” said Grak. “At the time I didn’t want to have a discussion of the finer points.”

“Those being?” I asked. Usually he wasn’t so circumspect.

“Words have power,” he said. “Long ago, before the Dwarven Coalition was formed, it was communicated and decided among dwarves that it was better to be seen by humans as a society of men. A dwarfhold would be seen as a small kingdom of ready soldiers, with no spare mouths to feed, as they sometimes thought of their women. By and large, it was easier to be respected as a man, easier to integrate into male traditions, which most of the early dwarves were striving for. The humans knew that we were not men, but so long as we harnessed the words, life was easier for us.”

“Okay,” I said. “But in the modern Aerb?”

“There are those who argue that we should flaunt our differences,” said Grak. “They would argue that we take on new words, to make clear that something different is being described. Other species push harder than dwarves, but it’s the sort of fight that will be slow and long until it’s not, and it comes with drawbacks.”

“Huh,” I said. “Yeah, I definitely would have remembered if you’d gone into it. But I don’t really understand why you didn’t.”

“I thought that you would ask me the obvious question,” he said.

“Ah,” I said. “I would ask you whether you preferred me to refer to you using the Groglir terms.”

“No,” said Grak. “I thought that you would ask me whether I prefered to be viewed as male or female.”

I thought about that for a moment. “But obviously the answer is that if you’re not going to be viewed as maka, then whether you’d rather be viewed as male or female depends on context.” He gave me a nod. “Those dwarves making the argument that they would rather human societies view them as male were doing it on the premise that they should be porcupines, showing off their spines for everyone, threatening war. But if the situation were different, then I can imagine presenting as female would have its own benefits, though, uh, I’m coming up a little bit short.” I stopped where I was for a moment, and Grak kept walking, not waiting for me to literally and metaphorically catch up with him.

“This was a you and me thing,” I said as I came up beside him once more. “You would rather that I viewed you as female so that I would think of you as a potential mate.”

Grak nodded once. He was blushing a little bit. “It was a foolish attraction that I am well over,” he said. “You are married.”

“Fake married,” I said.

“Hmm,” said Grak. “So you have not consummated?” It was very rare that Grak ever sounded smug about something.

“No, as a matter of fact,” I said. “Not that it’s any of your business.”

“You were supposed to,” said Grak, looking at me with furrowed brows, his hand still trailing along but obviously only getting a fraction of his attention. “And it is my business, because it’s a matter of law. If you do not consummate, you are not married, and if you are not married, then your trial by combat holds no legal weight. We could all get pulled back to Anglecynn. This is entirely my business.”

“Alright,” I said. “Fine, it’s your business, within one degree of reasonableness.” I sighed. “Are you sure we’re good, you and me? I don’t want to leave anything on the table as far as that goes.”

“I am handling myself well,” said Grak. “My feelings for you have faded.”

I couldn’t help but think about how things had been going between me and Amaryllis, and how my relationship with Grak was in some ways a mirror image, at least on the topic of desire. I felt bad that I didn’t hold any desire for him. Yet if I tried to imagine doing as Amaryllis had done for me, engaging without actually experiencing desire — well, yes, I could imagine having sex with Grak, and being happy at him being happy, more than taking pleasure myself, but it was like putting myself in the mind of an alien, and I couldn’t fathom how different things would have to be in order to make any of that into a reality.

Maybe if he had been the one to get pregnant with Solace, and I had been stuck in the time chamber for a few months with him instead of Amaryllis, and if I had just been really sexually frustrated … I didn’t know. That was a different scenario though, one where things happened between me and Grak because I was horny, not because I had made some rational decision to ‘help’ a friend.

It was all confusing to me, because there was very explicitly a harem thing going on, with my companions being women that all had their own appeals, whether they were appropriate and sane or not. Even Bethel, who was literally a house, who was evil, at least her, if put in a lineup with the others, I could understand why. But Grak? It felt like a cruel joke, or if not that, then commentary of some kind that I really wasn’t understanding.

(The locus was obviously another exception, but it was a package deal with Solace, and before Solace had died and become an increasingly-older child, I could maybe have slotted her into some kind of coherent ensemble. The older version of Solace had really given off the vibe of being up for anything. The locus itself already liked breaking rules, so why not another?)

“Did you want to talk about Amaryllis?” asked Grak.

“Sure,” I replied. “She’s been different, with her clones up and running. We’ve been spending way more time together, and while I think it’s going to change, for now it seems like she’s devoted her original self to mostly slacking off and joking around with me. It’s like it’s constantly movie night.”

“And this is the reason you haven’t had sex?” asked Grak.

“No,” I said. “No, it’s … I don’t know, it’s weird.”

“That doesn’t clarify,” said Grak.

“We’re not dating,” I said. “We’ve spent absolutely massive amounts of time with each other over the last half a year, which is really more like, uh, two years for her, I think. But still, there’s all this time together, and I don’t think that I have to tell you that I’m attracted to her —”

“You do not,” replied Grak. He started laughing to himself a little bit, and I waited for him to stop, which took longer than I thought it should have.

“But we’re not actually married, and we’re not dating, it’s all just this,” I paused. “It’s unspoken. It’s a bit flirty. It’s nice.”

“You’re worried that if it becomes sexual, it will stop being nice,” said Grak.

“Oh,” I said. “It’s kind of already sexual.”

Grak looked at me and raised an eyebrow.

“You know, I think I got way too accustomed to not having any privacy,” I said. “I just assumed that everyone knew my business. No, we, uh, were working on our stories for the marriage inspector, trying to make sure that everything was airtight, and — I don’t want to get into all the details of it, but yeah. And over the next few days we did some other stuff too, and then it was time to consummate, which wasn’t strictly necessary, but did seem like there was some legitimate reason to … and all the other stuff aside, I just had this realization that I couldn’t have sex with her and not tell her that I was in love with her.”

“Is there a reason that you don’t want to do that?” asked Grak.

“I don’t know,” I said. “Lots of reasons come to mind, but it’s hard to tell what’s backfill and what’s not. I can know how I feel, which is that something bad would come of it, without necessarily knowing why I feel that way. If I wanted to be really rigidly logical, I would probably blame a sense of narrative. But maybe it’s just that I think things are nice the way they are now, or maybe it’s some idiotic part of me that’s worried about rejection.”

“She would not reject you,” said Grak.

“I know,” I said. “Even if she was just a completely platonic friend, —”

“She is not,” said Grak.

I looked at him. “Yeah?” I asked. “What have you heard? Other than what I just told you.”

“I see the way she looks at you,” said Grak. “I listen to her defend you. You check her soul from time to time. Have you not seen it?”

“I try not to be invasive,” I said. “I just scan for threats or anything suspect. But yes, I’ve seen some suggestions in that direction.”

“You are being stupid, Juniper,” said Grak.

“Okay,” I said. “You’re probably right. So as someone with a level head and minimal personal stakes, what do you suggest?”

“Tell her that the marriage is meaningful to you and that you wish it were real,” said Grak. “Then have sex with her if she consents. Then reserve flirtation and coy glances for when the two of you are alone together.”

“Ah,” I said. “Sorry.”

Grak waved a hand, the one not trailing a ward. “We are almost done with the ward,” he said. “Then the hard part will begin.”

I watched from a safe distance as the bottle grew. Amaryllis and Solace were inside it, ready to leave at a moment’s notice. I was outside with Raven and Grak, fairly close to the bottle itself, but ready to get the fuck out of the way if things started to happen in a hurry.

Grak’s novel method (or ability) of partial entad warding was ripe for abuse, but only in specific ways. To hear him tell it, the manipulation had to be in the form of negations, ways of altering the behavior of an entad by subtracting what it could do, in whole or in part. This could be fairly fine-grained, but it depended on the specifics of the entad and what rules it was following. The teleportation key had a number of distinct inner workings, such as allowing you to view your worldline, having a two hour refresh time, and actually teleporting you. Grak’s partial wards could knock out individual elements of the teleportation key, like preventing it from showing a worldline, or preventing it from refreshing, but the limiter itself couldn’t be removed, or at least, he hadn’t worked out how to do it yet. It was exactly the kind of thing that was begging for an exclusion, since there were any number of entads which could, if their limits were removed, destroy the world. Grak was, understandably, being careful.

The bottle seemed safe enough though, and it was the first promising lead on the locus situation, so we were barreling ahead, and if warding got excluded to the Isle of Poran… well. That would be bad.

The strategy that Grak was taking was to selectively nullify specific elements of the extradimensional magic, and to do it in a slow and careful way that would prevent the bottle from breaking, which would almost certainly be catastrophic. Because the bottle was an entad, and a powerful one, it was impossible to run tests, but Grak had successfully done the same procedure on two other extradimensional entads of roughly similar function, which served as proof of concept.

The bottle was growing, more and more with every passing moment. Every once in a while it would stop, and Grak would watch it. I looked through his eyes, but whatever he was seeing in the magic of the bottle, I had none of the background necessary to understand or interpret it.

The problem with extradimensional spaces was almost always in their boundary conditions. The inside was bigger than the outside, yes, but how did that work when at some point the inside and outside had to meet each other? For something like Sable, that was easy, since the only connection from the exterior to the interior was through commands that seamlessly placed things in or out. But for a building that was bigger on the inside through star magic, the warping really had to take account of the difference between the inside and the outside, especially if you wanted something dumb, like a window, because if the interior wall was stretched, then the window might also be stretched, and would let in the same amount of light over a much larger surface area, making the outside dim, to say nothing of what would happen if someone tried to go through the thing. There had been cases of amateur star magic outright killing people who tried to walk into their new extradimensional rooms.

The bottle wasn’t just one window, it was pure glass. I had noticed the sunlight effect on my first or second time in: the bottle presented maybe a few square feet of surface to the world, but when you were inside it, the sun felt just as strong as it did outside. Something weird was going on at the boundary, a multiplier effect that allowed you to feel like you were outside. And Grak was having to grapple with that too, because as the bottle’s interior expanded against the exterior, that secondary effect was starting to cause some problems. The interior of the bottle was noticeably brighter than the exterior, its forest basked in sunlight that was almost blinding, even from outside. Grak stopped the process for a few minutes, and canceled that portion of the entad effect entirely.

It was slow going, but the bottle was growing. I wasn’t even sure what was happening, but my best guess, based on what Grak had said, was that he was unconstraining the interior space, and it wasn’t that the bottle was growing, it was that the interior volume was pushing out against the outer layer. This was anticipated to cause some shear stress, but the bottle, like other entads, had some degree of self-healing and resistance to damage, and Grak was doing something to compensate for the boundary.

I was mostly just standing there watching, fidgeting slightly and trying to will my Six-Eyed virtue to cover what Grak was doing. He was trying to make the bottle squat, manipulating the dimensionality by negating only part of it, so that we wouldn’t be standing next to mile-high walls of tall glass, and so that the ground within the bottle would be pushed right up to the opening.

After two hours of slow expansion, the bottle was half a mile wide, with the ground inside pushed up so that the trees were just barely brushing the upper part of the glass. The main tree, the one in the center, which we’d slept inside for a fair amount of my time on Aerb, was sticking out, fully outside of the bottle.

“How are you doing on concordance?” I asked.

“This is nothing,” said Grak. “I have already regained what was spent. It is like asking a clockmaker if they are winded from delicate work on a pocket watch.”

“Okay,” I said. “You’re still burning mental energy to do it. Is that fine?”

“It’s fine,” said Grak. “I can stop if I need to. The wards Thargox made needed to be dismantled halfway through, but the locus will hold and the ward is permanent.”

“You could just leave it like this?” I asked.

“I could,” he replied. “The plan is to expand it so the interior matches the exterior. The walls … should hold.” That was an uncharacteristically long hesitation from him.

“And if it doesn’t?” I asked.

“It’s hard to say,” he replied. “There may be a considerable amount of glass falling down.” He gave me a look. “I put up a secondary ward around us to annihilate the entad on contact, but if the magic fails and washes out too quickly, you will have to protect me.”

“Of course,” I replied. “Just say the word and I’ll use a unicorn bone. I can give you a second or third chance.”

“I don’t think it will help,” replied Grak. “This is for me to do.”

The big problem came a half hour later, when the bottle had been widened as far as it would go, so that the interior dimension matched the exterior dimension. It was a full mile across, all inside the ward, as planned, with the headspace shrunk down as much as it would go. The problem was with the neck of the bottle, which, no matter what contortions Grak attempted, couldn’t force the entire mass inside the bottle out of it, not without causing lots of damage to the domain. The locus wasn’t just the biomass, but it was a little the biomass, and to snap hundreds of trees and throw thriving plants under soil … we were worried about the outcome.

Amaryllis and Solace came out of the bottle for a consultation, Solace as a fast-moving cloud, Amaryllis using the Amulet of Five Spirits, which she’d promised was only on loan. When she landed, she turned back into her human form, fully naked, and took some clothes that Grak had ready. Entads did the nudity thing a fair amount, because ‘you’ was much more of a coherent concept than ‘you plus all the stuff you have on or with you’, and nudity excluded a lot of munchkinry. I tried to be a grown up about it, which meant that I only thought about boobs instead of saying anything.

“Is there an argument for leaving it in its current configuration?” I asked. “At least part of the biome is sticking up out of the bottle, and it’s full-sized. Maybe the domain can expand across the barrier this way?”

“Unlikely,” said Solace. “I don’t want to rush this, but this is substantially worse, as it is.”

“We are committed,” nodded Grak. “The issue is whether to push it out now, with the damage that would cause, or to try something else.”

“We should think about other options,” said Raven. “Grak, what’s your opinion on an annihilation ward?”

“It worries me,” said Grak. “The pressure is equalized, the interior matches the exterior … it could work.”

“Do it,” nodded Solace. “If it can’t be pushed out, then annihilating the bottle is the best option.”

I winced. I’d been hoping that we would keep the bottle, and maybe, if it wasn’t going to have the locus’ domain inside it, we could start building our own facilities. There were a lot of things that you could do with a bottle whose insides were that big. And Bethel, if she ever came back, if I could ever forgive her enough to work with her … I put those thoughts out of my head. It was a good entad for a meta-entad to use. I seemed to be the only one who cared about losing a powerful entad, so I kept my mouth shut. The locus was, obviously, more important.

“This is the second time my skill as a midwife has not come in handy,” murmured Grak, and the image of the domain coming out of the bottle as a birth was so strong that I couldn’t find it in me to laugh at the joke.

We were two hundred feet from the bottle when Grak changed his ward, and it was annihilated in an instant, dropping the land inside by a few feet where the thick glass had been. The sides of the domain slid down, toppling trees, but the destruction was localized to the edges, and more gentle than it might have been, with some of the edge still standing, showing off the strata of rocks, earth, and plant life.

The locus came to the edge shortly afterward, looked at us, brayed once, and trotted back into the woods, as though nothing had happened.

“Good work,” I said to Grak. “Really, really good work.”

“Did the quest update?” he asked.

“No,” I replied. “But we might have to wait for a bit. It’s not clear.”

“The bottle is gone,” said Solace, speaking softly, as though she couldn’t believe it. “And the locus is free to grow once again.”

Amaryllis looked at me with an eyebrow raised. She’d read the same reports that I had, and while she hadn’t expressed any skepticism, I knew she felt it too.

We knew better than to ask for a timeline on when we would or wouldn’t see results. Instead, we headed into the transplanted domain to see how things had changed, and in part, to be there for the locus in its time of transition. This was a big step, maybe the biggest step that the locus had taken since it had gone into the bottle in the first place.

It also meant that Solace wasn’t going to be traveling with us anymore. Taking the bottle around the world was one thing, but to abandon the locus to its own devices would be nearly unthinkable. That was on top of the fact that Solace’s powers would wane away from the locus, so by a strictly utilitarian calculation, it was better for her to stay where she could do the most good. I was worried that both Solace and the locus were going to become background characters now, from a narrative point of view, and most of the worry was that background characters were sometimes expendable for the sake of making a point.

But I was a single point of Loyalty away from the locus getting a new virtue, and we knew from experience that those could be game-changing, especially if it was coming hot on the heels of completing a companion quest, which … well, there had been a chance that after the bottle was annihilated, I would have gotten one, or if not that, an update. I was getting worried that this was only step one though, with another three or four steps in front of us, and there were other pressing matters, like the date with Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle and his zombies.

The locus didn’t seem any different from before, though I wasn’t a great judge. It — she? After the conversation with Grak, I was inclined to stop playing around with pronouns, since they seemed systematizing either way — was laying down and not moving much, almost napping, but that wasn’t unusual behavior for the locus. Solace patted the locus’ flank and told the locus that it had done a wonderful job, that it was strong and beautiful, which only reinforced the birth analogy in my head. Raven and Amaryllis joined in, giving their love and support, but I stood back, and after a moment, I realized that Grak was standing back too.

“You okay?” I asked.

He shrugged, then replied in Groglir. “It didn’t work.”

“The quest didn’t update,” I said. “That’s not the same thing.”

“The Second Empire was right,” said Grak. I could practically see his heart sinking in his chest.

“If they were, then we just have a different problem,” I said. “One that we can solve.”

“There is not always a solution to the problems that life creates,” said Grak.

I swallowed, because I had wanted to say that this wasn’t true for us, that we were special, that this was a world that didn’t give problems with no solutions … but Fenn was dead, and she had stayed dead. I knew enough from my own history as a DM to know that how it was supposed to work was that you would allow anything with an epic enough quest, that you could descend into the hells to rescue someone you loved, that you could slay a god and wrest control of their domain, that there weren’t supposed to be any actual limits, just limits of how long the party would stay invested in a campaign … but I hadn’t always DMed that way. I had, on occasion, decided that rocks fall and everyone dies, because what they were trying to do was stupid or impossible.

“You did a good job,” I said, resting a hand on his shoulder. “I didn’t understand any of it, but you did a good job. The locus is out of the bottle. That’s what we were trying to accomplish, and it’s done. Okay?”

“Okay,” he replied. His hand went up to rest on mine. “Thank you, Juniper.”

Once everyone was done fawning (heh) over the locus, we went to the tree house.

“I’ll keep three of my clones with you,” Amaryllis said to Solace. “And obviously there will be a contingent on Poran to handle the industrial and engineering considerations.”

“And what would those clones be doing?” asked Solace, raising a dark green eyebrow.

“Communicating with you about what’s going on with us,” said Amaryllis. “There don’t seem to be any distance limits on the sync. And beyond that, I can do whatever you’d like me to do. To the extent you need extra hands, —”

“It’s the extra minds that worry me,” said Solace. “You have real affection for the locus, I can see that, but it’s poisoned with calculation.”

Amaryllis set her lips into a thin line. “Very well,” she said. “I can station a clone at the edge of the domain, if you’d prefer. I don’t want us to lose contact with each other, not for longer than a day. Or I can make brief visits.”

“That would be better,” said Solace with a nod. “And we will, of course, want to start looking for druids.”

“That’s not how it’s normally done, is it?” I asked.

“Of course not,” said Solace. “But if we hew to the old ways and wait for people to come of their own volition, allowing whomever would like to into the domain, we would be overrun in a heartbeat.” She gripped her staff. “It would have been better to remain cloaked in secrecy.”

“I’m sorry,” said Amaryllis. “I really am.”

“I understand why you thought it was best,” said Solace with a wave of her hand. “What’s done is done. I’ll speak with the tuung, to see who among them might make a suitable druid, if the locus so chooses. And if none have the temperament or desire, then perhaps I’ll open the gates.”

“It will be a security challenge,” said Amaryllis. “But it would be workable, if it comes to that.”

“And in terms of the worst case?” I asked. “If the domain doesn’t expand and new druids can’t be inducted?”

“Then we’ll find a way forward,” said Solace.

I appreciated the optimism, I really did, but I thought it was a little bit misplaced. Amaryllis and Solace started talking about induction processes and how to balance the need for new druids against the risks involved, but I spotted the locus outside the door, and went to it, which no one seemed to object to.

Within half a minute, I was up on its back, and we were riding away from the tree house, exploring the changed domain. It seemed so much more open without the bottle looming over us, like a dome had been lifted off the world. Eventually, we came to the edge, a part that had broken off and sloped down, giving us a view of the sea. I didn’t know whether or not the locus could leave the domain, but it seemed like if it couldn’t, that would be the sort of hard and fast rule that the locus didn’t respect.

“Back in the old days, you’d just let in whoever wanted to come,” I said. “If someone wandered in, it was no big deal, and if they wandered back out, it was also no big deal. They could even hunt, so long as they didn’t take more than they needed. They could live with you, or on your domain, so long as they lived in the right way.” Some of this I was guessing at, some was history as relayed by Solace. “And if they loved the place, then eventually you would find them, and if they were the right kind of people, the right thinkers, then you would connect to them and allow them … hrm. Maybe it wasn’t like granting them permission, maybe it was letting your vast power flow through them, so long as they kept the faucet open on their end.” I liked that as a metaphor. “The problem, now, is that there’s not enough juice, and the flow has been reduced to a trickle. Enough for Solace to do what she can do, but there isn’t enough to push out toward others, nor to expand. At least, that’s my working theory.”

The locus didn’t reply. It could understand Anglish, or at least tone, but it only looked out at the sea. I wondered, if it ever did expand to reach the shore of Poran, whether it would stay as a doe or become something else instead.

“We could find a battery,” I said. “Some fucking enormous source of power and vitality, in whatever form, we could go on a quest to get it, and then hook it up to you somehow, again with me being a little light on specifics at the moment. And when that was done, you’d be able to pour yourself out over these lands.” I sighed. “Not too likely to actually work though, because if we tried to hook you into a rune magic engine, it would be like AC and DC, or, uh, two things that don’t go together where one is systematized and the other is not.” I snapped my fingers. “It would be like trying to integrate Lego with Play-Doh.”

The locus huffed slightly.

“I’m just thinking out loud,” I said. “I’ll have to try to find a version of that metaphor that works on Aerb.” Lego and its knock-offs were made out of plastic, but I was pretty sure that with the right setup, you could make a wooden version with lower tolerances and higher cost. Probably someone had already done it. Maybe it had already been done on Earth. I had no idea whether or not there were wooden Lego precursors, and once again wished that I had internet access to look it up. “Look, the point is, the way I see things now, we find some nigh-unlimited source of power that’s as wibbly-wobbly in concept space as you are, maybe even something pulled from the conceptual realm … or it’s not solvable. It’s like I said before, that maybe this is just it, all you’ll ever be. Maybe that’s even the lesson. I think the only real change is that now there’s a chance you can outlast Solace for an appreciable length of time.”

The doe huffed again, but didn’t move, and still stared off into the distance. I used the crown to look through its eyes, and got a multifaceted painting instead, one where nothing was literal and everything was either exaggerated or in metaphor. I reeled from it, the augmented vision comprehension of the crown not being nearly sufficient. The locus wasn’t even really seeing the world through its eyes, it was seeing an abstraction of the world, but not an abstraction that made things simpler. Even the image was, I was pretty sure, a simplification of that abstraction.

The outside world had been vibrant through its eyes, and the domain had been, if not dull, then repetitive, the kind of stale sameness as landscape pictures in hotels that were mass manufactured, selected for being as inoffensive as possible. The difference between the two was stark, and it took me a moment to realize how much it represented envy and hunger. The doe had been in the bottle for a long, long time, in a small, stagnant environment, and now it could see the outside world without a layer of glass. The Isle of Poran might legitimately have been like nothing it had ever seen before.

I worked some water magic and parted the clouds, sweeping them to the side and letting light hit the water, which sparkled for us, the grass, which shone a vibrant green, and the dark rocks, which became solid and imposing rather than dour lumps.

“Everything the light touches,” I began, but the words died on my lips, because I could see that it was meaningful to the locus, and maybe this was actually important.

Loyalty Increased: Six-Eyed Doe lvl 20!

Companion Passive Unlocked: Deer to Me (Six-Eyed Doe)!

The locus looked at me, and nudged me in the stomach with its head. I took the hint and swung myself up to ride her, but once I was there, she just stared out at the bright, shining land with me, and when I made to get off again, she moved against me, keeping me in place. I didn’t mind, of course, but I wondered about what the locus was getting from being mounted. I was going to look at the virtue, obviously, but my philosophy of late was that the game layer would keep, and I wasn’t going to let it interrupt me. Slowly, carefully, I looked through the eyes of the locus again, and this time held myself to it, staring at the world as it appeared to this alien intelligence.

It wasn’t even a matter of replacement, not a filter applied to the world, it was completely different, like a painting rendered by someone who was only hearing about the scene secondhand. And it wasn’t really from the same viewpoint, instead, rearranged so that everything was in its own eclectic composition. Seeing through the doe’s ‘eyes’ was misleading, because the doe itself was there, represented in its own view of the world, maybe a bit more small than it really was.

Standing beside the doe was a stag, and it was only because I was absent from the view that I interpreted that stag to be me.

After some time had passed, the locus turned around and headed back to the tree, where the others were waiting, their business concluded. I refrained from telling them about the loyalty up for as long as I could, because it was like breaking a spell, pinning numbers on something mystical. I would have to say something of course, I couldn’t not, and I would have to look, but there was a part of me that didn’t want to, because with how much the locus interfered with the interface of the game, it still seemed like the two shouldn’t be touching at all.

It wasn’t until later that night that I finally looked at the virtue.

Deer to Me: When within the domain of the locus, you can sweet talk the Layman. When within the domain of the locus, the map might become confused with the territory. You, and some distance around you, are part of the domain of the locus, except not for the purposes of the prior two abilities.

I stared at the virtue for a bit. It wasn’t obviously good, not like some of the other virtues I’d gotten. It was obviously in the flavor of the locus, with hardly any direct numbers or mechanical references, which I was a little grateful for. I wondered at some of the language used, and thought about ways to test ‘some distance’, then discarded those thoughts as being not in keeping with the spirit of the locus. I tried to imagine the locus as belonging to a completely different game, one without much in the way of rules, or with rules that mapped to something else, rather than reality, or where the reality as the rules presented it was more important than reality as reality was.

The biggest impact was, as far as I understood it, that Solace would stay at full power so long as she was with me, no matter how far away from Poran we got. The second impact, again, so far as I understood it, was that the locus could come with us, though I wasn’t sure whether this would require the locus to teleport, warp space, or Just Do It.

Either way, it didn’t change all that much, and it didn’t give us a magical out, which meant that we were going to go ahead with everything else as planned. In a few days time, we were planning to kill Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle.

The Aviary

Going into Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle’s exclusion zone was a legal gray zone. Amaryllis and I were dual citizens, with one country being an imperial non-member and the other being a full member in good standing. It wasn’t strictly illegal to cross into the Necrolaborem EZ, but it was illegal to provide aid and comfort, to engage in trade, or to do a whole bunch of other things, which we arguably had done prior to our assassination attempt. There was some hope among the Empire that Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle would eventually see the error of his ways, kill and bottle his zombies, and then become a regular trading partner using the older, less problematic methods of necromancy in order to keep his factories running, though there were other sides on that issue, particularly people who thought that what the Captain had done could not be forgiven. I could see both sides, but so long as there was a threat of death, the Captain just didn’t have the incentive to stand down from his threat of sending half a million souls to the hells.

The Doris Finch situation was something else entirely, not just because it was treated so differently by the Empire, but because we really were attempting to engage in trade of some kind with her. She had found some way of tracking people and sold it to Larkspur, then Uniquities: now, we were going to her in the hopes that we could have her sell it to us.

Even if the Captain hadn’t been in the picture, we probably still would have ended up coming to Doris at some point or another. The ability to paint a probabilistic picture of where things were was golden, the kind of thing that everyone wanted, and if both Larkspur and Uniquities had traded with her in order to get things found, that meant that others probably had too. Clairvoyance was rare on Aerb, and this was, apparently, repeatable, reusable clairvoyance of a sort, one which no one had the knowledge necessary to ward against. Once it became common knowledge that the Finches had that ability, Amaryllis expected there to be a loosening of restrictions, unless control of the ability could be wrested from the Finches, in which case the world would change in a major way.

It wasn’t just trade with Doris Finch that was prohibited, it was everything. No one was allowed into the EZ, and anyone who got out of it was kept out and in quarantine for a period of fourteen days, then given a once over by an anolia, along with a full sweep with wards to make sure that nothing was being smuggled out, wittingly or otherwise.

Here was the problem with Doris Finch: she defected.

If you made an agreement with her, you had to expect that she would break it unless she had overwhelming incentives to cooperate or expected wildly disproportionate retribution. She defected to a degree that I would have said was absolutely inhuman, but I knew humans well enough to know that some, when shown kindness or offered a good deal, would stab you in the back all the same. Doris Finch would lie, cheat, and steal, just as a matter of habit, sometimes even when she should have known that she wouldn’t get away with it. She had poor impulse control and used violence and subjugation as a first resort. She wasn’t insane, she was just really the worst person ever, and popular opinion was that what really pushed her over the edge was that her duplication power meant that her primary influences were other divergent versions of herself. That was the picture presented from the outside, anyway, and especially, the picture presented by Amaryllis.

It was about six days after our brief, ill-fated excursion to see Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle that we landed our ship outside the Doris Finch EZ, between the walls and the range of the Dorises. You could tell where the magic of the Dorises started: past that point, almost nothing grew, as the grounds had been salted with blood and the Dorises had stripped off anything of worth. There were no trees, just ugly, squat buildings in the distance, with a few built right up to the edge, a defensive measure, as one wall of the structure couldn’t be assaulted by other Dorises. The open ‘field’ was our target: we thought it better to have a meeting that was as much in the open as it could be, with a safe retreat back out of the zone.

“I hope you know what you’re doing,” said Captain Bonny. “You know I’m not going in there, right?”

“We know,” I replied.

“And you said that you were going to kill Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle, but didn’t,” she said, frowning at me.

“He was a tiny bit harder to kill than planned,” I said. “But it wasn’t a lack of firepower, it was a lack of intelligence.”

“So get smarter,” Captain Bonny said with a shrug and a smile. “And look, if I get so much as a whiff that you’re working with Blue —” she hesitated, seeming to remember who she was about to make a threat against, and her upright finger curled down. “I’ll resign as your captain, and the crew would call it quits too.”

“We’re not doing a deal with him,” I said.

“Doing one with the Finches though?” asked Bonny, raising an eyebrow.

“Them we’re not aiming to kill,” said Amaryllis. “Or at least, not kill too many. The risks of dealing with her aren’t the same. They’re not moral risks. They’re risks that you get stabbed in the back.”

“Well, armor plates on your back, that’s what I would suggest,” said Captain Bonny with a snort. “And we’ll stay well back.”

The DFEZ was surrounded by tall walls a few hundred feet from where the exclusion itself started. The walls had been put up by imperial steel mages mostly because it was an easy thing to do, rather than because it was actually effective at keeping people out or harmful effects in. I was pretty sure that, as with other exclusion zones, there had been discussions on how to ‘close’ the exclusion, in this case meaning to kill every single one of the Finches, but as with Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle, no one had actually done it. The easiest solution, and the one that I had thought of right away, was to simply soulfuck her, but the status of her soul was complicated, and it had been tried, only to meet with failure.

We were about thirty feet in when we met with a contingent of Dorises. This wasn’t a surprise: we were coming for a meeting, and hoping that all it would take was some diplomacy in order to get her working for us. You never could tell with the Dorises though, at least from what I’d heard.

There were about thirty of them all told, all variations on the same woman, in her thirties, maybe a bit younger. When she’d made her breakthrough and the exclusion happened, she’d been fourteen, and for quite some time she’d aged normally, all of her, which made people think that her exclusion zone would someday solve itself. Then, maybe fifteen or twenty years after the exclusion, she’d stopped aging entirely, all of her, for reasons that, if they were known, weren’t known to us, but probably had something to do with her cloning ability.

At her base, she didn’t look like much, the kind of woman that I could imagine running a struggling bakery or working as a waitress. She looked like she never smiled, and I knew from reading her biography that she was, in fact, a crazy bitch (not to be too gendered about it), but there was nothing all that surprising or unique about her. She had dark hair, was generally fairly thin, and had a narrow face with high cheekbones. If you saw her, I was pretty sure you would forget about her right away.

There were, of course, variations. To start with, their clothes were all different from one another, though there were commonalities in textiles. Maybe half of them were dressed in either leather or a rough fiber, which I knew to be skin and hair, respectively, taken from some Doris who had likely been cloned for the express purpose of being skinned and shaved. Beyond the clothes, there were differences in hair styles, tattoos, and piercings, most of them crude and extreme, with the tattoos in particular being what I thought of as ‘prison quality’. Altogether, they looked like a band of post-apocalyptic biker chicks, but without the bikes.

The one notable exception to their look was their weaponry, which came in the form of polished swords and void rifles. Doris Finch, naturally, did not respect the ban on void weapons, and at some point or another, possibly before the ban and possibly after, a shipment had come in. Because of the unique magic of Doris Finch, virtually anything could be multiplied so long as they could hold it, though there were limits on shelf-life for the cloned items, and naturally, they couldn’t leave the zone.

“You’re in our zone,” called the Doris in the center of the group as we approached. She was slightly higher status than the others, which in Dorisland meant that other Dorises thought she was too tough to fuck with, at least until she could take a shank to the guts in her sleep. She was wearing blue, not the human colors of her lessers, though I saw other bits of blue around, which might have come from the same dress, multiplied a few times. “State the deal.”

“We need tracking,” called Amaryllis. “Five or six candidates to track, entads and supplies to give in return. I have a list of fifty investables, plus the supplies we can get for you. Starting offer is a quarter million obols in supplies, teleported by bulk to wherever you want.” This was one of the things that Cypress, the alternate timeline of Amaryllis, had written was key to dealing with the Dorises: it was best to be completely disproportionate, offering immense rewards or incredibly severe punishments, both backed up as much as possible as being credible. The other key, she’d said, was to deal with as few of them at a time as you could.

“Payment now, results later,” said the central Doris, which I guess was her way of seeing whether we were idiots.

“Can you do it?” asked Amaryllis. “No payment without some guarantee of actual results.” A guarantee wasn’t that valuable of a thing among Dorises, but still.

“We can’t personally, but we’re part of the group that can. We’ll forward the request on,” replied Doris. “We’ll get our cut.”

“That’s not good enough,” said Amaryllis. “We give you funds now, there’s a risk you cut and run. We give you nothing, you have no incentive to pass it along to the people who can actually help us.”

“They’ll pay us a finder’s fee,” said Doris. “The upfront is just proof of payment.”

“We can do a fraction now,” said Amaryllis. “Then no more than a tenth at each step of the way, that gives both of us incentives to keep going. If we need longer, then payouts get spread more.”

“You’ll be eating the costs of the teleports,” said the Doris.

“I’m fine with that,” shrugged Amaryllis.

“Exchange happens now,” said the Doris. “We give you the location for the teleport, you give us the names and descriptions. Photograph or painting works better. We send it along, they’ll contact you. Dead drop at the zone edge works best for you getting your information, unless you have an entad that can talk to us.”

“We do,” nodded Amaryllis. She looked at me. “Juniper.”

Amaryllis handed me an envelope of papers, and I stepped forward, walking cautiously, my hackles raised. Doris Finch was insane, and you couldn’t trust her. I had a lot of void rifles pointed at me. One of my hands was on a mome bone in my bandolier, and I was ready to disappear from their attention, if it came to that. Amaryllis had a scroll that she’d rigged so she could pull down on a string on her own bandolier and hit them with the meme that the two of us were immune to. We were expecting a double cross. You had to, when Doris Finch was involved.

The attack came when I was ten feet away, but it wasn’t the attack I expected, not an attack against us, but an attack against them, Doris against Doris. The void guns began their thwips and thunks at once, along with the sound of more conventional weaponry, and I drew my sword, shifted my elemental plate to iron, and tried my best to stay out of the way, so long as I wasn’t the one being attacked. Through the Crown of Eyes, I could see everyone within fifty feet of me, which meant that when a Doris did eventually take aim at me, I was able to dodge out of the way and counterattack with a dagger pulled from my magical bandolier.

The Dorises didn’t seem to have it out for me though. This was an internal matter, and so long as I stayed where I was, sword drawn, the fighting that went on didn’t touch me, a few pot shots aside. As I watched, I could see the Dorises multiplying, splitting in two, both with the same equipment as the first. When the exclusion had first happened, these splits took five minutes of concentration, but now, it was down to half a second, little enough that it could be done in the midst of combat. Of course, the clones had no loyalty to each other, which was the whole problem with the Dorises, and which made the whole thing into a horrible clusterfuck, because a Doris could only work with herself for a limited time.

The battle went on for quite some time. Grak, Amaryllis, and Raven were bunkered down behind thick steel shielding, plus, I was sure, some wards, and eventually, as no one was really putting effort into attacking me, I walked over to join them.

“This is fucking ridiculous,” I said as I turned down the din of battle with vibration magic. “How long do you think this is going to take to sort out?”

“No idea,” said Amaryllis. “I’m not a veteran of this zone.”

“To be clear, they’re killing each other over who is going to get the contract with us?” I asked.

“‘Contract’,” Amaryllis laughed. “Most likely they’ll just steal the down payment and then do nothing for us. This fucking bitch.”

Amaryllis hated Doris Finch, maybe more than she hated any other enpersoned exclusion. If it was Amaryllis who had that power, she would have brought the world to heel with it, exclusion or not. I was pretty sure that I’d heard her rant about it at least twice before coming to the EZ was even on the table.

“Alright,” said Amaryllis after the movie was over. It had been The Prestige, which got her gears turning, for obvious reasons. This was day twenty-three of being cooped up in the time chamber together, unable to leave, with only each other for company. “Imagine this. You gain the ability to split in two. There are two of you. What’s the first thing you do?”

“I shoot my other self,” I said.

“Because you’re a fucking idiot, right,” said Amaryllis, nodding.

“If you’re talking about the movie —” I began. Normally this was one of my favorite parts of movie night, talking to Amaryllis and seeing what she thought about what we’d watched. If I’d had any foreign friends in Bumblefuck, I probably would have tried cultural exchanges with them, just to see what they thought of Americana and American culture, not that America didn’t export a ton of movies and television shows. This was even better though. Most of the time, anyway.

“No, I understand it in the movie,” said Amaryllis. “Caldlow was an obsessive, and had his own history with a double, which went poorly for him. It was commentary on him and his mindset. The whole movie tells a story about three madmen. And maybe we can make some leeway for there being no magic on Earth, and this unprecedented thing being frightening. But I’m not talking about that, or at least not directly. So do you want to try answering the question seriously?”

“I guess if I found out I had a clone, we’d have sex,” I said.

Amaryllis stared at me, waiting.

I sighed. “Alright, fine, it really depends on how the duplication happened, but we would try to work together, do some research, figure out if there are differences, yadda yadda, try to figure out how it’s going to work with one of us going to school and the other staying home, how we’re going to pay for food, that kind of thing.”

“You’re assuming that you’re on Earth in this scenario?” asked Amaryllis, raising an eyebrow.

“Oh,” I said. “Yeah, I guess I was.”

“Either way,” said Amaryllis, waving a hand. “You and I are normal people, sane people. Even if you scale the hypothetical up, I’m fairly confident that a million of you would be able to form a powerful nation, even if you had only your normal abilities as a mostly regular teenager.”

“Mostly?” I asked.

Amaryllis waggled a hand. “No offense intended, but you have your quirks.”

“Sure,” I said. “Honestly, I’m not sure that I would scale up. You’re saying that some of me would be firefighters, some would be doctors, I guess we … wouldn’t need police?”

“Maybe you would, maybe you wouldn’t,” said Amaryllis. “We have similar theories of personhood, thankfully, but after the point of divergence, maybe some of you would fall into the usual traps, and police would be necessary. But it wouldn’t all fall apart. You would have a completely shared culture, shared values, shared ways of thinking, and there’s no way that the nation of Junipers would end up as a failed state.”

“That’s the kind of thing that you always tell me never to say,” I replied. “Because it could be ironic foreshadowing.”

“I’m talking about Doris Finch,” said Amaryllis.

“Oh,” I said. “Well, go on then. Wolverine had his hangups about being the one in the spotlight, and an obsession with what it would take in order to do an impossible trick. He knew that he could never share the one thing that he loved, which was fame. What’s Doris Finch’s damage?”

“I have no idea, if you’re asking why she is the way she is,” said Amaryllis. “But in terms of who she is, she’s the person who ruins everything. She is the tragedy of the commons. She’s the reason that places have ‘limit one per customer’ signs, why laws have to explicitly spell out everything that the vast majority of people figure out for themselves. People like Doris Finch are the reason that you have to have laws in place for common decency. The Republic of Doris Finch doesn’t have police, because if those police were Doris Finch, they would take bribes and operate shake-downs, then shirk any work that didn’t personally benefit them. The stupidest thing about it is that she’s not dumb, she couldn’t be and still have as much faculty with magic as she does, but when it comes to placing an ounce of trust into other people, even if it’s herself — or even absent trust, if you ask her to just not fuck over anyone,” Amaryllis threw up her hands. “Almost anyone else, in her shoes, would have done better.”

“And this colors your opinion on Hugh Jackman’s character?” I asked.

“On Caldlow,” said Amaryllis. “And yes.” She crossed her arms. “It’s implied that the technology was one of a kind, never to be recreated, and it was his fault. He was a monster. Watching that movie is like if I showed you a movie about someone who was obviously supposed to be Pol Pot, except it was presented as a tragedy and a commentary on the nature of art. No. Fuck him. And Caldlow is worse than Doris, because at least Doris has the excuse that her brand of magic doesn’t work for anyone else, not that she would have given it up willingly if it did.”

I nodded, desperately trying to remember who Pol Pot was and drawing a blank. Cambodia, right? Probably genocide? Regardless, the movie seemed to touch a rare sore spot for Amaryllis, got a thumbs down in terms of ever bringing it to Aerb, and we did a rare doubleheader in order for her to get the taste of that film out of her mouth: she was much more a fan of A Fish Called Wanda.

After some time had passed, the gunfire and fighting died down. Pretty much none of it was directed our way, behind our steel shielding and Grak’s wards.

“Alright,” a Doris finally said, speaking to us. “That’s settled.”

I popped my head out. It was roughly the same number of them as before, but they were standing in a field of corpses from their fallen enemies, allies, and clones. I saw a few Dorises who were definitely from the same stock, wearing all the same gear and with the same tattoos and hairstyles, but, presumably, having switched ‘sides’. The only significant change, beyond the wounds some of them had and the marks of battle, was that most of them were wearing red instead of blue.

(There was a quite interesting phenomenon within the DFEZ called the ‘Conservation of Dorises’. The upshot was that there would only ever be as many Dorises as necessary, because if there were more than that, resource scarcity and general incentives would mean that the Dorises would kill each other. Therefore, if thirty Dorises were needed for talking to us and getting a cut, there would always be thirty Dorises, because any more than that, they would backstab for a position, and any less than that, and they would make clones.)

“What was that?” asked Amaryllis, standing up.

“Internal fighting,” Doris replied. “Nothing for you to worry about. We’re not interested in killing you.” This was bullshit. They would have killed us if they thought that they could, because they would get our stuff.

“Do we have a deal or not?” asked Amaryllis.

The Doris shifted in place. “You’re not talking to the same people. We don’t have access to the same magic.”

“You’ve got to be fucking kidding me,” said Amaryllis. “Then what are we doing here?”

“We can take you to them and ransom you off,” said Doris. “They’ll pay us a fee.”

“Any reason we shouldn’t just kill you all?” asked Amaryllis. “Any reason not to cut through you like a scythe and try to find them on our own?” She was saying this with rather a lot of void rifles in the vicinity, against thirty women who could make duplicates of themselves in half a second. But we knew Doris well enough to know that they were shit at coordination, and they knew it.

“It would take you longer and be more dangerous,” said Doris. “The only reason to kill us would be retribution for the inconvenience and whatever pleasure you’d get from it.”

For a moment, I really thought that Amaryllis was going to take her up on it, but whatever anger she was feeling at the situation, she didn’t let it get the best of her. I was worried about a double or triple cross, obviously, considering that it was Doris Finch we were talking about, but if it was a specific faction of Dorises that had the magic we needed, then bumbling around the EZ trying to find them seemed like it was a fool’s errand.

“You understand force and you understand power,” said Amaryllis. “If you try to move against us, we’ll end you.”

“Of course,” nodded Doris. “It’s just business.”

“A few of you tried to shoot me,” I said.

Doris shrugged. “We had to try. You seem like you’re strong enough that it won’t happen again.” She turned to Amaryllis. “But you should know that if we think we’re going to get fucked, we’ll throw our lives at you.”

Amaryllis nodded, but I think we all knew it was a bluff. Doris wasn’t self-sacrificing. Amaryllis, now there was a woman who would be able to make a suicide bomber clone. If Doris Finch tried it, her clone would, at best, start up an argument about which of them should be the one to do it, or try to spawn another clone to do the work for her. At worst, the clone would attack the original, or vice versa, not that they knew which was a clone and which wasn’t. That said, a Doris Finch would, if she thought that her life was about to end, try to take as many people down with her as she possibly could, especially other Dorises.

There was only a little bit of looting before we got going. One of the ways that Doris’s power was busted was that it cloned over her equipment too, but the big drawback was that the clone’s gear would disappear after twenty-four hours. The loophole was that if a clone with an hour left on the clock for their equipment made a clone, that new clone would have their clock reset. The answer then, at least some of the time, was to just make a clone, kill it, and take its stuff, keeping both sets of equipment until the timer was up, when you would find out which one had the longer timer. The clone would naturally resist that, but the Dorises had methods of clone production that would put the clone in a position to be easily murdered. Most of the equipment that was laying on the ground, if looted, would simply disappear by the next day.

We walked, traveling slightly behind the Dorises, because no way were we going to be willingly flanked by them. If it did come down to a fight, I was worried that we might not be able to kill them all before they simply swarmed us, especially since they had void rifles. My boots were soaked in blood from the firefight they’d had, and as a demonstration of their combat abilities, it was a little bit frightening, because they were above the level of your average cannon fodder, and there were just so damned many of them. If even one of them escaped, you could be met with a (dysfunctional) army a minute later.

They had incentive to kill us, naturally, especially since we were visibly carrying a rather large number of entads, and those entads, in the hands of a Doris, could be multiplied many times over, abusing the twenty-four hour rule (though the copies couldn’t leave the EZ, just like Doris). This was one of the reasons that travel into the EZ was so heavily restricted: with the wrong entad, the entire zone might get a whole lot worse, not just for the Dorises, but for people on the outside. Void weapons aside, a few of the Dorises were carrying obvious entads, a pistol made of slate and a sword whose surface reflected a false reality among them, all copied many times over. I’d been watching the battle, and neither was terribly special: the pistol fired off small stones instead of normal ammunition and could burst into shards, while the sword had some kind of parry and attack reflection assist.

We were in a relatively uninhabited part of the EZ, away from the big city, but it didn’t take us too long to reach a settlement, which consisted of some of the ugliest steel mage buildings I had ever seen. I’d thought that the ones in Necrolaborem were ugly, and they were, but they were ugliness with craft to them, focused entirely on functionality rather than looking good. These, which I presumed some breed of Doris had made herself, weren’t just ugly in the sense of not even trying to be pretty, they were ugly by virtue of being poorly made. The windows were misshapen, not that they had any glass to go in them, and the structure wasn’t square, instead listing to one side. All the buildings were like that, without any seeming craft or care, which wasn’t a surprise, because Doris would shirk work wherever she could.

“How far are we traveling?” asked Amaryllis.

“Not far,” replied Doris.

“Specifically,” said Amaryllis.

“Another mile,” said Doris. “They have a camp.”

The further into the zone we got, the less green there was, and there hadn’t been much to begin with. The Dorises weren’t great stewards of their land, and even if they had been, the sheer number of corpses around wasn’t good for most varieties of plants. Here and there we saw white fungal mushroom looking things, tall stalks and button caps, which I was pretty sure were growing where corpses had been dumped, based on the bones I occasionally saw at their base. There were vines with red leaves growing on a few of the buildings, plants that I knew fed on the plentiful blood in the zone. Small blue motes flitted around and settled down from time to time, another part of the ecology. It gave the place an unearthly feeling.

We saw other Dorises as well, though usually only briefly, or peeking out through windows. My crown let me see through the eyes of those holed up in their ugly buildings, and I regretted looking, because I saw a Doris going about the process of butchering her clone, and another in the middle of eating raw chunks of flesh. It was no secret that this was how the Dorises kept themselves fed, but it was still disturbing to see. A few of those rooms had tiny closet-like structures, the entrances so small that you couldn’t get out. Those, I knew, were used for clone killing.

The ‘camp’ we were heading to was bristling with armed Dorises, many of them in blue, and our little group stayed back, with our own opposite-faction Dorises in front.

“What now?” asked Amaryllis.

“They’ll send out a messenger,” said the lead Doris. “We’ll send one out too. They’ll negotiate, then we’ll hand you off when they pay us.”

The process for sending a messenger was to have one of our Dorises make a clone of themselves, which was done after she’d been deprived of her weapons, and while a fair number of guns were trained on her. It let me see the process of ‘cloning’ up close and without the frantic energy of battle going on. It was nothing more than a brief blurring, followed by a split, the whole process incredibly brief for what it was. When it was done, one of the clones was grabbed at gunpoint and made to march toward the camp, where a different Doris was following the same procedure.

“What happens to her when you’re done?” I asked.

“If she does a good job, she can live,” said Doris. “That’s her incentive.”

“And if they try to take her?” I asked. “Or she tries to defect?”

“We can hit her from this range,” Doris replied. I watched as a few of them raised rifles, aiming them squarely at the negotiating party. “It happens.”

We were, as a matter of fact, almost exactly at the proper distance from the camp so that we weren’t in much danger from their weapons, but so that the midway point could be struck from both sides. This was, apparently, the kind of thing that Dorises engaged in with some frequency, often enough that they had procedures for it. It was insane, because Doris Finch was insane. I wondered whether they would actually let the negotiating Doris go free, but figured that they must, because if they didn’t, the Doris would know that and bolt.

“What’s the difference between factions?” I asked.

The main Doris looked at me, and I could feel the others looking too.

“You’re red, they’re blue, what the difference?” I asked. “Just curious.” I wondered where they got the dyes, but I wasn’t going to ask.

“Resources,” said Doris, then turned back to watch the two Dorises who were negotiating with each other. I kept looking at her though, and eventually she continued. “Information, skills, and materials. Blues have most of the magics, hoard most of the entads, and control most of the city. Reds are more outskirts, better skills with materials. Greens are agriculture and food prep. Oranges are pustule mages. Purples are star mages and steel mages.” She looked between us. “How much of that did you know?”

“Some,” said Amaryllis.

“You people are supposed to believe in tit for tat,” said Doris. “We want to know what the outside world knows about the EZ.”

“Almost everything,” said Amaryllis. “There are regular forays into the EZ to capture a Doris for questioning.”

“That mostly gets Reds,” replied Doris. “You have better surveillance than that.”

“We don’t personally, no,” replied Amaryllis. “But we would know if there had been a substantial change in abilities. If a Doris has trained in a new discipline, it probably wouldn’t take long for it to be, if not public knowledge, then at least known to people with our clearances.”

“You have news from outside?” asked Doris.

“Skin magic was excluded,” said Amaryllis.

Doris nodded. “How bad?”

“Lots of deaths,” said Amaryllis. “Less than usual for a metro area. Not enpersoned. And it’s a free exclusion now.”

“No heat off us then,” said Doris. “But that’s another athenaeum down.”

“Two,” said Amaryllis. “It happened in Li’o.” Li’o would recover, naturally, but it would take some time.

“Huh,” said Doris. She squinted in the direction of the meeting. “Looks like they’re done,” said Doris, raising her own rifle and pointing it at their negotiator, who was walking back.

“They’re willing to trade,” said the negotiating Doris when she came back. “They’re offering three entad copies and four slaves, two Green, two Purple.”

“Distinct slaves?” asked Doris.

“Yes,” Doris nodded.

The leader Doris, as I was thinking of her, nodded, then looked at us. “You’re going to be transferred now,” she said. “They’ll stab us in the back if they have the chance. You walk, slowly, until you get to the midway point. There’s a kill zone there. We’ll send the negotiator out to confirm the function of the entads and the condition of slaves, they’ll send one out to make sure you’re who you say you are, and then we’ll all go on our way. If anything goes wrong, odds are both sides open fire, so you make sure that nothing goes wrong.”

“Understood,” I nodded. “Pleasure doing business with you.”

We went through the whole procedure as outlined, tensed up the whole time. I was really worried that as soon as we were on our way past the midpoint, the Reds we’d left would start taking potshots at us, but to my surprise and relief, they didn’t, maybe because the odds of hitting us were so low, maybe because they worried about an escalation. A Doris would put effort into depriving a different Doris of resources, but not too much effort. The way you had to look at Doris, at least from what I had heard, was that she would fuck people over only so long as it had some marginal benefit for her. In this case, it helped that the Doris slaves they were taking were in the way of the line of fire.

The Blues were organized, their camp in a bit better condition than the buildings we’d seen on the way in. At its center was a magestone building, maybe one that their captive steel mage had built, and that was where we were led, past armed Dorises that served as guards. Once inside, we were led to a big room with a table, where three Dorises, all cleaner and in better clothes, were waiting for us. The style differences were wild, with one of them in a vest and pants, the other in a full dress, and the third under a cloak with her shaved head covered.

“Welcome,” said the one on the right. She gestured to where four chairs were arranged in front of them. ‘Chair’ was being really generous, because they were made of lumps of magestone. I assumed that one of the steel mages had made them, and now that they were in place, they couldn’t be easily moved. “Take a seat. We apologize for the unpleasantness.”

“We just want to make a deal,” said Amaryllis. “All we want is tracking, because there are people we want to find. We’ll split up installments, so there’s back and forth. Please.”

“Things have become complicated,” said the shaved Doris.

“Are you fucking kidding me,” said Amaryllis. “Complicated in a way that means you can’t take payment for services rendered?”

“They need a service from us,” I said, staring at the Dorises. “Let me guess, you either need us to put down something that you conjured up, or you need us to be your hands outside the zone.” It was the kind of thing that I would have done, if I were the Dungeon Master.

“The former,” nodded the shaved Doris. “There was a research project in Dorisopolis that went sideways. It’s beyond our ability to contain. Do that, and we’ll be able to help you with whatever you need tracked. We’re senior within the organization, direct copies of leadership overseeing this sector.”

“Except that you would just stab us in the back,” said Amaryllis. “A Doris doesn’t do things out of gratitude, she does things because of expected reward. So if we dealt with this problem for you, we’d still have to pay, and I would rather skip to the part where we pay. We know, for a fact, that you were doing tracking as late as two months ago.”

“The problem happened a month ago and has been uncontained since then,” said Doris. “If we do the tracking for you, we’ll have a week, maybe less, before it grows out of control. Even if we could do the tracking you needed before then, it wouldn’t matter, because we couldn’t use whatever you gave us, because we would be dead.”

“I see,” said Amaryllis. “And everyone outside the zone?”

“It’s unclear,” replied Doris.

“Can we have a sidebar for a moment?” asked Raven.

“Go ahead,” nodded the middle Doris. She had three piercings through her left nostril, and I wondered who had done them for her. The information I’d taken in about the EZ hadn’t mentioned the mundane stuff like that, whether there was some Doris who plied her trade as a piercing or tattoo artist.

“Grak, ward please?” asked Raven.

Grak looked at her for a moment, then got out his now-useless wand and circled around where we were sitting, frowning in concentration and muttering a children’s poem in Groglir while he put on a show of erecting a ward that would give us silence.

“I don’t think we need to hide our abilities from them,” said Grak once he was finished.

“It’s a precaution,” said Raven.

“A sensible one,” said Amaryllis. “If they really do have a slow-motion calamity, I can see the upsides of letting it wipe out all life in the EZ, for what it’s worth. We could find a different way to get what we need. Maybe there are some quests that complete themselves.”

“The Library never banked on exclusions,” said Raven. “Every timeline where some calamity destroyed or otherwise permanently and irrevocably altered the world, we would send our best to go stop or divert it. I’m of the opinion that should be the policy of our group as well. Even if you think that killing nine million of this woman is a good thing, there’s a good chance that the stakes are there for a reason. Exclusions never allowed Uther to circumvent an adventure.”

“Fine,” said Amaryllis. “I wasn’t actually suggesting it, just saying that it’s very tempting for obvious reasons.”

“We’re going to work with a woman like her?” asked Grak. “We should expect to be betrayed.”

“Right,” I said. “And if we help, we should expect that they’re going to give us nothing in return. Best we can do is ask for an up-front payment or something like it.” I rubbed my face a bit. “You know, I was kind of hoping that they would send us to a third EZ. It would be kind of funny to have a quest chain that required visiting all of the thirteen.” I looked at their faces. “Not laugh-out-loud funny.”

“I really thought that we were good on our timeline with Perisev,” said Amaryllis, ignoring me, as she rightly should have. “If this can’t be done in a week or less, we’re going to need to start worrying about her, given that we need to get back to the Captain.”

“It’ll be fine, one way or another,” I said.

Grak made a show of dropping the ward, and we resumed our discussion with the Dorises.

“So,” said Amaryllis. “My guess is that you were violating imperial research bans.”

“The Empire of Common Cause has been emphatic that we’re not a part of it,” said Doris. “We Blues made an offer to abide by a few of their laws and were rejected.”

“So that’s a yes,” said Amaryllis. “Yes, you were basically trying to do things that would result in, if not an exclusion, then the kind of situation that you currently find yourself facing.”

The Dorises looked at each other, then nodded.

“Tell us then,” said Raven. “What kind of magic?”

“Blood magic,” said shaved-head Doris. “A contingent of Dorises have trained in blood magic, and we Blues have been trying to find some way to exploit it.” I knew enough to read between the lines there. The Dorises didn’t go off and train in magic on their own, because something like blood magic was an uphill battle even if you lived in a stable society and had decently optimized institutions of learning. No, what happened with the Dorises was that those with relative resources and power would lock their lessers in dungeons and demand that they learn magic Or Else, and sometimes this worked. That was supposedly how they’d gotten steel magic, star magic, bone magic, and pustule magic.

“We have the same blood,” said the vested Doris. “Blood has power, and we were able to gather more of that power in one place than anyone before through all human history.” This was where you were supposed to say ‘mortal history’, but my understanding was that humanocentric language had been in vogue up until not that long ago. “It was showing promising results, until it wasn’t.”

“And what’s the specific problem?” asked Raven. “You were playing around with vast quantities of extensible blood, which failure condition did you run into?”

“We’re not sure,” said the vested Doris. “We used star mages to open a portal to the elemental plane of blood, just large enough for one of us to fit through. We sent a blood mage there. Something happened, something foul, and through the portal came a monster. Now they’re here, and growing. Nothing we’ve tried has been able to kill them.”

“A worm, about this big around?” asked Raven, holding up her hands to make a circle, thumb touching thumb and index finger touching index finger.

“That’s part of it,” said the vested Doris, not seeming terribly surprised. “The information leaked?”

“Not as such,” replied Raven. “But it’s something that I’ve dealt with before. We should be able to handle it.” She looked at Amaryllis. “I’ll leave it to my party members to negotiate terms.”

“We’ll deal with the problem,” said Amaryllis. “In exchange, you’ll get one of your slaves to teach star magic to my husband.” It took me a moment to realize that she meant me. It was still pretty new.

“We don’t have the time for that,” said shaved-head Doris. “The worms have already infested the research building. If they get out, we’re not confident in being able to stop them. They feed on blood. It’s not something that we can throw bodies at. And there’s something else in there, an unknown, if the reports are correct. We need that portal brought down and the problem dealt with. We don’t have time to give an education.”

“He’s a fast learner,” said Amaryllis. “Five hours of extended education, and in return, we’ll deal with the problem. On top of that, before we go in, I want the first tracking done. It’s not one that we’re hopeful about, but it’s one that you’ve almost certainly done, even if it was just because you wanted to know. Uther Penndraig.” We really weren’t expecting results on that one, because it was very likely that Uther was wearing the amulet of nondetection, an absurdly powerful bit of kit that was meant to no-sell almost any attempts at detection.

“He’s in the Fel Seed EZ,” said the shaved-head Doris. “Halfway down a dimensional tube. We can give you the location, once you’re finished with your work.”

“That shouldn’t be possible,” said Raven, leaning forward. “You shouldn’t be able to know where he is. He’s got an entad on, an incredibly powerful one. It blocks any attempt at divination.”

“That would explain why it was so faint,” replied the Doris.

Raven was staring with an intensity that I rarely saw from her. I knew that she had done damned near everything she could in order to find Uther, and that the amulet of nondetection had stymied quite a bit of her searching. It was probably disheartening, to come into a place like this, where they had a novel magic, and to have it simply work without many problems. It made sense to me though: the Dungeon Master wouldn’t leave only one path to follow, he would leave several.

“Your detection is probabilistic,” said Grak. “It was faint because you only detected those times he lost or removed the entad.”

“Maybe,” replied Doris.

“That would imply that he’s not dead,” said Raven.

“It would,” nodded Doris. “More information will have to wait until we’re not under threat of death. We can run it again. We’ll get your husband a room with a star mage, and then you’ll work with us on making sure that the EZ stays intact.”

A Bloody Mess

I wished that I had Grak’s temporal plate, because I wanted time to think, not just about what was going on, but about what I knew. Pinno had said that the entity had acted like Doris until they reasoned with it, and if it was acting like Doris because it was Doris, then that meant she could be reasoned with and talked into not being the person that everyone thought she was. And for her talk of moving against the Blues, she hadn’t actually done that, she had been waiting in this facility, waiting for … well, by all appearances, waiting for us, or someone like us, an imperial response or something. Had she heard everything we’d said? If she had, then she would have heard everything we’d discussed with Pinno as well.

“Okay,” I said. “We’re letting you free.”

“I’m not sure that’s wise,” said Raven.

“We promised,” I said. I looked over at Grak, giving him a nod. If I had figured it out, I hoped that he had too.

“Juniper,” said Amaryllis. “I really think that we should talk about this before doing anything rash. If she’s a world class blood mage, one with more blood, hers and others, than anyone has had before —”

“Promises work better when people know they’re ironclad,” I said. “You’re saying we should defect against Doris? That justifies a lack of trust in us.”

Amaryllis was watching me, and I could feel her mismatched eyes boring into me, stripping me bare. She was good at reading people, but not that good if she was in the wrong mindset for a proper reading to take place. Maybe she could see that Doris wasn’t actually afraid of us, but maybe she thought that was because of typical Doris fatalism, not because she had the upper hand. Maybe she thought that I was being headstrong, not that I knew something that she didn’t. I wasn’t trying to make my face readable, because Doris was watching us, but I was hoping she would understand.

“Okay,” she finally said. “You’re right.”

Grak dropped the ward with a brief gesture, and Doris scooped a handful of blood up from the ground, then tossed it at the boundary where the ward had been, testing it.

“You don’t use a wand?” she asked Grak.

“No,” he replied.

“What are your plans once you’re out of here?” I asked her.

“Good question,” she replied. She stepped forward, cautiously, until she was past where the ward had been. She’d been careful to move so as to not put herself too much closer to us. “Did the Blues send you here?” She was directing most of her attention at me, not the others.

“They did,” I replied. “They wanted us to shut this down, but they didn’t tell us quite what we were dealing with, and it seemed as though to them, this was a threat so powerful they couldn’t ignore it. At the same time, they couldn’t deal with it on their own. I’m not sure whether or not they knew what they were up against. It seems to me that if you’re gunning for them, we should make a deal.”

“A deal?” she asked.

“A deal,” I nodded. “We were going to teleport in supplies in exchange for tracking a few individuals, hopefully establishing a long-term deal with them, tit for tat. Presumably that capability is going to be yours once you make your move, which means that we should make a deal with you.”

“You would double cross them,” said Doris, nodding.

“No,” said Amaryllis. “We’re not allied with them, just trading partners. We’re not offering material assistance to your coup, we’re just trying to figure out something that protects our interests.”

“But you are double crossing them, because you said that you would do this,” replied Doris. “You said that you would deal with what had happened here.”

“They lied to us about what was going on,” I said. “Maybe they didn’t fully know what had come in and killed so many people, but they knew more than they said.” Or they had intentionally shielded the clones we’d talked to from knowing enough. “They were talking about every Doris in the EZ dying, and maybe the chance of the problem spilling out beyond that. If they had been upfront with us about this being an internal matter, there’s a good chance that we wouldn’t have agreed to deal with it. If you hide things in the contract, the contract is null and void.”

“Well,” said Doris. “It’s food for thought. And who are these people you’re looking for?”

“Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle is one,” said Amaryllis. “Fel Seed is another. Aside from that, we have a list of names, some just as tests. There are certain people we would like to make sure are dead.”

“We used to talk to him,” said Doris. “You’re trying to kill him, I suppose?”

“Wait, you talked to Fel Seed?” I asked.

“No, of course not,” Doris scoffed. “Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle. He arranged for one half of a communication entad to be transported to us. He thought that we were all natural allies. He got frustrated with us though, and eventually stopped calling.”

“Huh,” I said.

“We didn’t mean any offense,” said Amaryllis.

“None taken,” said Doris. “And if that’s what you want, what are you offering in return?”

“Whatever you need, in your new regime,” I said.

“Food, clothing, maybe even entads,” said Amaryllis.

“Labor,” I said. “Expertise. Companionship.”

“You would send people in?” asked Doris. “We don’t have a lot of other people living here. The Empire forbids it.” It went unsaid that life could be hard for someone who came in, and amenities left something to be desired.

“The Empire can be swayed on the classification of this place as a major exclusion,” said Amaryllis. “You’re excluded, but that doesn’t have to mean that you keep on living the life you’ve been living. All it will take is agreeing to follow a few different rules.”

“If I follow the rules, that means I’m at the mercy of those who don’t,” said Doris. “You know that. Anyone who comes to the EZ knows that.”

“You’re in a unique position,” I said. “You’re powerful. You might be the single most powerful Doris to have ever lived.” She definitely was, if I was right about her. We were surrounded by her blood. She hadn’t even threatened us with an explosion of blood at lethal velocities, which I took to mean that she simply wasn’t worried about us. “You don’t need to make doubles, which means that you don’t have to worry that you’re going to get betrayed by someone who’s exactly as strong as you. Imagine yourself as, if not a god, then a demigod. You’re not at the mercy of those who don’t follow the rules, because even if you follow them, you’re still stronger. When you’re in a position of power, you can dictate how things will be. The only enemy you have here is yourself.”

“But you’re suggesting that I don’t split,” she said. “Meaning that I wouldn’t have myself for an enemy.”

“I don’t know,” I said. “But I meant your only enemy was yourself in the sense that you have to worry about self-sabotage, the infectious nature of self-hatred. It applies even if you’re not literally set against yourself.” I was watching her. There was a risk in making this about me, rather than about her, but if there was some grander point to Doris Finch, then I supposed this was it. “It’s easy, when you hate yourself, to just fuck things up because you think that’s what you deserve, or because you don’t care about what happens to you — or you only care at the lowest, base level, when the you of tomorrow seems far away. All the slavery and murder that have marked the EZ since its creation, that hasn’t just been because it’s expedient, or downright necessary, it’s been because you don’t give a shit about those other Dorises. More than that, actually. You know them, and you think that they deserve what they get.”

“Which they do,” said Doris.

“Which means that you deserve it too,” said Amaryllis. The tone was sympathetic, but the words weren’t.

“And I do,” said Doris. Her eyes were on Amaryllis. “Obviously I do.”

That gave Amaryllis pause, but I had expected it. I understood the mindset.

“Forget deals with us,” I said. “You were sitting here for a reason. If you wanted to break out, you could have broken out. You’ve been building up power there in the plane of blood, and at a guess, you’ve had a capacity to steamroll the other Dorises for, I don’t know, months. The Empire might be able to stop you, but it would probably cost them resources that they don’t want to spend, which means that the prospect of being untethered from this fucked up society is ahead of you. But you haven’t acted, because it’s scary.”

“Scary?” she asked, not doubting, just seeking clarification.

“It’s scary to be in charge,” I said. “It’s scary to not have anything to fight against anymore, to have no enemies that can realistically stop you from doing whatever you want.”

“Something you know from experience, I suppose?” she asked, raising a blood-matted eyebrow.

“Yes,” I nodded. “But I realized that even before the world was cracked open in front of me,” I said. This was overstating my abilities and means by quite a bit, but we had a billion obols now, and if I had prep time, I could rival the greatest. I wasn’t a god, but maybe a lesser demigod, again, with prep time. “Even for people who can’t clone themselves, there’s such a thing as being your own worst enemy. From what’s been written about you, you shirk work unless you’re forced into it, you take shortcuts and cheat yourself, you have very little drive — honestly, I think some of it is probably just detachment and numbness, but I don’t actually know you, I just know myself. If you want to talk about your future and how you’re going to manage it, we can sit down.” I glanced over at Amaryllis. “My wife has some good thoughts on how to deal with yourself, both internally and externally.”

“I don’t want an advisor,” said Doris, shifting her stance. “Someone who is going to try to turn me to their own ends? No thank you.”

“Someone to help you be the person you want to be, or the person you should be,” I said. “And I agree, you would want to be careful about who you let into that position, and you don’t know us at all, we’re just … not you, and that makes us a bit more worthwhile to talk to. We all know you could kill us whenever you wanted, so we’re safe to bounce things off of.”

“You’re making assumptions about me,” said Doris.

“If I’m over-estimating you, I think that’s probably fine,” I said. “But I’m not trying to talk myself out of a jam here, I really am trying to help you.”

“There are obvious incentives for you,” she said.

“Sure,” I replied. “And that makes it hard for both of us. It makes the things I’m saying look like they might be a ploy. Obviously there are benefits to being friends with the strongest Doris in the EZ, the one who no one can steal from, the one who no one can kill, even if you decide that you don’t want to be the lord ruler of the others.”

“And why would I decide that?” she asked.

“It’s what I would do,” I said with a shrug. “If I had to pick a bunch of things to be, manager, negotiator, and politician would all be at the bottom of the list. I’d let someone else handle things, even at some cost to myself, because that’s how much I don’t want to spend my time trying to coerce people into doing what I want them to do, or making hard decisions about resource allocation, infrastructure, cultural norms, laws … I’d have preferences, obviously, but if it were possible, I’d have someone perfectly aligned with me do it for me.”

“The same is true for anyone,” said Doris. She was staring at me. I was doing the bulk of the talking, which I knew wasn’t my strong suit, but I kind of got where she was coming from, and maybe that made up for the lack of raw social power. My picture of Blood God Doris was that she had been through the wringer, fighting for ages, not wanting to fight, but being forced into it, over and over again, employing temporary measures to stay ahead, to survive, but just fucking exhausted by it all. If she rested though, some other Doris would pull ahead.

“Not everyone,” said Amaryllis. “I enjoy that kind of thing.”

“You enjoy making hard decisions?” asked Doris.

“Sometimes,” said Amaryllis. “I enjoy being at the center of a humming enterprise. I like setting up tasks and then checking them off, one by one, coordinating departments to solve keystone problems, coming in to learn the people and issues involved. I enjoy the process of picking between two goods, or even two evils. Some people don’t like the act of evaluation, or sour on it when there’s skin in the game, but I’ve always had a taste for it. That’s not true of Juniper, and from what he seems to think he knows about you, that’s not true of you, but there are people who gravitate toward those roles, and I’m one of them.”

“Odd,” said Doris. She tapped her foot and looked at us. We weren’t particularly acting like she could kill us, which I was sure she noticed. If it came down to it … well, it depended on what her precise limits were. “I’d take more food and more water,” she finally said.

“You could have a hot shower, if you wanted to,” I said. “We’re not in any rush.”

“I don’t suppose you have a hot shower in that vest?” asked Doris, raising an eyebrow at Grak.

“I do,” he nodded.

From within the vest he pulled out another piece of kit he’d picked up, a tiny little house the size of a coat button. He hesitated for just a moment, then walked some distance away from us, well beyond the star magic structure, and set it down within his anti-blood ward, the only place where the floor was cleared. With a command word and a hand signal, it began to shake and grow where it was, until it had enlarged to its full size, which wasn’t very big. I was pretty sure that it was based on a tiny house that I had seen on TV: I loved tiny houses.

“It’s a portable home,” he explained to Doris as he walked back to us. “It has a small tank with hot water, a small stove, a refrigerator, a shower, a toilet, and a bed. It’s yours to use. The cupboards are stocked. Take what you want.”

Doris hesitated. “Bound to you?” she asked.

“To me,” said Amaryllis. “Invested in him.”

“You could have this for every Doris in the EZ,” she said. “Hot water, a shower, it would change everything.”

“That’s one of the reasons we brought it,” Amaryllis lied. “From what I understand about the way investiture works with you, it would have no problem proliferating, so long as it stayed invested.” This would obviously require a lot of clone killing, which was left unsaid. To Amaryllis, and to a slightly lesser extent, to me, killing the clones the moment they were created in order to steal their stuff wasn’t much of an ethical question at all. Amaryllis would have murdered a clone of herself without thinking too much about it, and that clone would have happily gone along with it. “We do, of course, have access to a wide variety of entads that we could give to the EZ. Historically, that approach hasn’t yielded results, but perhaps things would be different this time.”

“Maybe,” said Doris. She was looking at the little house. Maybe she was thinking that it was a trap, but I was pretty sure that she was strong enough that there was no trap that we could have set for her that would have been strong enough. I wasn’t sure about our odds in a straightforward battle, but I was confident that trying to lure her into a trap would result in battle. The blood all around us was her blood. Her body … well, maybe she had a spare on the other side of the portal, or somewhere in the facility, or maybe she just didn’t need it anymore. We didn’t actually know what her powers were.

In theory, given that my fingerprints were all over Aerb, its systems designed by an alternate reality version of myself, I might be able to figure it out just by thinking about what I thought was cool. I was trying to brainstorm when Doris began moving, not particularly quickly, in the direction of the tiny house. We waited in silence until she had gone inside.

“Well,” I said. “I think that went well.”

“How powerful is she?” asked Amaryllis.

“Dunno,” I said.

“Did you get outside information?” she asked. This was by way of asking if I’d gotten a quest update.

“Nope,” I said. “And just so you know, I’d put even odds on her being able to hear us.”

“To hear us,” said Amaryllis. “Through all this blood?”

“Yeah,” I said. “Maybe. It’s certainly possible.” Anything was possible. That was one of the things that made this approach attractive. Partly I just didn’t want to have another big fucking battle that we skated through by the skin of our teeth.

“Grak,” said Amaryllis. “Wards?”

“Better if you come near me,” he said. “I’m saving concordance.”

We all stepped in towards him, getting inside the wards that he’d put up.

“To make it clear, we’re vulnerable to a blast?” asked Raven.

“I’m afraid I don’t understand what’s going on here,” said Pinno. “Something about the future we saw … this is different.”

“No,” I said. “Not actually different, I don’t think, your books were just making their own guesses about what had happened. A giant blood entity came through the portal and took over the EZ, it’s just that the blood entity was, in fact, a Doris who achieved the absolute highest heights of blood magic through being able to clone her own blood, living non-stop in the elemental plane of blood, and having maybe as many of a million clones working on the problem at once, with the best of them culling the rest. The entity acted like Doris because she was Doris, and listened to reason because Doris would listen to reason.”

We shouldn’t be talking at all, signed Amaryllis. I know you’re deadening the noise, but we don’t know what we’re dealing with.

That means cutting people out of the conversation, I signed back. And it presents Doris, who is probably watching us, with the wrong picture of us, one where we’re paranoid schemers who have learned Gimb just so we can sign at each other without anyone listening in.

“So this is the plan?” asked Amaryllis. “We teach what might be the most powerful blood mage the world has ever known how to be good?”

“No,” I said. “Look, good can come later, right now, all she needs to know is that she’s basically invincible, that no one can take that away, and that it’s not a scramble for survival anymore. She’s experienced an unbelievable amount of trauma, on top of maybe not starting as the best person, and —” I stopped short.

“Joon?” asked Amaryllis.

“Just … Bethel,” I said, sighing.

“Bethel?” asked Pinno.

“He’s making the same excuses for her as he did for a former friend of ours,” said Raven.

“No,” I said. “No, I’m just forgiving Bethel, if only a fraction, and wondering whether this is all part of a planned lesson that was intended to help bring her back.”

“I’m afraid I’m lost,” said Pinno, narrowing his eyebrow ridges.

“It’s complicated,” I said. “Long personal history stuff.” I hesitated. “I, or someone else, can explain at least some of it later.”

“You think that Doris Finch is an argument in favor of having Bethel return?” asked Amaryllis.

“If Doris can be reformed, that is a good argument,” said Grak.

“They’re totally different,” I said. “I mean, completely, totally different, and it’s not really what we’re doing here, because this isn’t actually about Bethel at all, it’s just a thought that I had. I was explaining that the Dorises, as people, are completely fucked up. They’ve been suffering here, for a long time, at their own hands. And for this particular one, who is probably better off never splitting again, if that’s even something she could do, if it even matters given her presumed skill — for her, it’s important that she understands that she’s in a position where it doesn’t have to be how it was. Once she’s there, once she’s traipsed up Maslow’s hierarchy of needs, then we can start talking to her about what her life should be like, how and why to break herself of her current terrible habits that have been learned over the course of a lifetime of pain and suffering. But I think what comes first is just saying, ‘hey, it can be okay now’.”

“We came in here with an objective,” said Amaryllis. “More than one, actually.” I was pretty sure the translation of that was ‘two quests’. “And so far as I know, those objectives haven’t changed.”

“Yeah,” I said. “Fuck ‘em.”

“Juniper,” said Raven. “You understand that there are very important people who might take offense to that?”

“I do,” I said. “I’m taking a gamble that we’re not on that much of a railroad. We’re going down roads, but some of them are being built right in front of us, and just because there’s a plan doesn’t mean that plan can’t be changed. If this opportunity was placed in front of us, it was for a reason, and I don’t think that reason was just so we would get some exposition before the boss fight.”

Pinno was looking very confused.

“And this is going to be your approach with all of them?” asked Amaryllis. “You’re going to talk to Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle about why torturing people in the name of commerce is probably a bad idea?”

“No,” I said. “Him, if I had to, I would talk about that desperate need to deny that you’ve done anything wrong, even when it’s clear to everyone that you have. I’d tell him that it’s seductive to believe that we live in an unjust world, and therefore excuse our patterns of being shitty to others.”

“But you’re not going to actually do that, are you?” asked Amaryllis.

“I wasn’t planning on it, no,” I said. “And even here, I don’t know that what I’m proposing is the right call. But she was waiting here, Amaryllis. Regardless of anything that’s happening on the narrative level, she was waiting here, and I don’t get the sense that she was marshalling power or waiting to see who would get called in, I think it’s because the idea of being the ruler of the whole EZ, especially this one, is fucking terrifying, as it should be.”

“You’re projecting,” said Raven.

“I’m finding common ground,” I said. “Realistically, our other option is to fight. Maybe we can win —”

“We can,” said Grak.

“We can?” I asked him.

“I left the ward up and removed the boundary,” said Grak. “When she passed through it I got a sense of how much blood she contained. If her extreme hypertension is suddenly relieved, the explosion will vaporize everything around us. No blood would remain. The struts would be destroyed and the portal would close.”

“Does she know that?” asked Amaryllis.

“I cannot tell with warding,” said Grak, looking her over.

“My guess, and it’s only a guess, is that she’s not just here, she’s there on the other side as well,” I said. “If she’s doubleplus ultrahypertensive, it’s probably so that she has a way to bomb the prime material plane, if it comes to that. It’s a dead man’s switch.”

I tried to think about what the virtue would look like. Infinite hypertension, the ability for your body to hold literally any amount of your own blood, plus the ability to continue producing blood even when you were definitely very full, a way for it to not kill you … I could see it as part of the progression from the hypertension virtue. Maybe I would add on a way to vent that pressure for effect, like little Tony Stark blood thrusters coming from the hands and feet, allowing flight. The other stuff that Pinno had mentioned, maybe I could see that too, blood homunculi and blood control, the kind of vast upper limits and capstones that someone very much like me might have thought up during a boring lecture in English class, all of it combined with the fucking broken ability to clone herself to make more blood.

“Alright,” said Amaryllis. She didn’t really have the room to pace within her portion of Grak’s ward, but she was giving it her best. “She doesn’t like me, and I don’t like her. I would park a clone here, but I would be too worried about her killing it, which would have fairly large costs associated with it, both in Miunun and Anglecynn. We don’t want to leave anyone we care about in the EZ, because that woman is a literal walking bomb that could wipe the whole place.”

“Not quite,” said Grak. “I don't think that it would be that large.”

“Huh,” I said. “Large enough to be a deterrent and a fuck you, not large enough to end the EZ entirely?”

“It’s hard to say,” replied Grak. “Very large explosions of blood were not my area of study.”

“The question is, if our objective is reform or redemption of Doris Finch, of all people, how do we accomplish that?” asked Amaryllis.

“Step one is probably to conceptualize her as not being the same as all the others,” I said. “They’re all forks with no merging. The Dorises as a collective are terrible, but it’s entirely possible that individual Dorises are … I’m not going to say blameless, but we might be conflating slaveholders with slaves and oppressors with the oppressed.”

“I don’t understand how you can empathize with her,” said Amaryllis. “She could have solved these problems at nearly any point just by choosing to be different.”

“She’s a fuck up,” I said. “Look, the way I see it, Doris Finch is that feeling of deciding that you’re going to fuck around playing clicker games at one in the morning instead of working on a paper you had due. It’s slacking off and then doing everything you have to do at the last minute because only when it’s literally hanging over your head do you have enough motivation. Doris Finch is that, multiplied by a thousand. You’ll note that she doesn’t seem to take any pleasure from all the clone killing. Of all the things that there could be in the EZ, a lot of them are notably absent. No bloodsports, no recreational torture, no direct sadism, —”

“You’re being generous,” said Amaryllis. “I don’t mind that you are, but you should realize that you are. You see some piece of yourself in her, and you’re extrapolating out. And if this has all been set up for you, then you’re probably right, but as a general approach to dealing with people, I don’t think that it’s going to be workable.”

“But in the here and now?” I asked.

“I would like it better if we had outside information,” said Amaryllis. “But I suppose that would make you too obviously right.” She sighed and looked over at the tiny house. “I suppose we have some time. I’m going to take ten minutes to check out, if that’s okay with everyone.” She closed her eyes and started concentrating.

“I’m not sure that I understand … any of this,” said Pinno.

“Your work here is probably done,” said Raven. “It’s not the crisis that you came prepared for, and it wasn’t a civilization-ending threat in the first place.”

“I should let you know you’re not forgiven,” said Pinno. He looked at me. “Neither of you. I don’t believe that anyone in the Library would risk action against you, given how powerful you are, but it’s possible, and if you were involved in any kind of scenario where you were clearly a component of the problem, that might provoke a different response.”

“You can transport your catatonic people to the Isle of Poran,” I said. “I can fix them there.”

“I don’t think that will change much, as far as mending fences,” said Pinno. “But it would be appreciated.” He nodded to us, and his eels fluttered.

“Pinno?” asked Raven. “Anything you think you heard from us … it would be better if the others didn’t know.”

“I will make no promises,” he said, before giving us a small bow and moving away, his boots splashing through the blood.

“Well then,” I said. I looked at Grak. “Objections?”

“None,” he said. “Some of what you said resonated with me.”

“Such as?” I asked.

“I spent quite some time dressing in a way I did not wish to dress, doing things I did not want to do, because I thought that I deserved to be unhappy,” said Grak. “I do not share your opinion of a future self as a clone though.”

“Because of, uh, thread-based thinking?” I asked.

Grak nodded. “My people have clones, Juniper. I am a clone of my father, his father a clone as well.”

“Ah,” I said, finally making that connection. “I suppose my instinct is to say that you’re not actually clones in the sense that I’m using it to refer to Doris, but surely you’ve encountered that argument before, and it’s really more about, uh, how we conceive of the world. I won’t even say that it’s an invalid way of thinking.”

“It is probably not the time for philosophy,” said Grak.

“No, probably not,” I said. “But I’ll sit down with you to hash it out sometime, when we’re not a razor’s edge away from death.”

“Are we?” asked Raven.

“I don’t know,” I said. “I would hope we’re on the downslope. In a few hours, Doris will probably come out of there feeling more refreshed than she has in decades, which will hopefully make her a little easier to talk to. I think she — well, the other version of her — was right about it being hard to make good decisions when you’ve got so many problems you have to deal with. There’s a mindset that comes from the kind of scarcity that the Dorises continually face, and while Amaryllis is right, some of it is artificial, I think that pervasive way of thinking among the Dorises became foundational.” I looked over at the tiny house. “I guess my worry is that without branding as a new kind of entity, people will treat her like they think she needs to be treated, which will just make things more difficult. If everyone is trying to stab you in the back because they think you’ll stab them in the back … yeah, that would make it hard for Blood God Doris to find a good future for herself.”

“You actually care about her,” said Raven, looking at me.

“You were telling me that I should care more,” I said. I glanced at Grak. “It’s probably easier for me to care about Doris when I think about people as being these, uh, patterns, I guess, rather than threads, or assemblies, or something else. Besides that, she hasn’t personally affronted me.”

There was some silence within Grak’s wards, as we waited.

“I’m back,” Amaryllis finally said. “Do you think there’s a way that we could make that process take a little less time? I’m missing out on conversations.”

“Maybe we’ll figure something out,” I said. “You can still hear though.”

“Yes,” said Amaryllis. “But I’m concentrating on something else, and trying to multitask is, ironically, something that causes it to fail.” She looked at the tiny house. “Nothing from the Caledwich library, by the way, just a feeling of wasted time, which I’d known when I got my mission. I really should check on the others as well, at least one of each cluster.”

“Do you think you would do so well if your selves were pitted against each other?” I asked. “If it was a matter of only one of you eating?”

“We’d go half rations,” said Amaryllis. “And if we couldn’t survive like that, we would take a random chance to decide who to kill, or better, a stark evaluation of who was more fit to survive.”

“I’m not sure I would,” I replied. “I might get greedy, or just upset. That’s why I can’t find it in myself to be upset with Doris.”

Amaryllis looked at me. “Alright,” she said. “I understand.”

“Do you think you have the insight to help her?” I asked. “Because I don’t think that I can do this without you.” I looked at Grak and Raven. “No offense.” Having to say ‘no offense’ a lot was a sign that you were saying the wrong thing.

“I would not be able to help her if my life depended on it,” said Grak.

“She’s better suited,” said Raven. “By skill, if not temperament.”

“Obviously I’ll help,” said Amaryllis. “On the off chance I need to, I’ll just pretend she’s a worse version of you.”

Quest Update: Diplomacy in Duplicate — There is a god among Dorises, one with more raw power than any other has had before, unable to be killed by all but the most extreme measures (or memetics, that would work too). You’ve decided that you want to help her. Hopefully this wasn’t just because you learned that pacifism comes with buffs. This quest replaces Murder in Duplicate and has no end condition.

There were some bumps and turns in talking through things with Blood God Doris, but we had so many creature comforts available to ply her with that it wasn’t all that hard to get her to relax. The fact that Sable was, at any given time, filled with furniture, toiletries, foodstuffs, music, and entertainment, meant that it was easy to convert a section of the warehouse into a temporary chill out zone, which we had prepared for Doris as soon as she was done in the tiny house. She had come out wearing the clothes she’d found there, including a ridiculously stupid shirt that said ‘Clone Zone’, which I’d had specially made for Amaryllis as a gift, and Doris must have thought was meant for her.

With the grime, blood, and sweat all wiped away, she looked surprisingly normal. She had a single visible tattoo, which I could only see by her collar, peeking up from her borrowed shirt, and her hair was grown out, hanging damp down her back. There was still a hardness to her, which I’d seen in all the others, but she was powerful, and comfortable in that power. When she left the tiny house, she dropped all pretense, and the few inches of blood parted for her like Moses parting the Red Sea.

“I’m not sure I see this working,” said Doris, stretching out.

“And what’s clouding your vision?” asked Amaryllis. “Surely not people trying to kill you. You’re invulnerable.”

“Trust doesn’t come easily,” replied Doris. “Not either way.”

“It’ll be easier if you lie about who you are,” I said. Doris had cleared away the blood around us, which I appreciated, and I was feeling comfortable. “There’s no reason that anyone has to know that you’re Doris. I mean, it’s obvious if they look at you, but you can make a blood homunculus out of someone else’s blood, and that should cloak it.”

“A … what?” she asked, leaning forward a bit.

“Were you not listening in on us?” I asked.

“Watching,” she said. “Listening is a bit beyond me.”

“Oh,” I said. I looked at Raven.

“The damage is likely done,” she said, folding her arms.

“What’s a blood homunculus?” asked Doris.

“From what we know, you take control of someone’s blood and make a, uh, blood creature,” I said. “My guess would be remotely piloted, and more importantly, not tied to your unique magic, meaning, capable of leaving the zone.”

“And who would I kill for their blood?” asked Doris.

“Eh,” I said. “Humans can survive missing something like a liter of blood, you could get donors. Or you could get a blood mage to donate a person’s worth of blood.” I glanced at Raven, then looked back at Doris. I wasn’t sure whether Ell had one hundred times the blood volume of a human, but even if they did, I wasn’t about to volunteer Raven.

“They’ll think I’m a monster,” said Doris.

“Sure,” I replied. “But that’s not much of a change. And this is just a matter of public relations. Ironically, that might be a place where Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle would have come in handy.”

“I don’t think it’s a terribly hard problem,” said Amaryllis. “It would depend on what form these blood creations actually took, but if it’s just a matter of people being repulsed by blood control, that’s something that can be dealt with. It’s a downstream problem. The current problem, in the here and now, is what you’re going to do.”

“And you want me to be god-queen,” said Doris, leaning back and looking at us. She had eaten quite a bit, and drank more, but seemed sated now.

“You’re going to exert power just by existing,” said Amaryllis. “You can’t be challenged. You can be a small god or a big one, but you’ll be a god either way. As for us, what we want is for you to be a good partner. We don’t really care what has to happen for that to work out.”

“You don’t care if I need a quarter million obols?” asked Doris, staring at Amaryllis. “You don’t care if I need servants imported into the EZ? You don’t care about breaking imperial law.”

“We can work on all of those,” said Amaryllis. “But the Empire only has laws so long as there are people enforcing those laws, and so long as the Empire doesn’t decide that those laws need to be changed.”

“And you can just do that?” asked Doris. “You can change what the Empire says and does?”

“We’re kind of a big deal,” I said. “But for it to work, you need to take care of yourself. Look, we know that you’ve got a lot of blood in you right now, and if you pop, it’s going to wipe out most of the EZ.”

Doris stared at me. “Why in the fuck are you just sitting there then?” she asked.

“Risking our lives, I guess,” I said. “From everything that people say about you, you’re a backstabber and a cheat, maybe pathologically so, but you wouldn’t kill someone just because they wanted to talk to you. You’ve got nothing to gain.”

“That’s batshit,” she said. “You have everything to lose. If I weren’t so scared about what powers you’re hiding, I could steal everything you have. I could enslave you, ransom you, anything I wanted.”

“We’d give you pretty much everything we have,” I said. “Why the fuck would you steal? You dumb or something?”

Doris smirked at me, eyes brightening. “No,” she said. “You know that’s one of my buttons, huh?”

“Look,” I said. “We didn’t come here expecting you. We thought some kind of monster was going to come out of that portal. But you’re here, and … presumably you have the other end locked up tight?”

“I control it, yes,” said Doris.

“And if you were to die here —” I started.

“Not for you to know,” she replied, all humor leaving her face.

“He’s just curious,” said Amaryllis. “If he sees a mystery, he wants to go poke at it.”

Doris relaxed slightly. “Sorry,” she said.

“You’re going to have to get used to people being curious,” I said. “They’re going to test you. That will be one hurdle.”

“But we don’t even know what you want,” said Amaryllis. “If you want to stay cooped up in a building, that’s different than being, effectively, the arm of the law that governs the whole EZ, depending on whether that’s actually within your power or not.”

“You said you would give me anything that I asked for,” said Doris, abruptly changing the subject. “All your entads?”

“Some of them wouldn’t work for you,” said Amaryllis. “Most, even.”

“But you would give them over?” asked Doris.

“No,” said Amaryllis. “We wouldn’t. And you know that you could take them from us. That’s the challenge that comes with power. And that urge, the urge to take what you can, when you can, even if you don’t have a need right now, that’s just something that’s been built into your brain by years of not having enough.” Amaryllis let out a sigh. “You see it in people who survive catastrophes and wars, a desire to keep a pantry well-stocked even if it means that the food will go bad before it’s eaten, sometimes squirreling things away in hidden places so that if someone comes in and steals everything, there will be something left. You’re going to want things. You’re going to ask for things that you don’t even want, just so that you can have them, just to be assured that you’re not going to lose it all.”

Doris leaned back, and looked from Amaryllis to me. “I want to be better,” she said. “Fuck, I’ve always wanted to be better.”

“Before, you had an excuse,” said Amaryllis. “It was a good excuse. I would have used it, in your position. You were beset on all sides. You didn’t like making the copies, but it was necessary, and you would think, sometimes, that this time it would be different, that you would cooperate, or that you would split the spoils. And then it would come to that moment, and maybe it would happen, or maybe it wouldn’t, but you would think about killing her, or them, and taking it all for yourself, and you would think that, knowing that they were thinking it too. It’s hard to cooperate, when you know the other party is thinking that.”

Doris was staring at Amaryllis. She nodded once.

“You don’t have that excuse anymore,” said Amaryllis. “People will be coming for you, but you can beat them to a pulp. You have the luxury of acting in retribution, instead of in expectation. That luxury isn’t going to be easy. The instincts that you have, honed by decades of coming out the winner by being more ruthless, are going to fade slowly, and never completely. But if you go along with what your first instinct is, then you’re going to be worse off.”

“And what if I can’t help myself?” asked Doris. “What if they’re right about me?”

“The fact that we’re here, alive, says that they’re not,” replied Amaryllis. “You were waiting with the bulk of your power on the other side of that portal, resisting the urge to go on a rampage, to take everything you could while you had the power, because you could see that it had an end, and you wanted to make sure that it was the good end. That’s more proof that you can handle this.”

“Okay,” said Doris.

“It would be better with advisors,” said Amaryllis. “Better with a group of people that you can talk to, who can help you know what you want and how to make that a reality. There are going to be tests along the way, no matter what you do, and those tests will be easier to pass with support. I’m not nominating us, we have our own things going on, but I can suggest good people to you.”

“You’re good,” said Doris. Staring at Amaryllis. “Good at what you do. And you like doing it.”

“I’m unfortunately unavailable,” said Amaryllis. “But if you want or need my ear, we can leave you an entad to keep in touch with us. If circumstances allow our advice and counsel to be slow in coming, then letters will work too. One of the first things that I’ll get started on is reconnecting mail service and having regular bulk teleport into the EZ.” She let out a breath, then looked at me. “Sorry, but we’re on a bit of a time crunch here. We promised a dragon that we would kill Blue-in-the-Bottle, but we don’t know where he is, so we’re going to have to use the predictive power of the Dorises. If it’s okay with you, we’re going to go tell the Blues that this facility and what’s inside it is unlikely to be a problem for them in the near future.”

“You’re leaving me here, then?” asked Doris, looking Amaryllis over. There was a very faint note of desperation in her voice, and if I could hear it, then I was sure that it was a shrill alarm to Amaryllis.

“If you don’t want to be alone, I would understand that,” said Amaryllis. “We can stay with you for up to a day. I don’t imagine that you want to give up this facility, because it has the portal, but we can help you set up on the roof, if there’s roof access, or somewhere else that will be a little more inviting and accommodating. And after that’s done, when the time is up, I’ll be able to call in an entad clone of my own, who will be able to talk with you for at least as long as it takes to get permanent staffing.” Amaryllis had held off for as long as she could, but eventually she dropped the possibility of a clone. I hadn’t heard it in her voice, but she must have been watching Doris, hoping that there was some other resolution.

“Okay,” said Doris. “I would appreciate that, thank you.”

We spent the rest of the day helping her out, which mostly involved pulling stuff from Sable and having Grak set up wards around the portal so that it would be safe and protected. It turned out that there was roof access, and once we were up there, we spent some time doing incredibly fast landscaping, adding in soil and grass seed that were taken from Sable. It would take a fair amount of time for it to grow in, but if this facility was going to be a home for Doris, then it was better she have a place with some real, natural greenery.

“It will look great in another week or two,” said Amaryllis, after about an hour of work. “But these things take time.” I hadn’t even realized that we were working on a metaphor.

“They’re watching us,” said Doris, looking out at Dorisopolis around us. We were high up, but not so high as some of the other magestone buildings.

“Let them watch,” said Amaryllis. “Let them understand that someone is growing things here.”

I slept in the tiny house, which took a real leap of faith, but we had no one to offload sleep onto, and I wasn’t about to go so long while running on fumes. I was worried that I would wake up to the sound of calamity, but there was nothing but Amaryllis, running her fingers through my hair and telling me that it was time to rise.

It was the leaving that I was most worried about, but that was fine too, in part because Amaryllis had her clone there, and we weren’t actually leaving Blood God Doris alone. I still felt weird about leaving Amaryllis there, even though I knew she wasn’t the ‘real’ Amaryllis, even though I knew that they would merge experiences. I gave her a hug and told her to stay safe, and she seemed like she appreciated it, because I knew that this was something she really didn’t want to do.

“It’s going to be fine,” said Amaryllis once we were well outside the facility. “I wouldn’t have left her there if it wasn’t.”

“You really think it’s going to work out?” I asked.

“She’s just reassuring you,” said Grak.

“It’s going to take a long time, and be very uneven, and it might cost me my life, but yes, I think that it’s going to work out,” said Amaryllis. “Having a clone here is going to set me a bit on edge until I can get a replacement for her, and I’ll breathe easier once we’re out of the EZ, but yes, I think this is workable, if maybe not a panacea for the EZ as a whole.”

And for all the tension that we were feeling, our meeting with the Blues, their central leadership this time, went about as well as it could have been expected to go, with some token explanation about what had gone on in their facility, and terms for delivery of supplies more or less what we’d planned on when we’d come into the zone. I wanted to know the method they were using, especially because I was hoping that I could copy it for myself somehow, but everyone else was against spending more time in the EZ than we needed, especially since we could just pay the Dorises to do the work for us.

Roughly forty-eight hours after we’d entered the zone, we were leaving again, all resting easier once we were aboard the ship, but right up until the last moment that we could see the DFEZ, I was worried we would see a colossal detonation of blood. It never came though, and we were off, a small pile of coordinates with us, and tracking information for Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle, who I was sure was going to get much less pleasant of a resolution.

An Elevated Monologue

I had no idea what, if anything, there was to do about Solace and the locus. I had no idea how the locus had seen their relationship before the unbottling, before the resurrection, or at any other point. And maybe the metaphor that I was seeing was just a thin slice of time, the locus picturing Solace as being mean by wanting to go away. Their relationship wasn’t one of child and parent, but there had definitely been times when I thought my parents were fascists. Surely the locus was the one who could control whether or not they went? I talked about what I’d seen with the rest of the party (Raven after we’d had a day away from each other), even going so far as to send a letter to Valencia, but the feedback I got in return wasn’t all that helpful: we needed more data, and would monitor the situation, but it didn’t necessarily mean anything, and even if it did mean something, it wasn’t like we could actually intervene, except by talking to Solace.

There were more important things on our plate.

Our communication with the Dorises was via entad: one that we’d taken from Larkspur, ages and ages ago, which the Dorises still had the other end of. Thankfully, they had held onto it, and their reckless duplication of it hadn’t substantially harmed our ability to use it for tracking communication. As far as long-distance communication entads went, it was pretty fucking neat: it allowed two users to think map data at each other, while also enhancing their power to think in terms of maps. It took the form factor of a large pocket watch, almost too big for a pocket, which showed a map that could be pinched and pulled through smartphone-like touch controls. In this way, two people on opposite sides of the hex could communicate by looking at the same place and annotating it with whatever they wanted to say. If you had something to add to that map, you could just think at it, and fill in some details, including a bunch of different overlays. (What it was for wasn’t always a question that you could answer with entads, but my guess was that it was largely meant for reporting back on exploration missions, rather than what we were using it for.)

Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle was deep underground, which was awkwardly marked on the entad map by elevation arrows attached to topological lines and a heat map. The entad was great, but it worked best in two dimensions, and for Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle, that simply wasn’t the case.

“I’m really thinking about the social approach,” I told the group, on our last day on the ship. Things with Raven were rocky, but the talk about soul-editing had been put on hold for the time being, and the understanding that there was no real urgency to any of it was helping, at least in my opinion.

“You know we effectively killed him, right?” asked Amaryllis. There were three of her at the meeting, which was a bit unusual, since normally she kept her selves separated. The primary version of her was the one doing most of the talking, and identifiable by the entads she wore, Sable chief among them. We called her Primary; the other two were Seconmary and Tertimary. They wore color coded clothes, with reds for the original, pink for second, and white for third, mostly so that people could keep them straight, though the syncs were common, and the differences between them mostly in the moment-to-moment.

“We didn’t kill him,” I said. “He’s still definitely alive, or at least undead.”

“What’s the social plan then?” asked Raven. “How are we going to talk him into being good, or on the path to good?”

“Uh,” I said. “Okay, so, let’s take as a given that Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle is redeemable, that there’s some solution which results in him voluntarily, or I guess, maybe through force, deciding that he’s going to stop being a douchebag, release all his zombies, and then stick to the less problematic version of necromancy, which would still make him a multimillionaire. So far as I see it, the problem with him isn’t that he’s prioritizing money over pain and suffering, or that he’s a horrible despot, it’s that idiotic proclamation that he made once he’d been found out. Like, let’s say that Elisha Blue’s whole life has been set up as an object lesson for me. What does that lesson entail?”

“This seems like a bad way to approach the problem,” said Grak, frowning.

“Well, sure,” I said. “And yes, it would have been better to have done this before our first time into the EZ. I’m just saying — look, he wrote this whole thing about how the world was shit, how they’d keep buying from him anyway, how no one actually cared. That wasn’t the right play from a PR standpoint, it was obviously not the play, but it was what he did anyway.”

“Are you back on the narrative train?” asked Primary.

“No,” I replied. “Just acknowledging that certain things are possible for me that might not otherwise be possible for anyone else, and not because of the game layer. I’m not even approaching it like I’m trying to figure out what the Dungeon Master might want from me, I’m trying to see Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle as maybe being just a guy, albeit one who ended up in extreme circumstances. I’m trying to see if that framing holds, and if it works.”

“You think that most people would do as he did?” asked Grak.

“I think that his failures are human failures,” I said. “They’re amplified, obviously, and extreme, I’m just thinking about that letter he wrote, and what was going through his head. If he really, honestly believed that it didn’t matter whether he was engaging in what was effectively torture on a mass scale, he should have kept his mouth shut, made some denials, or offered a reframing. Instead, he blamed everyone else, and he did it publicly. It was important for him to shift the wrongdoing onto others, to deny that this was anything other than how the world had been set up to betray him.”

“So we tell him that it was his fault?” asked Grak, raising an eyebrow.

“I don’t know,” I said. I drummed my fingers on the table. “I’m just trying to get inside his head. Even if there’s no social option, it might still be helpful in some other way. One of the things that doesn’t show up in his biographies, probably because they didn’t know, is when he found out that there were still people living inside the bodies that he was using. It seems like a vital question to me, and the assumption is that he knew from the start, but there’s no evidence backing that up. It’s all implication.”

“Would that really be better?” asked Raven. “If we entertain the notion that he didn’t know until that initial report was published … Juniper, he’s keeping half a million people locked into their unmoving bodies just as a safeguard against enemy action, ready to doom them to the hells.”

“Yeah,” I said. “I know, he’s a monster. But I do think it makes a difference. Like, if he knew right from the start and decided that he was going to go ahead with it, and damn the pain he was inflicting so long as he could make products on the cheap, then yes, I would say that there’s a good chance that he can’t be talked out of being who he is. On the other hand, imagine that he invented this process, and didn’t realize why it was excluded, but tried to make the best of being the only practitioner of his magic, building up his empire, not realizing that there were people inside those bodies after all. Imagine that he doesn’t find out until the day that the paper runs the story, then has to do some quick experimental work himself to figure out whether it’s actually true, and it slowly dawns on him that yes, actually, he’s spent decades working these bodies to the bone, and there are people trapped inside.”

“You’re telling yourself a story,” said Grak.

“I am,” I admitted. “I really, fully admit that. But if there’s any chance that we can take the non-violent path here, I’m trying to think about what that path might look like. We don’t need to consider those worlds where he’s irredeemable, we need to consider the ones where there’s some set of words that will turn him. If anyone has any guesses about what those worlds might look like, and how we might prepare for them, I’m all ears.”

“It’s good to see you newly energized,” said Primary. Her voice was very calm, and the clones were giving me sympathetic looks. “But in this hypothetical, Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle’s reaction to being told that he had spent decades doing something he thought was good but was actually unconscionable was to loudly declare that no, it was justified. Then, when that didn’t help him, he decided that he would further commit to his course of action, changing absolutely nothing except to double down on the torture. I don’t think we can redeem him, in this or any other world.”

“I’m trying to think of how to put this,” I said. “Let’s say that you find out you did something bad. You see yourself as a good person, so obviously there’s an internal struggle. Sometimes, in some people, that struggle doesn’t end up with you copping to having done something bad. Sometimes, to preserve your self-identity, you start to make up excuses. You say, ‘oh, but I’m a good person, so obviously the things that look bad are actually good’. You cling to flimsy evidence in favor of you, and try to poke holes in solid evidence against you. And then you commit to those ways of thinking, because they’re a defense mechanism. They’re what lets you keep looking at yourself in the mirror without wanting to blow your head off with a shotgun.”

I was getting some looks.

“I did things that were bad on Earth,” I said. “And I’ve done worse on Aerb. There have been times that I’ve succumbed to doubling down on bad behavior.”

“Trying to see yourself in monsters is unhealthy,” said Grak.

“Well — I guess I can’t argue with that,” I said. “Or I can, but I won’t.”

“And to be clear, you’re not arguing that Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle is good?” asked Raven.

I leaned back for a moment, trying to think about how to phrase it. “Amaryllis? Can you help translate?”

“If I understand right, you think that there is, if not redemption for Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle, then at least some understanding we might arrive at before killing him,” said Primary. “Do you regret killing Onion?”

“No,” I said. “But I do wish I’d understood him better, and I think we could have avoided a fair bit of pain and suffering if I had. Or … even if not that, then at least it would have been a chance to take something from it, to learn and to grow. If all we ever do is walk into places where there are some people who need to die, and then we kill them …” I trailed off.

“Then we’ll power up enough that we might be able to squeak past Fel Seed,” said Primary. “We’ll meet Uther, then somehow elevate you to godhood. That’s our long-term goal. There doesn’t need to be any lesson taken from any of it, unless you think that’s the path to godhood, which … is certainly a theory.”

“Not everyone can be redeemed, Juniper,” said Raven. “Not everyone can even be understood. Some of the people Uther killed, we could barely fathom the reasons for their evil. There are truly alien monsters out there, beings whose methods of thought you can barely make sense of.”

“Elisha Blue is human,” I said. “We should be ready to kill him, but I’d at least like some insight into how he got to where he is now, and if it’s possible for us to put in some social effort, I think we should do it.”

“I don’t have any argument with that,” said Primary. She turned to look at Grak. “So long as Grak can protect us?”

“Void is difficult to deal with,” he said. He was right; it was kind of funny that something that had been a threat right from the beginning was still a threat this far in. “Everything else, I will do my best.”

We talked some more after that, particularly about what we thought Blue-in-the-Bottle’s contingencies looked like, and what specific form his immortality took. We didn’t know for certain whether the body we’d killed was a puppet, a wind-up doll, or something else. My contention that he had a phylactery somewhere had been met with skepticism from the others when I’d brought it up following our first encounter, which was sensible, since the only reason you would expect it was because he had many of the hallmarks of lichdom. Liches weren’t even a thing that existed on Aerb anymore, not since Uther’s time, and they’d been a totally different phenomenon, per Raven (almost a year of Uther’s time, spent on a bad lichen pun).

The Underline landed just outside of Necrolaborem, this time moving faster, as we were presumably unwelcome. The ship took off as soon as we were on the ground, back to safer environs, waiting for us to give a signal so that we could be picked up. The plan, such as it was, started with us finding the entrance to the underground complex that the Captain was presumed to have, based on his probable location. The worst case scenario was that there was no connection to the surface at all, and we would have to tunnel down to him, but we were prepared for that.

I had been busy making inktads on the ship. Like rune magic, ink magic was best if you had quite a bit of time to prepare, since that would let you make the strongest results that were most applicable to your situation. Most of the stuff I’d made for the Doris EZ had been completely useless, since I had thought that we would need crowd control and area of effect magic, but since we hadn’t actually had to go up against a clone tide (except a few brief moments in the market, which Grak had solved), they’d gone unused. There had been a really neat gun that got better the more people were around, and I hadn’t used it a single time. Heck, I had gotten through the whole EZ without killing a single Doris.

For Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle, I was most worried about undead warriors, the kind of implacable killing machines that would be hard to take down no matter what magic I used, so I had thought long and hard about it, and then gone whole hog on burning out nervous systems. That was frighteningly high i-level, meaning that I couldn’t quite manage it without some serious limitations, which I put in place as requiring charge up time, discharge time, close contact, and precise positioning. The end result was three pieces of kit: one was a glove that could do nerve damage to whatever it touched or kill outright by scorching through the nerve system if I could have a hand on someone’s neck or skull for long enough; another was a dagger that could pulse outward from wherever it was planted, targeting the nerves specifically; the third was a net, which, instead of burning through nerves, would draw them out instead, literally pulling them from the body that was trapped beneath the fibers. That third one was weaker, too derivative of the first, but I was hoping that it would be good for a single use.

I hadn’t been able to solve the issue of him being underground with inktads though. If we had to tunnel down four hundred feet to where the Dorises were saying Blue was, that would almost certainly mean calling in Bethel, and no one wanted to do that, least of all me. We had not, however, removed that option from the table.

The first guards we saw raised their weapons, then dropped them almost immediately at a signal from one of the zombies in their midst. The weapons were set on the ground, and then the group walked toward us with hands raised.

“Ah, shit,” I said. I didn’t like this.

“Mr. and Mrs. Smith,” said one of the guards with a nod. “The Captain would like you to come with us.”

“We decline,” said Amaryllis. “If there’s talking to be done, we can do it here, out in the open.”

The guards looked at each other. They both looked frightfully young. The zombie between them was staring straight at us. I was pretty sure that the Captain could see through the zombies, and maybe even talk through them. It had, after all, given them a signal.

“Wait here,” said one of the guards. He trotted away, leaving us standing awkwardly in a field.

I was extending vibration magic as far as it would go, draining my internal stores of power to do so. I was worried about snipers, or if not snipers, then bombs, or if not bombs, then … something else. Obviously bombs and snipers could both be stopped by either still magic or Grak’s wards, but I wasn’t about to pretend that just because I was grossly overpowered meant that I was immune to everything: I had been disabused of that notion very thoroughly by this point.

We waited for about ten tense minutes, and eventually, the manservant, Terrence, came to meet us.

“My apologies,” he said with a bow. “The Captain had wished to speak with you in person, and it hadn’t been anticipated that you would accept the offer but decline to move.”

“Our primary concern is taking out his hostages,” I said. “Any help that you can give us with that, with or without his permission, is appreciated. We have his location now. It’s going to be over within twenty-four hours.” We debated what to tell the civilians, and decided on the truth. It would be better for the Captain to be hit with a blitz, but we didn’t have the capabilities to blitz straight into the ground.

“I can’t tell you, because I don’t know,” said Terrence, keeping his voice stiff.

“That’s okay,” I said. “Can you tell me where the entrance to the underground portion of the city is?” His eyes flicked to the side, looking to the other members of the party. “There are many ways for this to go, Terrence. So far as I’m concerned, you’re an innocent in all of this. I don’t want to rip your memories out of your skull or break your fingers, but I will.” This was an exaggeration. (There was a chance that I would need to soulfuck him though.)

He trembled. “There’s an elevator shaft in the manor,” he said. “But that’s where I was instructed to bring you in the first place.”

“Lead the way,” I said.

He moved awkwardly as he took us to the manor. It was a trap, it had to be, and while I could blame Blue-in-the-Bottle for a lot of stuff, I wouldn’t have blamed him for trying to lure us into a trap to kill us. Him being underground was really, really unfortunate, because even if we were carving our own path through the rock to him, he had plenty of chances to bunker. It was a bad situation, to be sure. I was iffy on going down the elevator with Terrence, but it would depend on what we saw, and what I thought our chances looked like.

Everything was pretty much exactly as we’d left it. There were all the same guards, which I was watching closely, and the same zombies, going about their tasks. Some of them were, now that I had a chance for a closer look, obviously scripted, just as Grak had said. Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle was a showman, and he’d set things up so that visitors could see the labor on display. It was sickening to think that there was still a person inside them, looking out through dead eyes as their body raked the same small group of leaves on repeat just in case someone walked by.

I was trying to keep some sympathy and understanding for Elisha Blue, but it was difficult, when faced with this madness. Maybe it really was that he just didn’t give a shit about the pain and suffering of others, but there was a chance, a chance that he had this alternate reality constructed for himself, one where this suffering was by consent, or the inevitable product of an unjust world. There was a chance that he could be disabused of what notions he had.

He knows more than he says, Amaryllis signed to me in Gimb. She had been watching Terrence.

“There’s a good end here,” said Amaryllis aloud. “That good end is that the Captain agrees to stand down and release his half million hostages. He agrees to practice a lesser form of necromancy, one which doesn’t require the suffering of the souls. If there’s anything, anything at all, that you can tell us, now would be the time.”

“He doesn’t tell anyone very much,” said Terrence as he led us into the manor itself. The museum was still there, with exhibits still running.

“Tell us about the facility down below,” I said.

“I don’t know anything,” said Terrence. There was a hitch in his voice. I felt bad about saying that I would rip out his memories and break his fingers. I would feel considerably less bad if my saying that in some small way helped to alleviate the pain and suffering of half a million people.

“Was it made by entad?” asked Grak. “There is no visible fill.” He was right; if you were building underground, you needed to put all that stuff you excavated somewhere, and there was no corresponding hill or mountain. It was the kind of thing that the Empire of Common Cause occasionally looked for, thinking that it might give a hint about where he was hiding the hostages.

“I don’t know, ” said Terrence. “It’s like a normal building down there. Please don’t hurt me.”

“What are the walls like?” asked Grak. This was the point in any D&D game where someone’s minor bonus to a little-used skill finally came in handy.

“They’re smooth stone,” said Terrence. “The pipes and wires are on the outside. He has an office that’s nicer, that’s the only place I’ve gone.”

“Are there other entrances?” I asked.

“I don’t know,” Terrence replied. His lip was trembling. “Please, I don’t know.”

I had unfortunately miscalibrated my threats, it seemed. Probably if I had kept Intimidation as a skill, I would have figured out some way to give him the right understanding of what I considered to be at stake, and to motivate him to be forthright with us.

“It’s okay,” said Amaryllis. Her voice was smooth and gentle. “We just want to know what we’re walking into.”

That gentle voice was undercut by both her armor, which had a plethora of spikes coming from it, and from the sword she was carrying in her hand. She had more entad support than any of us, given how much of the Anglecynn stash was usable by her and her alone. There were no less than sixteen different swords that could be pulled from Sable at a moment’s notice, three pistols, two rifles, and other, more exotic weapons. I was scared of her, and based on our sparring, there was no way that she could beat me in a straight fight.

“There will be guards,” said Terrence. “He doesn’t use people down there, because people have needs.”

“Is it a facility for making zombies?” I asked.

“I don’t know!” said Terrence, voice raising. “I don’t know what’s down there.”

“It’s alright,” said Amaryllis. “We don’t expect you to know, but it’s important that we have every advantage that we can get going into this.”

“Well I don’t know,” replied Terrence, his voice soft.

I glanced at Amaryllis, and she gave me a nod. She was no Valencia, but she thought that he was telling the truth. I felt bad for having a kid mixed up in all this (‘kid’ was how I thought of him, though he wasn’t more than a year or two younger than I was). I resolved to make sure he was taken care of once this was all over. Clearly he knew things, and we would need to ask him questions, but we weren’t going to deal with Blue-in-the-Bottle and then leave this place without any leadership, even if we did have to kill the Captain.

Terrence led us through the manor, and I was feeling particularly paranoid. There were lots of zombies around, standing guard, watching us. I could see through their eyes, which were tracking our movements. Void weapons were the only thing that I was worried about, but I was worried about them. Amaryllis had inch-thick sheets of steel inside Sable that she could pop out, I could set my elemental armor to thick iron plate, and I had not only the ability to ‘parry’ void, but could track eye movement and attention to see where a shot was likely to go, the better to dodge. I was still nervous. If the Captain had rigged up a void bomb, or a set of them, somewhere inside the manor … well, that would be a problem.

I had expected the elevator to be small, barely capable of fitting us all in it, but no, it was a freight elevator, big enough to fit a car. I didn’t like the level of engineering that had obviously gone into it: it spoke to the importance of this place, and the amount of resources that had been poured into Blue-in-the-Bottle’s enterprise. I wondered when elevators had been invented on Aerb, and when this one had been installed, and who the Captain had gotten to do it. Elevators needed maintenance. Did Blue just train up his own elevator repair technicians? I was thinking about all those questions because I was nervous. A freight elevator like this had Implications for what we would find down there. It was the kind of thing you would use for transporting heavy equipment or lots and lots of bodies.

I reached out with water magic. I’d leveled it quite a bit since those initial lessons with my fake mom, but trying to use it to track people was still difficult work. Water magic worked on scale, with huge clouds and bodies of water, and people were, fundamentally, not what it was for. It was like trying to count grains of sand from ten feet away. You could guess, if they were all in a clump, but not be exact, because you couldn’t see the individual grains. Here, it was complicated somewhat by the water table, which the underground complex was well below. Still, I could easily sense where the water wasn’t, and make some kind of guess about numbers down there.

“Hundreds of thousands below us,” I said. “Maybe more.” It was a whole fucking city. I couldn’t count them, but I could feel them moving around, not the rows upon rows of stacked zombies that I had expected. I looked at Terrence. “Do people come in and out of this place often?”

“Almost never,” said Terrence. “Zombies come out, sometimes.”

“Wait,” I said. “They don’t go in?”

“I don’t know,” replied Terrence. “Processing is done somewhere else.”

“And he’s inviting us down to see what he has going on?” I asked.

“I don’t know,” said Terrence again.

“I’ve got a bad feeling about this,” I said. It was like going down into the Temple at Li’o, but worse, because the pretense of normalcy and civility was so paper thin, and the forces arrayed at the bottom of that elevator shaft were almost certainly incredibly dangerous. We had Grak, which meant protection, but I was worried, and not getting less worried as time went on.

“Go or no go?” asked Amaryllis.

There were two main options, if the answer was ‘no go’. The first was facing down Perisev directly and telling her that it couldn’t be done, and either enduring her wrath or trying to kill her. The second option was calling in Bethel, though the strongly worded advice from Valencia was that outcomes would be much, much better if we didn’t approach Bethel with any immediate requests, and not until we could stomach her being, if not a part of the group, then a part of our lives.

“Go,” I said.

“Please don’t take me with you,” said Terrence.

“Nah, you’re fine, you can leave,” I said.

Almost as soon as the words were out of my mouth, he had taken off in an awkward run, leaving us alone in the manor, save for all the zombies around us. I could see through their eyes: they were watching us, and that meant a strong chance that the Captain was watching us too.

Raven was the first into the freight elevator, looking calm and serene in her banded armor, not even seeming to mind that she was momentarily outside of Grak’s mobile wards. He followed her though, and I followed after, careful to stay as protected as possible. I had a single point in LUK, and I was hoping that the apprehension that I was feeling wasn’t from that, because if it was, that would be a good sign to run.

If the elevator had been enclosed, I probably would have opted for us to bail, but it was open, with metal grates showing the walls beyond it, and the top exposing the machinery that made the elevator go up and down. The floor was thick metal, which also made me feel better, because that would be an impediment to a void attack from below. Maybe it was just that the market attack by the Dorises had rattled me more than I’d realized at the time. Getting shot in the head with a void rifle would kill me: it had happened before.

The bit I was most suspicious about was a thin wire running up the side of the elevator car to the top of it, where there was a little box, and with a signal to Grak, before we’d even touched the controls, I stepped up into the air using still magic and opened the box up, looking inside to confirm that there wasn’t an errant void crystal there. It was just a speaker though, one which sprang to life as soon as we began moving down. I had my sword drawn, ready to cut the line at the first unfamiliar word, ready to mute it. There were risks to letting him talk, but it was four hundred feet down and slow going.

“The Finches told me you were coming,” said Elisha Blue’s voice through the tinny speaker.

“Of fucking course they did,” said Amaryllis with a sigh.

“There’s no microphone,” I said. “At least, not that I could see.”

“I know more about the four of you than I did a week and a half ago,” said the Captain over the speaker. “I pulled what strings are still available to me. If I were still under the veil of ignorance, I might boast that many have tried to kill me and all have failed, but I know you now for Uther’s heir. By the balance of probability, it seems likely that this will be my final death. Uther was not in the habit of putting people to the sword and then finding, at the last moment, that they were talking sense.”

“He was, actually,” said Raven. “Maybe twenty percent of the time.” She was in her fighting stance, weapon drawn, but had a slightly bored look. I wondered how many villains’ monologues she’d sat through.

“I must still do my best to convince you, of course,” Blue continued, “But failing that, someone will have to look after my enterprises here, either to dismantle them, as regrettable as that is, or to keep them going, if you so choose. I am, of course, in the face of my demise, bending the knee, fully and completely, surrendering without conditions or expectations. I do not anticipate that will sway you.”

“It does, actually,” I said, frowning. “Man, really wish we had a microphone —”

“To start with, I did not know of the condition of the zombies until many years in,” said Blue. “I knew that they retained something of their soul, of course, but in creating them I was working with something else, something that was not the soul, which was instead pathways of being, expressions of something higher, a missing element, which the essentialists of the time had been seeking, shortly before their complete collapse at Lankwon. I had twenty factories fully staffed with zombies when the first whiff of something wrong came. There was an entad which tracked people, one that I had bought at great expense to have some surveillance of the zone, yet it showed each and every zombie as a person, where the earlier necromantic creations were invisible. Some testing to get to the bottom of this showed that this was consistent across many such entads, and some experts on entads I had brought in contended that this was due to some conceptual underpinnings of entadic function. The zombies were ‘people’ in some respect, but neither ‘alive’ nor ‘dead’. I had coined the term ‘undead’ early in my career, but it would prove prophetic.”

“Uther coined it,” said Raven.

“Like hell he did,” I said.

“You must understand that it did not occur to me that they were experiencing anything, if it can even be said that they are,” said Blue. “It has long been a contention of my detractors that zombies experience life as we do, with the sole exception of being unable to control their own bodies, but this is far from a settled matter. We know of their suffering from two sources, the first being entads, which function according to their own dubious logic and sometimes give false readings. The second source is from the hells, in those rare cases where a zombie is destroyed prior to its soul being bottled, something that I have never willingly allowed to happen, but which could not be prevented in the once-common raids on my zone. The damned have memories of their time as zombies, and are afflicted by the conditions they have endured. For a long while, I denied that evidence as well, coming as it did from the hells, but I deny it no more.”

I was frowning at this monologue. Maybe this was a last ditch effort at avoiding being put to the sword by me, but I wasn’t sure that I bought his unconditional surrender. Villains, even redeemable villains, didn’t just do that. It made sense to do, if you learned that I had punched out a dragon (this wasn’t true, but everyone was repeating it). But if Blue were sensible, I didn’t think that it would have gotten to this.

“It took me time to come to terms with what was happening,” Blue continued. The elevator was going really fucking slow, and I figured that was at least partly to give him time to say what he wanted to say. I wondered whether he had timed his speech and adjusted some gear ratios so that we would arrive at the bottom right when he finished. “And yet once I looked at the zombies with a clear head, I was surprised to find that it all still made sense. The trade-off was taboo, but it was no different than other trades we make with much less in the way of misty-eyed sentimentality. We accept small tortures in our lives, often in exchange for payments. People live with aching bones from their work, hands rubbed raw by labor, miner’s lung, grocer’s itch, scrivener’s palsy, deformities inflicted by the physical strains of their occupation. Of late, retirement has become commonplace for the elderly, and the very language of that practice belies how people think of it. They talk about how that cessation of work is a reward for everything that they’ve put in. People do not want to work, but it is of necessity that they do.”

“We are only a third of the way down,” said Grak, glaring at the speaker.

“What of consent, you might ask?” Blue continued. “I have not been so divorced from the outside world that I have not read the words of my detractors. They will claim that a man cannot consent to being stripped of his very will, that there is no possible way to justify what is, to some eyes, equivalent to slavery. Yet this is a simple question, that of whether we are capable of committing to some future from which we cannot escape. The answer, trivially, is that we are. A man is allowed to ruin himself in the gambling parlors. A woman is allowed to bear a child. And imperial doctrine, last I heard, was that there existed a legal right to suicide, and beyond that, a right to an eternity in the hells.”

“Technically,” Amaryllis began, and I was sure that she was about to quibble on that point, but we didn’t have a microphone, and Blue continued on.

“I have signed agreements from every single one of my zombies,” said Blue. “I’ve had them in place since the moment I was first certain that some existence persisted within those bodies. I have done my best to accommodate the moralists, to make costly concessions to their philosophical demands. People understand what it means to be trapped within their body, to feel minor pains, and they agree, as should be their right. I have done everything in my power, everything, to make sure that this process is done in a safe and ethical way, to prepare those people for what they will have to endure, and to minimize what they are still able to feel. The man-hours that have been spent on all this, the sheer cost of it, would make even the richest people in the world blush.”

“Doubt it,” I said. I was seeing his game now: he wasn’t going to void bomb us, he was going to talk us to death. Whining about how much it cost him wasn’t particularly endearing though.

“It is a disagreement in philosophy that underlines this whole affair, that has been the bane of my existence,” said Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle. “But more than that, it is simply my nature as someone who the powers that be feel that they can ignore. Do you believe that my harshest critics were crusaders? No, of course they were not. Instead, it was vested interests in a variety of places, laborers whose jobs were being threatened, politicians who felt that they could score a hit against someone far away, newspaper writers who saw a story they could tell, one with a villain at its heart. When the embargos were placed, it was other captains of industry who benefited, their competition having been dealt a blow that went far outside the bounds of the free market. And these boycotts which metastasized into embargos weren’t done with any critical thinking at all, because that replacement of labor had to come from somewhere, and it came, in the end, from underdeveloped countries, those places where there were fewest protections in place for workers, where the pay would be as low as possible. I will not, cannot, say that it is better to be a zombie than to live and work in poverty, but that is because I don’t believe such things can be compared. My detractors will make bald-faced claims otherwise, declaring it obvious that my way is the worst of the two. It allows them to feel a smug superiority when they purchase goods made by paying only the slightest sliver of an obol to a diligent and suffering worker.”

“Has the elevator slowed?” asked Amaryllis. It was rock wall all around us, which the metal struts were bracing against. I was pretty sure that the question was rhetorical: we were all feeling like this was taking a lot longer than it should have.

“There has, through human history, been a need for villains,” said Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle. “We have trouble with the complex, the nuanced, the grey. I have been smeared, backward and forward, not just because of what I have done, but even for those things which I am entirely innocent of. I doubt that I will convince you only through claims of my innocence, but for the record, I must address what has been said. It is true that I have hostages, zombies which have been set up and exist for no other purpose than to be damned in the event of my death. It is not true in the slightest that they are in perpetual agony; they have been pithed, their brains partially destroyed, their souls held in perpetual stasis. No one believes me, naturally, and I have so far gotten no one to come in for confirmation.” I frowned at that. His hostages were a major point against Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle, and it didn’t terribly surprise me that he had an answer for it.

“It is also true that people have been damned in the course of my experiments,” Blue continued on, “But I should stress that it is always against my will, and in spite of every effort I had made in order to ensure that it would not happen. They make me out to be a monster, of course, saying that I engaged in cruel and malicious experimentation, which supposedly happened either as I was doing my initial research into the creation of the zombies, to ensure my own immortality, or in the wake of the allegations against me. It’s a difficult thing to prove, of course, that I didn’t do any untoward research, especially as I have done all manner of other research. Do you know who people depend upon in order to make these allegations? Devils. An infernoscope pointed at a devil will show you only what that devil wants you to see.”

“How long can he keep talking?” asked Amaryllis. “This is a test by the Dungeon Master. A test of our patience.” She kept speaking even as Blue continued on. “Can we acknowledge that half of what he’s saying is utter horseshit? He’s trying to muddy the waters and give us some excuse not to kill him, but he would have been better off just keeping his fucking mouth shut.”

“We do not have much of this left,” said Grak, also speaking over Blue.

“I still think that he’s, if not redeemable, then someone we don’t have to kill,” I said. “He has different ideas about what’s right and what’s wrong, and he’s made a hell of a lot of excuses for himself, but if he’s placing his neck on the chopping block — not killing him is going to be complicated.” He had started in on some sex stuff, addressing the issue of zombie brothels (ick), and I stopped for only a moment to listen and confirm that was about what I thought it was before continuing on. “Look, he’s — I’m not saying that he’s a good guy, I’m saying that there’s a path of some kind, and if this is something that represents too much evil for us to — oh Jesus Christ, shut up about the brothels.”

“Mute him?” asked Raven, and with a sigh, I complied. Muting things certainly wasn’t the most mind-blowing application of vibration magic, but it did seem to be the one that I used the most often. I kept an ear on him, trying to juggle my threads while still staying on guard. “Juniper, what’s the tip of the spear, if and when we do talk to him? What’s the plan of attack?”

“He’s already said that he gives up,” I said. “We get the locations of all his stored zombies so that they can be spiked, as the first thing we do. Obviously that’s going to take some time and some manpower, and there’s no way of knowing whether he’s telling the truth or not about whether we’ve got them all. But if he’s going to give up his insurance, which frankly doesn’t insure anything, that’s a point in his favor as someone who can be suffered to live. We replace his government entirely, which will take some transitional periods and probably some imported talent, along with a lot of logistics to get the EZ hooked into the planar trade network, and —”

“Perisev gave us a mission,” said Raven. “We weren’t supposed to bottle his zombies down to the last and replace his government with him as a prisoner and necromantic workhorse. We were supposed to kill him.”

“She’s right,” said Amaryllis.

“I know she’s right,” I said. “That’s a problem for the future. We were given two months, and we’re still well on schedule, even if there are hiccups here. We deal with Blue first, then we deal with the fallout from however we choose to handle this.” I looked at Raven. “Come on, surely Uther wouldn’t have been pressured into killing someone he didn’t want to kill, especially not an enemy who had wholly and completely surrendered.”

“Don’t count your chickens before they’ve hatched,” said Raven.

Over on the other thread, I was still listening to Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle as he spoke at length about how he was blameless for every crime he’d ever committed or been accused of committing. The funny thing was how often there was a tacit admission of wrongdoing right before he launched into an explanation of how this was perfectly right and fair, no more than should have been expected of anyone in his situation. In fact, most people, faced with the same situation, would have fared far worse when subject to the same pressures, especially given the level of scrutiny that he had been under.

If he was a reflection of me, then it was a really unflattering reflection. I tried to map myself to him, to think about how I dealt with — well, it was hard to say similar things, but I had hurt people and acted as though it was simply how anyone else would have acted. I’d made excuses for myself, usually while steeped in anger or depression. When Arthur had died, I’d punched another boy for saying that God had a plan, and it had taken months for me to admit that maybe I shouldn’t have done that. I had been a dick to pretty much everyone in my life, and it had been easy to think of myself as, if not the good guy, then as justified in what I had said and done.

But the more the Captain talked, the harder it was to see myself in him. He had gone all in on rationalizations, and I was sure that there were lies mixed in there, not that I was necessarily a stranger to lying to myself. For me though, there did eventually come a time when I would acknowledge that I had done something wrong. Blue-in-the-Bottle didn’t really seem to have reached that point. Even if he could admit that his zombies were experiencing things in those bodies, a bullet that I would have expected him not to bite, there were still excuses. Me? I could admit to having done shitty things, and I was at least trying to not do shitty things in the first place.

I tried to imagine how the Captain would have dealt with something like, say, secretly dating Tiff behind Arthur’s back, or treating Fenn less seriously than she deserved, or dating Maddie, or the Fel Seed Incident … and to maintain that these things weren’t wrong seemed like it would require a level of pathological aversion to introspection that I didn’t feel particularly applied to me. I was aware of my flaws, for the most part, aware of the costs and risks of what I did and how I thought. If anything, Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle reminded me more of Arthur, and the way that he would hunker down for an argument, becoming essentially immovable from his position, even (or especially) if it was a bad one. Arthur would spout a bad take, then joyfully try to defend it, and it was sometimes hard to tease out what he actually believed and what he was just saying in order to be contrary.

“The point remains,” he continued, yet again, “That I have put significant amounts of my own funds into solving these problems, and found, time and again, that it simply does not matter. No remedy will suffice to silence my critics, and I doubt that anything I’ve said here will sway you. People want a villain. They want a clear and obvious evil. For some, I’m that, no longer a man, but something irredeemably warped, deserving of death by my mere existence. I do hope that you’ve seen the light, but we can discuss my unconditional surrender, if you would prefer I remain alive.”

As predicted, the elevator finally coasted to a stop right on the final word. We had weapons drawn, but the fact that there had been no attack against us as we were going down was, to me, a sign that the Captain was more or less on the up and up. He knew enough about us now to know that we were coming for him, and that we were likely to win where others had failed.

“Alright,” I said. “Let’s talk.”

Orison

“Is it done?” asked Perisev. Her voice carried on the winds, silky and smooth but also quite loud. I hadn’t remembered quite how big she was, nor the strange way she moved, as though unbothered by physics.

“No,” I replied back, amplifying my own voice with vibration magic. “We have everything under control.”

“I did not task you with bringing everything under control,” replied Perisev. She slinked closer, though that didn’t really matter, since we were already within range of her dragonfire. “I tasked you with killing the necromancer.”

“We have plenty of time left to do that,” I replied. “You gave us two months, and it’s barely been one.”

She came closer once more, close enough to look us over. “You made a deal with him.”

“A temporary one,” I said. “He’s got cities down there, multiple cities, and untangling everything that he’s done, that’s going to take some time. There are innocents in all this. We need to create a new order.”

“And after that, I suppose that you’ll kill him? On the sixtieth day, perhaps?” asked Perisev, raising a scaled brow. Her claws were massive, just like everything else about her, and they were sharp enough to slice straight through steel.

“That depends,” I replied.

“On what, little one?” asked Perisev, seeming honestly curious about my answer.

“On how much we need him,” I said. “We’re talking about a migration of people that’s unprecedented in mortal history, at least so far as I know. And if another month passes and we still need him, then you’re going to have to figure out what you want to do about us failing your quest.”

“You would defy me?” asked Perisev. I stared at her, willing my face not to move a muscle. The answer was yes. “I’ve spoken to Tommul. There are persistent rumors that you cost him an eye, through magical means or otherwise. He’s none too happy about that, but it would seem that your legend, such as it is, greatly exceeds reality. Do you have a plan for killing one of our kind?”

“Uther managed it,” I said. “I’m sure that I could find a way, if I had to.” We had workshopped it. There wasn’t much that I could bring to bear against a dragon, save for memetics (maybe) and chlorine trifluoride, though the latter was so dangerous that we weren’t keeping any in Sable, and burning a dragon to death seemed like a crazy plan just on the face of it. There were other tricks, but I expected them to be more costly.

“Hmmm,” said Perisev, looking us over. “Has Elisha told you what he does down there?”

“Yes,” I replied. “He raises children until the age of eight, then kills them and sends their souls directly to the hells for devils and demons that have contracted with him.”

“Not always the age of eight,” replied Perisev. “There is more money in raising a child to the specifications of the purchaser.”

“That’s not something that’s going to be continuing,” I said.

“Do you know how many he’s personally damned?” asked Perisev.

“No,” I replied. “Tens of millions, at a guess, maybe higher.”

“Yet you suffer him to live,” said Perisev. “You met with him, and made a deal.”

“Not much of a deal,” I replied, frowning at her. “It’s going to be a complete dismantling of everything that he’s built. It’s a deal only in the sense that he knows we won’t respond to leverage, and isn’t so much of a sociopath that he wants his legacy to end in total calamity.”

“Is that your measure of him?” asked Perisev. “I always wondered, of Uther, whether he was as naive as the stories made him out to be. It was hard to tell. In his reforms, he could be mercenary, in his laws, he understood people and their deviancies. But in his personal dealings, there was a lack of cynicism that people found startling.”

“It’s not a lack of cynicism toward Blue,” I said. “No matter what his motivation, it would be catastrophic for us to lose him, because he’s made himself the glue that holds the EZ together, and because of imperial incompetence, he’s been left to grow in peace. We’ve got a month left, per our deal with you. That’s just enough time for us to take this from catastrophic to being very bad. I’ll kill him myself on the last day.”

“No,” said Perisev. “Kill him now. Elisha Blue is a man who is so afraid of his own death and so apathetic about others that he would damn a hundred million souls to the hells in order to squeeze another handful of years from this world. Every bit of honesty and compassion he’s shown you has been because he decided that was his best chance at winning your mercy. You may be willing to allow him life, but I am not. You must kill him.”

“I refuse,” I replied.

Somehow, I had thought that I would win this standoff by planting my feet and refusing to be intimidated. Maybe the most likely outcome, from my perspective, had been that she would go do it herself, and I would have to decide in short order whether or how I was going to stop her.

Instead, she opened her maw and spat a gout of jet black flame at us.

We were standing within six feet of Grak, which was the only reason that we survived. He’d put up all kinds of wards, anchored to himself, and dragonfire had been at the top of my wishlist. The ward had been costly, requiring time in a rented time chamber just so that he would be able to build up enough concordance. The dragonfire was annihilated on contact in the irregularly-shaped bubble around him that followed the contours of his skin, but there was enough of it that all we saw was black, and as soon as she was finished, we were witness to the destruction it had caused beyond what was warded.

The manor behind us was on fire, and the ground just beyond where we were standing was molten, the heat from it blocked by a different ward. The ground was shifting beneath our feet though, because the dragonfire was burning our surroundings, and the ward didn’t extend all that deep.

I felt a hand on me, then a brief moment of blinding pain, and then we were standing elsewhere, the heat that had seeped in completely vanished.

“Fuck,” I said. “She actually tried to kill us.”

“You shouldn’t have said you would work on a way to kill her,” said Amaryllis, scowling at me. “You basically told her that we couldn’t fight back. Remember that for next time.”

“We’re on war footing now,” said Raven. “Dragons rarely back down.”

“Tell the Underline to clear the area,” said Grak.

“Give me ten minutes and I’ll send word to one of the clones,” said Amaryllis. “I assume she knows about the ship.”

“She’ll be coming for us,” said Raven. “We don’t have the firepower to kill her or the defensive abilities to keep her out.” She looked at Grak, who had been the one to use the teleport key: the temporal plate made him much faster when time was short, and I was pretty sure that if we’d stayed even a fraction of a second longer, we would have been facing down claws and teeth. You could ward against dragonfire, but as I’d seen firsthand when Tommul crashed into Greychapel, dragons were resistant to wards. The wards offered no guarantee of safety, no matter how good they were.

“Where are we?” I asked. We were in a small room, one whose windows were closed. I could smell salt in the air and hear a breeze. When I used the Crown of Eyes, I could see through dozens of viewpoints, most of them in small, modest, well-worn rooms dominated by stone, ceramics, and rough textiles, with little wood. The species were varied, but trended human. No one was looking outside though.

“Extraction point twelve,” said Amaryllis, looking around. “Cidium.”

“Chosen as it was far away,” said Grak.

“Good,” said Amaryllis. “Give me ten minutes, I need to update one of the clones on the ship, if they’re still alive in ten minutes. Juniper, use the flask to send a message please.” She popped pencil, paper, and the Fourfold flask from Sable in short order, then immediately began concentrating on the merge.

“On it,” I said, needlessly. My blood was pumping fast, and I was sure that my brain had dumped all kinds of chemicals in response to the attack, though what I needed was a cool head, not twitch reflexes.

“What’s the plan?” asked Raven after I’d rolled the paper up tight and given the short version of things to the clones.

“We have three bases to defend,” I said. “I assume she’s going to come after us, possibly after having gone down into the bowels of Necrolaborem and murdered Blue herself, though I don’t know how well she can dig. Anglecynn would be able to bring a lot of firepower to defend us, so my guess is she’ll make for the Isle of Poran.” It had taken us six days to get from Poran to the NLEZ: a dragon moving at top speed could do it in half a day instead, though there was nothing to say that Perisev didn’t have her own forms of fast travel.

“Then we defend Poran,” said Grak.

“Maybe if we can get her into the domain of the locus,” I began.

“It would be putting both the domain and the locus at risk,” said Raven.

“What do you suggest?” I asked. “We pull in Uniquities or Anglecynn, get them to bring their expertise to bear?” I was keenly aware of the figure that Pallida had given me, that the cost to kill a dragon was twenty billion obols, and I was certain that it was higher if you had to do it in uncertain conditions on short notice. Those weren’t the kind of resources that the Empire would shell out without asking a lot of questions, and I didn’t really think that we had the time for that. Amaryllis had at least partial control over Anglecynn, but not enough that she could bring forward an immediate response to a rogue dragon at a cost of tens of billions of dollars. If Perisev were to come after us while we were in Caledwich, that would be a different story, but I didn’t know what the state of Caledwich’s anti-dragon planning was, and the civilian and military deaths following from that would be hard to stomach.

“We fight,” said Raven.

“We could,” I said. “Another boost of skills from drinking souls and I could see what there is to uncover in the fields of magic I have, supplemented with bladebound stuff.” I turned to look at Amarylis, who was still in the middle of concentrating. “Souls of exceptionally skilled mages aren’t easy to come by though, and it’ll require yet another sacrifice to get up to the virtue that lets me take from souls.” I tapped my foot and gave Amaryllis an impatient look. It wasn’t her fault that her power took ten minutes, that was just anti-cheese from the Dungeon Master, but I really wanted her advice, or at least support.

“Do you think it would work?” asked Grak.

“What?” I asked, looking back at him. He’d set up wards around the room, basic protections that went beyond what he carried with him, and now he was watching me.

“Enacting the same plan you did with Onion,” he replied. He went over to the window and opened the shutters, which gave a view of how dizzyingly high we were. Cidium was built into a cliff; it was a city that should have been logistically and logically impossible, except that it had been around for long enough to have adaptations. The air was noticeably thin, not quite enough that we were going to suffer for it, but enough that I wouldn’t have wanted to have a full-on fight, or run a marathon. We were all breathing a little harder than normal, especially Grak. “Do you believe that using a gimmick twice would be allowed?” he asked.

“I don’t know,” I said. “You think it would get patched or excluded?” But I repeat myself. “It’s not the kind of thing that I would allow in a tabletop game more than once, but if scaphism gets cut — it’s a virtue, not some unintended consequence of the system.”

“You use Skilled Trade to get Scaphism,” said Grak. “In combination, you are using one scarce resource to power your way into a second scarce resource. In the language of your games, you are using a fourth level power in order to gain a thirteenth level power, which you are using to go epic level.”

I winced at that logic, because it was exactly the sort of thing that I would have shut down, if not right away, then eventually, once the novelty had worn off. If it had been Reimer, because it was always Reimer, I probably would have asked him to sunset the character, and if he didn’t go for that, then I’d have gotten heavy-handed with some rule changes. Or, fuck it, if the problem seemed really intractable, I hadn’t been above just starting a new campaign with different characters, depending on how far my plans had already gone off the rail.

We had actually gotten to that point, where I was worried that god would shut the universe off because he was upset with me.

“Alright,” I said. “Hang on for a moment, I’m going to pray.”

“You’re what?” asked Raven.

“We’re operating under the assumption that there’s a god of Aerb,” I said. “Not these —” I caught myself before I called them ‘piddly’, because the gods of Aerb were still gods. “Not the kinds of gods like the others, a fully omnipotent and omnipresent god. I won’t say that it’s undeniable, especially since most of the weight of evidence is from what you would probably just describe as visions, but … I’m going to pray to the Dungeon Master to allow maxing out everything to work just one more time.”

“Okay,” said Raven, frowning at me. “Be tactful.”

“Sure,” I replied. I turned to Grak, who was looking out the window at Cidium, partly to watch for threats, but from the way his eyes were moving, also because he was interested in the view. He’d been here once before, to acquire the site, but hadn’t spent any actual time in the city. “Anything I should tell the Dungeon Master?” I asked him.

“We have our own conversations,” replied Grak, still looking out at the cliffside city.

“Alright,” I replied.

I settled myself down and faced away from the others as Raven opened up a book from the entad on her wrist and began looking for something, perhaps ways to kill dragons. We already knew everything in those books, but I got the sense that Raven liked books for the comfort that they gave her in uncertain times.

“Are you there god?” I asked. “It’s me, Juniper.” I was keeping the party from hearing me, naturally, because it would have been too embarrassing. “We haven’t really spoken since you excluded skin magic in Li’o, apart from a few stray thoughts here and there. Since then, I haven’t been having such a good time. I have to say, it’s really taking its toll. Some of that shit, if it had been done at the gaming table, by me as a dungeon master … the players would have gotten up and walked away. Tom would have taken me aside and asked me if something was wrong, Reimer would have called me a shit, Arthur — I don’t know, because I never did that egregious of a violation with him. Sorry for being vague, but you should know my grievances, and talking about them … that shit with Bethel? It sucked. It sucks more because she’s such a vital tool. I don’t want to reconcile with her. I don’t want to forgive her. In a just world, that would never be asked of me, no matter how much she reformed. This isn’t really about that though, nor is it about that shit with the pipe dream, which I still hold against you. Everything else, I hate, but I understand. Some of it was almost — not fun, but there was satisfaction to be had, at points. And some of it was fun, but mostly that came down to the other players, not anything you did.” That was wishful thinking on my part, but I couldn’t not believe that my companions had minds and agency of their own. That way lie madness.

I swallowed. I was getting off track. I should have gone into the prayer with a plan, but this wasn’t exactly prayer, it was more making a plea with an incredibly powerful entity for leniency, or with promises in exchange for rewards. Maybe that was what prayer was, at its base.

“I’m planning to kill Perisev,” I said. “She breathed fire on me, because she thought I was vulnerable, so fuck her, she’s dead to me, and hopefully literally dead as well. She sent me on a dumb quest, but when I neutralized Blue-in-the-Bottle, she just threw the quest out the window, so again, fuck her, she’s dead. Maybe there are people you don’t want me to kill, or to learn a lesson from, like Doris, but if Perisev was one of those people, then she should have come at us without so many threats and overt acts against us, even before the attempted roasting.”

I took a breath. “So with that said, I don’t know if I’m going to be able to kill her without going all-out. That means that I need to pull whatever dirty bullshit I can. You punished that, at Li’o, but you let it work before you nixed it. You could have stopped me before I killed Mome Rath, but you stopped me after. I get that. But there’s been this feeling of trying to keep things in my back pocket, holding onto them for a time of need, rather than because it makes sense on the object level. I’m worried that I have to pull my punches with Perisev because if I don’t, then there’s another exclusion coming, and I’m going to need everything I’ve got to make a run past Fel Seed. Something something ludonarrative dissonance.” If he was a kindred spirit, he would get what I meant.

I sighed. “I don’t know what you want. I can guess, and infer from what you’ve said, or from what I’ve seen of the game, but you’ve got this sense of humor that makes it hard to know when you’re being straightforward. Probably the implied existence of a Hitler achievement doesn’t imply that you want me to kill six million people. I’m a little more confused about the point of the Seven Locks one. But, look, the whole reason that I’m talking to you is that I want to be able to cut loose in the coming fight and not get punished for it because it’s the same trick a second time, or because it’s not ‘fair’, or not what you want. So … if that’s at all a consideration, then I guess I’m asking for this to be the last hurrah. And if you hate the tools you’ve given me, or I found a trick that you’re not liking anymore, then let it be after this fight. If you could, maybe give me a sign?”

There was nothing. I wasn’t sure what I had expected. The ancients, and to a lesser extent, modern religious people, seemed to read signs into everything. After an animal was sacrificed, they would cut it apart and see whether any organs were malformed. They would watch the clouds and the winds. So far as I could tell, nothing in the room had changed, and everyone was right where I had left them.

“I think The Underline is clear,” said Amaryllis, coming out of her trance. “Are things good here? Nothing on fire?”

“Not yet,” replied Grak.

“We should expect her to have entads,” said Raven. “We should also expect some facility with at least one magic, maybe more, at least magus tier, maybe in the top one percent in the world.”

We already knew all that. Raven had a habit of filling silence with information. Maybe it was reassuring to her, or maybe that was just the way she was. Maddie had been the same way, though it had always been about things I didn’t care much about, like k-pop or Minecraft. I had sympathized with the impulse, if not the subjects.

“She’s going to be the one to pick the battlefield,” I said. “That is, unless we have a way to pick one for her.”

“She can only pick a battlefield to the extent that we have things we need to protect,” said Amaryllis. “Unfortunately, we have a lot of things we need to protect. Poran is the worst case. We should be ready to move there at a moment’s notice. I’ll check in with the other versions of myself and set us up with a protocol to ensure that we can pass messages quickly with the Fourfold Flask.”

“I made the mistake of thinking that one damned person in this whole world would be sensible,” I said, shaking my head. “She’s just lucky that she’s right.”

“She’s right?” asked Raven.

“I’m fallible,” I said. “I can be beaten. Throw enough force my way, and I’m toast. Unless I’m grossly mistaken, I’m not playing by normal narrative rules, I’m playing by tabletop rules. Being able to suffer loss is part of the game, which means it’s probably the nature of reality. It’s actually super inconvenient to have people thinking that I can’t lose, because some of them are just going to rage against what they see as fate. They’ll come at me with everything they have, not leaving anything to chance, and I don’t even know if there will necessarily be a way out. I’m glad that we didn’t get to see what else Perisev had prepared, but worried that we’re going to find out in short order.”

“I need to sync with the others,” said Amaryllis. “But it would be good for us to have a plan in place so that I can propagate it.”

“Do we have a bearing from The Underline on where Perisev was going?” I asked.

“None,” said Amaryllis. “They never even saw her.”

“Then can we make a new contract with the Dorises?” I asked. “Track her?”

“Maybe,” winced Amaryllis. “The faction that controls the search capability isn’t fully appraised of Blood God Doris, and they don’t know that I’m there. It’s a possibility though.”

“The results of that tracking determine what we end up doing,” I said. “If she’s going to Anglecynn, we set up in Anglecynn with cooperation from the military there. If she’s going to Poran, then we defend the locus with the help of the tuung. Can you get on it?”

“Sure. But the tuung are going to do fuck all against a dragon,” said Amaryllis. “There are capable fighters among them, but even with as much entad support as we can give them, they’re not going to so much as make a dent.”

“What does our stock of souls look like?” I asked. “How many ink mages do we have?”

“Not enough,” replied Amaryllis. “There isn’t some stockpile of souls that we can draw from. Most of them go into large, secure tanks, where they get mixed around. It’s a similar problem with soul mages, whose souls aren’t saved and labeled. I’ve been trying, but the infrastructure doesn’t exist. For those people who do have souls in neatly labeled bottles, there are ceremonial aspects to it, and it’s not like there’s a centralized repository. The data isn’t collated, and procurement can’t go through a central authority, because that central authority doesn’t yet exist.”

This had been one of those tasks that Amaryllis had taken for herself, and I wasn’t terribly surprised to learn that it hadn’t yet borne fruit. For the Onion fight, I had been taking common skills, mostly gathered from the mooks we’d killed, members of the Golden Cete we’d killed outside Boastre Vino, the guards at the blacksite, or during our sweep through Li’o. Getting Ink Magic to 100 would take four magus-tier ink mages, and we hadn’t even fought one of them, at least so far as I knew. Aerb was not set up for the collection and exploitation of useful souls. Soul scaphism was like having a car in a place that didn’t have roads.

“Okay,” I said. I took in a breath. “And someone should contact Bethel.”

“Seriously?” asked Amaryllis.

“Yes,” I said. “Maybe not for this encounter, if Valencia doesn’t okay it, but if we’re having trouble figuring out what kind of possible solution there might be to Perisev, that’s a sign that we need the firepower she can bring to the table.”

“Doing that before either of you are ready is a recipe for disaster,” said Amaryllis. “And I want to hold off on being around Bethel for long enough that I don’t have to work at keeping a cool head.”

“Do you have to work at it?” I asked.

“Yes,” she replied with a curt nod.

“We will hold off,” said Grak. He looked at me. “What were the results of your prayer, if any?”

“You prayed?” asked Amaryllis. She seemed worried.

“I did,” I said. “And I didn’t get anything much out of it. Nothing concrete.”

“Were you respectful?” asked Amaryllis.

“He’s not some authoritarian thug,” I said. “Why do I have to defend your god to you?”

“He’s not my god,” Amaryllis replied. “He’s everyone’s god, whether they want him to be or not.”

“Yeah,” I said. “And you’ve been taught deference to gods, because they’re big and strong, and if they want to, they’ve slapped people down before, usually not for petty stuff, but —”

“But sometimes for petty things,” said Raven. She had a dour look.

“Sure,” I said. “But I don’t think that applies for the Dungeon Master. I don’t think he’s driven by ego.”

“The gods are not driven by ego,” said Amaryllis.

“Mostly not,” replied Raven.

“Okay, you know what, we have a dragon to kill,” I said. “We can talk about theology later. I treated the Dungeon Master how I thought he probably wanted to be treated, which was as a dungeon master. I tried to put things in that frame, like I was stepping outside the frame of the game to have a chat.”

“Fine,” said Amaryllis. “We’ll debrief later.”

“In the meantime, we need to procure souls and wait to see where she strikes,” I said. “We should have some time before she closes the distance to either Poran or Anglecynn.”

Spilled Ink

There wasn’t a lot of good information on who the most powerful gold mage of all time had been, but there was a decent chance that I was in the top one percent of all time. Gold mages were hampered by their quest for gold, and unstable by design, which meant that there were hard limits on how much wealth they could accumulate before they burnt out. It was entirely possible that I had rocketed up to the top of the pile for gold mages, all at once.

It wasn’t like the power that came from having tons of skills in their hundreds. No, this was raw, unbridled power, untamed except by my single point in the skill. I flew up, and probably would have killed myself if not for the fact that I had so much other magic at my disposal. I continued straight into the sky for a full second, and found myself far above the clouds. I could see the curve of Aerb, caused by some arcane effect that in a videogame I would assume had something to do with render distances, but here I probably thought was in order to mimic Earth. Light curved, making it look like I was shooting up from a sphere.

Skill increased: Gold Magic lvl 2!

I needed to skill up as fast as I could, and spent ten minutes in the air putting the new power through its paces. I flew up and down, getting a bit dizzy before I realized that I needed to consciously allow the fluid in my ears to slosh around, and then spent a few minutes testing that, trying to get my brain to agree with my senses about what was happening with my body. It was difficult work, but the levels in Gold Magic went up fast. The skill dealt with several aspects of the magic, all the various problems that weren’t quite covered by a general do-what-I-mean that seemed to come with it. I pulled steel ball bearings (these were an eternally handy tool that no self-respecting adventurer should be without) from my spare bandolier and tried firing them off using the tactile telekinesis.

Gold magic generally Just Worked, but there were certain required secondary powers that it simply didn’t have. I could easily break the sound barrier, but I didn’t have the incredibly fast reflexes and time perception that I would need in order to avoid slamming straight into the side of a mountain, or otherwise causing some major catastrophe. Gold magic would protect me from myself a bit, but not so much that I couldn’t accidentally kill myself if I was doing something dumb, or pushing it to its limits.

Gold magic passed tenth level with no virtue, and I was on the fence about whether or not that was a good thing. Most level 10 virtues were weak, parlor tricks more than superpowers, but I wasn’t sure that I would be able to get to level 20 before Perisev arrived. I wanted to know what direction the virtues would go in, whether they would be about the gold, the entity, or the tactile telekinesis.

(I was focused on leveling through gold magic and honing as much natural skill as I could with gold magic, but a small thread of my mind couldn’t help but think about all the ways that gold magic was stupid, at least from a worldbuilding perspective. It was something that I had talked about with Amaryllis a few times, with her eventually coming around to my point of view, or at least indulging me when I wanted to rant.

There were a lot of components that went into any good magic system, but gold magic had an inherent disharmony between the method of acquisition and the actual power granted. Having to stock up a big pile of gold that you couldn’t share with anyone and were bound to protect was a perfectly fine method of gaining power, but the power itself could have been anything, and it being tactile telekinesis was stupid and random, disconnected from whatever the magic was attempting to do or show with its acquisition method (‘capitalism bad’, probably, or ‘greed bad’). At least if it had been longer range telekinesis, you might have been able to make an ‘invisible hand of the market’ pun.

I had made some real stinkers like that in my time though, where two different pieces of a magic system or other worldbuilding element were just stapled to each other. Maybe it was just Aerb echoing the kind of failure that I sometimes came up with, or the laziness I sometimes approached worldbuilding with. It was hard to say.)

Skill increased: Gold Magic lvl 13!

Perisev was going to show up soon, I could practically feel it, though we had twenty minutes or so, maybe a bit more, maybe a bit less.

Take the gold and relocate it to somewhere only you can obtain it.

“And where would that be?” I asked, not really expecting an answer.

Celestar, it replied. Use the glove.

“Are you fucking kidding me?” I asked. “How am I supposed to do that and be back in time to kill the dragon?”

You have time if you go quickly.

It was a worrying level of specificity. It was also known that the call of the gold could and did lie about consequences.

I looked up at the sky. Celestar was overhead. I was fairly sure that the call of the gold wouldn’t ask me to do something that was impossible, not right off the bat, just hard or costly. This … I would need air, which we’d had a solution to since back in Caer Laga, and I would be able to survive the vacuum of space through the use of gold magic to keep my insides inside, and the lack of heat … it was nothing that I couldn’t prepare myself for, but I would have liked more than mere minutes of notice.

I landed next to our small group, touching down softly.

“Training and testing going well?” asked Amaryllis, raising an eyebrow. They’d been watching me, but hadn’t asked me to come down: vibration magic let me keep an ear on them.

“I need to move the gold,” I said. The pallet was still there, with the remaining gold bars loaded onto it.

“Where?” asked Amaryllis, tensing up slightly. This wasn’t entirely unexpected, which was part of the reason the pallet had been loaded.

“Celestar,” I replied.

“We might have to bail,” Amaryllis replied after a brief pause. “It’s too total of a loss and too far to go. Beyond which, there are threats up there.”

“Yes,” I replied. “I think I can make it back in time. Two hundred forty thousand miles, that’s a lot, but once I’m out of the atmosphere I should be able to pour on the acceleration. I’m already breaking the sound barrier when moving through air, this would remove friction from the equation.”

“Twenty minutes,” said Grak. “That’s twelve thousand miles a minute. Double unless you teleport back.”

“We can’t endure even a single minute of a dragon attack,” said Amaryllis. “It could destroy the locus outright. It could burn and destroy every building on Poran in that time.”

“Those are the stakes,” I replied. “Are you advising against it?”

“No,” said Amaryllis. “Hurry.” She reached down and touched the pallet with Sable, then ten seconds later, once it had vanished, handed it to me.

I didn’t waste time on saying goodbye, and instead lifted off toward the moon, slipping on Sable and the breathing gear as I tore through the atmosphere. I was up out of breathable air almost as soon as I’d left, and pushed on forward, making sure that the gold magic was keeping everything in place, the tactile telekinesis extending to and suffusing my gear. When I was clear of the last dregs of air, everything became clear and bright, with nothing to obscure my view. I could barely feel the vacuum when it came, and only through the vague sense that I was using a fraction of my force to fight against it.

Achievement Unlocked: The Final Frontier

Space warped around me. Aerb was flat and infinitely tesselating, with the sky having the same appearance no matter where you were, barring some variations on what they called the projection layer. To make that even the least bit coherent, Aerb needed to be folded up, and the light coming from the sun, moon, and stars needed to be essentially straight with respect to the surface of the plane. It was a four-dimensional mess, and I just trusted in the image of the moon ahead of me, trying to ignore the way things were curving away from (or toward) me, all that upper dimensional stuff not entirely important. So long as I was looking at the moon, light was following a path from it to me, and though it might not be where it appeared to be, I had no better way to navigate, no way to untangle how the light was being fucked with.

The multicolored stars were moving around me. They weren’t actually stars, not like we had back on Earth, they were giant, hollow, glowing shells, and close enough that there was some parallax. They were all out past Celestar, but still near enough, and with enough variation in distance, that constellations were warping. I was stunned by it. I hadn’t expected traveling through space to actually feel like traveling through space.

And dead ahead was Celestar.

“The moon sucks,” I said, staring up at it. Tiff was curled in next to me. It was a cold night for stargazing, but we had heavy sweaters on, and it hadn’t gotten chilly enough for us to retreat inside. I liked the chill in the air even in normal circumstances, but it was all the better with her warmth beside me.

“Yeah?” asked Tiff. “What do you have against the moon?”

“Fiction is better than reality,” I replied.

“Have you ever read Baudrillard?” asked Tiff.

“Probably not,” I said. “Give me a hint?”

“Uh … he’s the guy who came up with hyperreality?” she asked, more than said.

“Oh,” I replied. “Then no, doesn’t ring a bell.”

“Nevermind,” said Tiff. “Not important. Please, tell me why the moon sucks.”

“Okay,” I said. “First, the good points about the moon. It’s really, really big, it orbits so that we get nearly perfect eclipses, and it produces some great tides. All those are good worldbuilding features.”

“Plus it protects us from asteroids,” said Tiff.

“Well, sure,” I replied. “But from a worldbuilding perspective … protecting the whole world from an outside threat as part of a thankless job? That’s great if it’s a person doing it, not so much if it’s an inanimate lump of rock, even less so if practically no one knows about it.”

“It’s pretty though,” said Tiff.

“It is,” I said, staring up at the moon. It was a waxing gibbous, which was the kind of information that I had foolishly filled my head with. “But … it’s a plain white sphere. There’s no life up there, no civilization, nothing organic, just pock marks from other rocks smashing into it, a waterless sea … don’t you ever think about how much more exciting the moon could be? If you read early science fiction, you can see all these thoughts and possibilities about what might be up there.”

“Do you love me?” asked Tiff.

I looked over at her. “Yes,” I replied.

“I love you too,” she said, giving me a little smile. We were at that point in our relationship where we were saying it kind of a lot. “Does your mind ever get overrun by all the ways that I could be better?”

“No,” I said. I tried to think about that. “You’re perfect.” (And I really did mean it.)

“Oh shut up,” she said, smiling slightly. “No one is perfect. But to think about all the ways that things could be better, more interesting, more compelling … it’s fine to have dumb opinions about the moon and how boring it is, but you can’t let that outlook leak out into your real life.”

“I do love you,” I said.

“I’m not talking about us,” she said. “You’re obviously blind to my faults at the moment, but — you know that map and territory thing that Arthur talks about?”

“Sure,” I replied.

“Okay, well Baudrillard’s idea was that in the modern world, we have this super detailed map, so detailed that we live inside it, and the real world is crumbling away from a lack of use,” said Tiff. “Well, the representation of the real world, anyway.”

“And this guy is a French philosopher?” I asked, staring at the moon.

“Sociologist, I think,” said Tiff. She curled in toward me. “Just something to think about. The moon as it exists in fiction, or in representation, or media, is not actually the moon. We have this hyperreal version of the moon, in our heads, and it’s alienated from that moon, and just … I’m not saying you can’t or shouldn’t talk about how life isn’t what it could or should be. I don’t know. I’m sleepy, I’m rambling.”

We were silent after that, and she fell asleep next to me, her breath hanging in the air and her nose red from the cold. I was left staring at the moon, and thinking what I would put up there instead.

Aerb only had one moon, but it was a huge, ripe, beautiful thing. It didn’t have much in the way of color, but against the backdrop of the multi-colored skies, that might have been a bit much. It was laced through with geometric lines, criss-crossing and curling, ordered in a way that was both obvious and unobvious, clearly the product of design but without the intent quite clear. There was green, in places, trees and fields, and blue in other places, rivers and lakes, but for the most part it was off-white, a very pale milky color, with a point of pink, where something terrible had happened.

The elves had a focus on perfection, not just as a persistent cultural trait, but as an immutable core of their species. They needed things to be just so, conforming to the ideal of its type, placed within the proper hierarchies. From a certain viewpoint, the elven experience was one of grinding down the world around them into a tolerable form, so that errant, unruly things would not trouble them anymore. Almost all differences between elves came down to variation on what perfection fundamentally meant: one of the great problems of the elves was that their ‘perfect’ was not immutable, as much as they might wish it so, and as much as they might believe it to be static.

It was hard to learn much from the partite elves of the fifth wave of migration, those who had left Celestar immediately before the cataclysm. It wasn’t that they weren’t willing to talk, the problem was that hardly anyone knew what, exactly, had happened. The leading theory had to do with a school of philosophical thought that had enjoyed some popularity at the time. In essence, the philosophers had posited that there was a great upward bend to elven history, that perfection was, by steps, increasing with every passing century, if imperfectly, and that this rise in perfection was happening faster and faster. The past was less perfect, and thus deserving of scorn, but the future was where true perfection lay, apotheosis for the elves, and for Celestar. As philosophers were wont to do, they turned these philosophical musings into plans for concrete action: it was the duty of every elf to hasten the apotheosis of perfection along.

And that was more or less what was known. Telescopes showed no signs of life on Celestar, no evidence that there was anyone still living there, and strangely, no growth of the plants or trees, no change to the sculpted environments of the elves, no decay or erosion. Very few people or organizations had the resources necessary to get to space, and expeditions to Celestar were rare, especially after a number of high-profile missions there were inexplicably lost. Who or what was causing those (presumed) deaths was unknown. It was, all in all, a spooky place to be.

Start decelerating, said the call of the gold, speaking into my mind.

I stared at Celestar ahead of me. It was larger in my field of view than it had been, certainly, but not so much larger that I thought I needed to worry. I had enough rudimentary physics knowledge to know that going from A to B in space meant spending half the trip accelerating and the other half slowing down, but I didn’t have a good gauge for where the halfway point was, nor how fast I was actually going. I started slowing down a bit, watching Celestar and trying to do the math, which was difficult, given that I didn’t have access to the numbers that I needed. Sadly, the Range Finder virtue, that lowly level 10 bonus from Thrown Weapons, had been lost to feed soul magic. It might actually have been helpful.

You’re going to crash into Celestar, said the call of the gold.

I put my full force of my gold magic into going away from Celestar, but I was still traveling toward it, my accumulated velocity not quite being canceled out. I added in still magic, and I was fairly sure that helped enormously, but it wasn’t going to be enough. I was going to slam straight into Celestar, and I had no idea whether I had the power necessary to keep myself from dying on impact. Without any appreciable friction, I must have gotten up to some insane speeds.

At the last moment, I changed tactics, angling myself to the side, trying to dodge the moon instead of slowing down enough not to hit it. That effort might have borne more fruit if it had been done earlier, but instead of missing Celestar, I just barely clipped it.

It all happened very fast. The amount of counterforce that I could apply was enormous, so once I’d made impact, I came to a sudden stop almost immediately, and I was checking myself over for injury even as pieces of wood and rock were still falling down around me. I’d grazed the side of the planet for a length of about a mile before I’d slowed down enough to get under control, but between gold magic and still magic, I hadn’t taken any injury. I wasn’t even bleeding.

I had fucked up a fair stretch of Celestar on my landing, and rose up to look around me, both to check the damage I’d done, and to find a place I’d be able to hide the gold.

Celestar had been perfectly manicured, back when it had been widely inhabited. The exact history of Celestar was unclear, and was thought to stretch back far before the creation (or instantiation) of Aerb itself. Elves hadn’t turned every inch of Celestar over to productive use, but they had ensured that everything followed the aesthetic of perfection, and set everything up so that it could last for lifetimes, never needing maintenance or upkeep. There was a derisive term used in worldbuilding circles, ‘Ragnarok Proofing’ that referred to imaginary civilizations that made things to last long after the civilization itself was gone, usually for no clear reason. It was mostly as a method of creating zones of adventure for players. In the case of the elves, ensuring that their structures and gardens could withstand an apocalypse was a part of their warped mindset, above and beyond all the cultural considerations. The hundreds of years since Celestar’s calamity had left everything virtually unchanged: it looked shockingly liveable, aside from the damage I’d done on my arrival.

I spotted a large dome in the distance, and flew toward it. I needed a place to hide the gold that would be quick, easy, secure, and something that I could find again in short order. Celestar was huge, bigger than the Earth’s moon, and there were relatively few landmarks, aside from the major lines that commerce had traveled along. In theory, the call of the gold would be able to tell me where my gold was, but part of the reason that I was being asked to do this was so that I’d have a way, way harder time getting this gold back if I ever broke the compact. The least I could do was to acquire a few landmarks in case I needed to return without the help of gold.

I flew down into the dome, which had a crack in the ceiling, not one from wear, erosion, or anything else, but instead from a rock that I must have kicked up on my arrival, since the break was clearly new. From there, I flew, hovering into what must have been an office, its books still intact on the shelves, chair halfway out from behind it. Everything was pristine, like I had just come into the office of someone who had stepped out for coffee and would be back in a few minutes.

I popped out the pallet of gold onto the floor of the office, then paused for a moment to look at it, waiting for further instruction from the call of the gold. The gold wasn’t hidden, this was just security through obscurity and the immense difficulty in actually getting to Celestar. If I’d had time … it wasn’t worth thinking about, this was all in service of keeping the power.

“Good to go?” I asked, hoping that there was no further obligation.

Yes, replied the call.

I pulled out the teleportation key, pinpointed Poran, and tried to use it, but to no avail: we’d known that it didn’t work across planes, but hadn’t had any evidence one way or another whether it would work out in space or on Celestar. I didn’t take the time to swear.

As fast as I could, I flew out from the building, back out through the hole in the roof, and zipped straight through the atmosphere of Celestar, trailing a sonic boom in my wake that died off after I was through the air.

From space, Aerb was a ball of muted colors, and I flew toward it as fast as I could, trying to be mindful of acceleration this time. In theory, I could speed directly toward it, wait until I was halfway there, then start putting force in the opposite direction, but that would be inefficient, since still magic meant I could slow down faster than I could speed up. I also had no idea where on Aerb I would end up: the ‘ball’ was really the boundary layer where space got fucky, and in theory, a photon hitting that boundary could end up anywhere on the hex (if Aerb even had photons). A star was the same distance from any point on Aerb itself.

Space warped around me as I crashed through the layer, and when the land below me was decidedly not the Isle of Poran or the sea that surrounded it, I tried using the teleportation key again, focusing in on the point where my segmented worldline had a large cluster.

After a brief moment of dulled pain, I looked around to find myself at the site where Bethel had previously sat, which was now just an empty stretch of land. No one was around, but there was smoke on the horizon. I rose into the air to look at it, and was just in time to see the great black dragon come screaming in for another pass.

I flew at her, watching her mouth closely, because everything I had against dragonfire was by way of mitigation, rather than being able to fully protect against it. With the level of gold magic I had available, it was possible that I could fling it away from me as soon as it made contact, but I wasn’t going to risk testing that.

I was faster than her, in the sense that I could move quicker, but she was faster than I was, in the sense that she had the reflexes necessary to actually use her speed. She saw me coming, the blur of a person probably difficult to notice, and raised her claws against me, but I had enough speed that I was able to slip between them and slam straight into her. I’d been leading with my sword, holding it so that it would have the full weight of my body behind it and strike true, not that the actual weight of my body was very meaningful in all this. I’d been aiming at her head, but struck her in the chest instead, my sword piercing her with enormous resistance.

I pulled back almost at once, flying backward at top speed, and outraced the dragonfire that she breathed at me, even as I was trying to use the sword’s magic to multiply the wound. She was jet black and hard to see, her blood no doubt the same color as her scales. I was waiting for her to counter-attack as I flew away, but instead she went the opposite direction, past the domain of the locus, and I was obliged to follow after.

“Tommul is dead then,” she said. The words were a shock: we were far apart from each other, though growing closer, and both of us were breaking the sound barrier in the course of the chase. It wasn’t vibration magic, but dragons were never very big on entads, in part because the resizing capabilities that came with most entads didn’t tend to be so lenient as to cover someone the size of a house.

I slowed to match her speed instead of going into ruthless pursuit. We’d left the Isle of Poran behind, the two of us so fast that there was no way a fight would stay confined there, which was probably for the best.

“It took me less time to figure out how to kill a dragon than I thought,” I replied. That was too snarky by half, but it felt good to say. Killing Tommul … it hadn’t been in the heat of the moment. I had already won when I blinded him, and again when I cut off his wings and he’d slammed into the ground. I had killed him because I didn’t want a third act of that particular drama. There was something gratifying in killing him, like there was in killing a wounded deer that I’d been tracking through the hills, bringing the inevitable to finally pass.

“A shame,” Perisev replied. “I had hoped that there were rules and caveats to your power. Can you truly not be stopped?”

“I don’t need to be,” I replied. “You’re the dumb asshole who thinks leaving Blue alive for a month is a bigger disaster than killing him and letting the chips fall where they may.”

I was still holding back on speed, following her but not closing the distance. The truth was, I wanted to talk, to explain that I wasn’t some horrible monster. Sometimes you had to work with despicable people, surely she would understand that.

“What the fuck did you want from me?” I asked, after she kept going with no response. “What answer should I have given to your quest, or to Blue, that wouldn’t have seen you breathing dragonfire on us?”

I wasn’t really expecting an answer from her. My best guess was that this conversation and this chase were both in service of stalling, or maybe trying to get me to some secondary location where a trap had been set. Maybe she was charging an entad. Continuing on with this, rather than rushing her down and stabbing her to death, was probably just me giving in to my desire for closure, for some reason that I was doing all this. Perisev was an asshole who had gone back on her word and tried to kill me, but if my life as a protagonist was going to be me righting wrongs like that … there had to be a better way.

“Until a few months ago, Uther was the only example of his kind,” said Perisev. “There were many things to say about him, but it couldn’t be known what was inherent to the phenomenon, and what might be malleable. If Uther had gone there, he would have found a way to solve the problem clearly and cleanly, even if it left blood on his hands.”

“You don’t know the first fucking thing about me or Uther,” I replied. I could feel the anger rising. Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle was a difficult situation for me, and for our party, and it wasn’t my fault that I hadn’t been allowed a situation where there was a clear and decisive victory within reach. “Uther was given stories by the world. The only reason anyone could say he didn’t have it easy is because it went on for so long. You trying to kill me because there’s no way to cut a problem down to the quick? That’s asinine.” I could feel my anger rising, though I had no real stomach for this fight. My mind kept going to those millions of people living under Blue’s rule, most of them not even knowing that there was a world above. Killing Tommul had been a moment of victory, but one whose satisfaction hadn’t lasted.

“Truce?” asked Perisev. Without waiting for a response, she landed on the ground, going from above the speed of sound to a dead stop in a meadow, taking no longer than it would take a car going highway speed to brake. I dropped down, hesitant, to stand beside her, far enough that I wouldn’t be at the mercy of her claws, and hopefully far enough that her dragonfire could be dodged.

“I’m tired of these fucking tests,” I said. “You’ve been putting on pressure and trying to suss out my capabilities. You’ve been trying to figure out the rules by being an adversary. Pretty fucking dumb, in my opinion. I’ve got millions of people that I’m somehow responsible for back in Necrolaborem, and handing them off to the Empire, which hasn’t done a damned thing about that place for its entire sorry existence — killing is easy, but the rest of this stupid shitty world is not.”

Perisev was watching me. “I have never met someone so calm in facing down a dragon,” she replied.

“I’m angry,” I said. “I’m angry because there are millions of people being held hostage by Elisha Blue, and there’s nothing that I can do that will turn back that damage or make it okay. I’m angry because there are trillions of people in the hells, and no way to obtain justice. You? You’re barely even worth talking about. I’ll kill you like I killed Tommul, and at least I’ll know that I’ve done one thing today that the world is better for.”

“Yet if I bow my head, as Blue has done, will you let me live?” asked Perisev, cocking her head to the side.

“No,” I replied. “You gave me two months, then tried to roast me after one. I’d be a fool to entertain the idea of letting you live. I wish there were a way to bind you, to make sure that your commitment to peace was solid instead of threadbare, but there’s not. Besides, there’s a good chance you killed one of my friends.” I didn’t actually believe that would have happened, but killing people off-screen wasn’t beyond what the Dungeon Master would do. It was entirely possible that Amaryllis, Grak, and Raven were all dead. Possible, but I wasn’t going to make assumptions.

“And yet you speak with me,” said Perisev.

“I don’t want to kill you,” I said. “It’s a necessity, a burden. I need to get back to Necrolaborem and do what needs to be done there, whatever that might end up being.” I was sure that they had a whole culture there, one that would need to be dealt with. Removing the oppressor was only a first step, and the damage that had been done to those people was incalculable and irreversible.

“Our history is a history of stories,” said Perisev, either launching into a new argument or stalling for time. “Stories are the universal constant of both mortal and immortal species, of every thinking creature. Uther was, in his way, the ur-protagonist, an inflection point around which thousands of plot threads bent.”

“And?” I asked.

“Stories are universal,” replied Perisev, looking me over. “But their forms, their structures, their tropes, are not. Uther was the protagonist of many stories, but they were all stories of a certain type, peaks and valleys, building tension and climax, inciting incidents and calls to action. The world was warped around him, even if it was never obvious that this was so. He was, in some sense, the culmination of the stories of the Anglish, and the bringer of a new generation of stories, and the creator and completer of stories himself. At the time, I thought that this was the trajectory of history, that there was something in Aerb that turned toward stories, and had been accelerating us toward something or someone like Uther.”

“And then he left,” I said. “And the story magic, or whatever it was, dried up.”

“There was a last gasp of it, but yes,” replied Perisev, with warm air washing over me from her nostrils as she sighed. “For nearly five hundred years, there was no grand narrative arc. We were unstoried. Those of us who studied these things, we had questions about the nature of Uther, and what had happened, whether all his power explained his centrality to the stories he wove in the real, or whether the stories begat the power. We could not know how they mingled, and whether they ever would again. The time of the Second Empire was a frightening one, because it was almost deliberately outside the bounds of narrative, with no strong, singular leader, only people of importance working together in mutual agreement, an ideology that revealed its weaknesses, blind spots, and flaws. When it ended, it was anti-climax.”

“And then there was me,” I said. “And I don’t conform to the Utherian ideal.”

“You conform to the new ideals of the time,” replied Perisev. “Rootless, wandering, obsessed with the structure of things, wanting to bring context, to argue until you’re blue in the face. You are, as is this time, beyond the level of story. Do you think it goes unnoticed how you produce stories from nothing?”

“How so?” I asked, resisting the urge to cross my arms, because my sword was still in my hand, and I needed to be ready for an attack.

“The interviews in the papers, the articles put out by newspapers that you now own, the testimony put forward by yourself and Amaryllis in the Lost King’s Court, even the myths that you’ve spun for the tuung, who were raised on stories that transcended reality.” She huffed once, showing a bit of fang. “It is the style of the time. You are the nexus of it. Unlike Uther, your stories will never exist just on the object level, they will twist and contort themselves through subversions, retellings, and recontextualization into something different, a story about stories.”

“That’s Amaryllis,” I said. “I have fuck all to do with it.”

“It doesn’t matter,” Perisev replied. “You are a product of the spirit of the times, or the spirit of the times was created to serve you, but the world in this third modern age is a blending of cultures, an understanding that there is no one true culture, that stories are just stories, unfounded and ungrounded, written by men who have not lived their lives, but rather, have steeped themselves in the reality of those stories.”

“I’m not even from Aerb,” I said. “I’m from Earth. I’ve read about three fiction books since I got here, and haven’t had much time for literary criticism. None of what you’re saying means a goddamned thing to me.”

“It should,” Perisev replied. “You should understand your circumstance in this world, your position, your path. Surely you’ve thought on the pattern of narratives. Surely your wife, if not you yourself, has made an attempt to put everything into the cycles of narrative that Uther described five hundred years ago. And surely she has seen that you do not fit the pattern.”

I tightened my grip on my sword. “There’s no way that I can keep you alive. Even if there was, I wouldn’t. You don’t have half the understanding of narrative that we do, and if you did, then it would still have been a bloody fucking stupid idea to try to kill me.”

“Then if peace is impossible, better we finish this quickly,” she replied.

I was expecting the attack, and moved away from her claws when they came, then hurled back toward her with my sword in front of me, making myself into a spear with the sword as its tip. She had almost certainly expected the counter attack though, and sprayed dragonfire at me as I approached, which I zoomed out of the way of, going up and over her with fire hot on my heels, the maneuvers causing me to momentarily lose all sense of where the ground actually was.

I popped a unicorn bone from Sable and began burning it, worried that I was one wrong move from getting a roasting that I wouldn’t be able to come back from. Instead of having to loop, though, I slipped down when the fire stopped and delivered a solid strike, piercing through her scales by dint of my speed before shooting back away from her as quickly as I could, not wanting to risk being so close that she could get me with her claws.

I used the sword to multiply her wounds again, pushing at it until it stuck, watching her to see if I was appreciably weakening her. She was bleeding, but it was like poking a human with a long needle: in order to do any real damage, I’d either have to be very precise with my pokes, or make a whole lot of them.

I decided for the latter, mostly because she was so damned fast. With the multiplication of wounds through reflection, a death of a thousand cuts would only take one hundred twenty-five cuts, which was a little bit more manageable.

By the fourth run I took at her, I was starting to feel it. The overwhelming power of gold magic was doing almost all of the heavy lifting, and still magic helped to stop me, but none of it was completely effortless, particularly not the moment when I struck her. It was a workout, if nothing else.

She tried to roast me, but I was simply too fast, and by the time the dragonfire moved through the air, I was already somewhere else. In some ways, I was like a very annoying fly, buzzing around and occasionally coming in for a slight nip that did almost nothing. She changed her tactics, turning marginally so that my sword was more likely to deflect off to the side rather than pierce through her scales, and trying to get an angle on me so that she would be able to meet me with claws or fire.

When I backed up for another run at her, she took off into the sky, and I shot off after her.

She was faster in the air, but the biggest advantage as she flew along was that it limited my angles of attack. In the atmosphere, a good fraction of my power was being used to simply push the air out of the way, which limited my ability to cut in toward her at a fast enough speed that I could pierce through her scales. The best option was to try to get ahead of her and then rapidly switch directions, but she was too smart and too aware for that, and the first time I tried it, she changed where she was going, which didn’t net me much.

I was on a timer, though not one as concrete as when my skills had been ticking down. No, instead I was worried both about the next call of the gold, and beyond that, my body’s ability to keep going. I wasn’t using all that much in the way of physical effort, but it was still unsustainable, especially because I wasn’t fully trained up in how to handle movement that came from gold magic. The turbulence through the air was also taking quite a bit of my power, since I was many things, but aerodynamic was not one of them.

I was watching her as we did our dance through the air, trying to figure out the landscape of this battle. Surely if I just stabbed her enough times, she would lose blood and begin to falter. Yet as I looked her over, I could see that I was doing less damage than I would have expected. If I had been stabbed by a hummingbird a dozen times, I would have healed up. Why should I assume that she would have no way of doing the same? Healing would almost certainly be magical in nature, but dragons were magically resistant — it was possible though.

If she did have healing of some kind, then I was left with the prospect of either causing enough blood loss that she could be taken out, or doing so much damage to her that the magical healing got overloaded.

There was still no clue as to where she was leading me, and a vague worry that I wasn’t doing enough to stop her from getting to wherever she was going. Realistically, I didn’t have much of a way to stop her, because my pokes with the sword imparted very little in the way of momentum, and I couldn’t exactly get her to change course.

I decided to change tactics. I had Sable, which in turn held literally thousands of objects in it, maybe as high as millions, given that there’d been several periods where we were just stuffing things into it like crazy. Naturally, most of those things were completely useless, but there was one in particular that I was hoping would serve me: void bombs.

With a moment’s hesitation, I pulled one out, ripped off the covering that was attached to the adhesive, which set the timer, then flew in close, stopping only for long enough that I could slap it right onto Perisev. It was a big bomb, roughly the size of a grapefruit, and I was nervous about whether or not it would just get ripped off by the air flow, but it held against the odds. As I flew away, I was fairly sure she realized something was wrong, and she shifted to look down at it just in time for it to blow up in her face.

The void happened when I was well outside the blast range, but I swooped closer to her as soon as the bomb had gone off. The one I’d used had been an iteration of Amaryllis’ void arrow design, with two explosions: the first scattered void crystals, hopefully getting them more than a foot away from each other, while the second ‘explosion’ was a detonation of a void crystal itself, which it was hoped would chain to the others. It was a major violation of international law, and not all that smart with the warnings about the Void Beast, but it was certainly effective.

Perisev howled and stopped almost at once, and I could see the wound I had given her, a black chunk of flesh missing from her, its extent surprisingly large. I pushed on the reflection blade in an effort to widen it and multiply the impact as best I could, and she plummeted to the ground, with me close behind her.

With the two of us having lost our speed, I was again at an advantage, capable of leveraging my acceleration for a strike against her. I readied another void cluster bomb, the second of the two we had prepared, but I wasn’t confident that it would do what I wanted, given that critical injuries to her vital organs were more important than stripping away the upper layers of her skin and muscle. In fact, I was surprised that the void bomb had done as much damage as it did: I had thought that it would slow her down, not knock her out of the air.

But as I got closer to Perisev, I saw her eye on me as she dropped, and realized that she was, in fact, more clever than I had given her credit for. With the element of surprise, she was able to touch her claws against me, and while I had enough power to prevent the claws from shredding me, that wasn’t what she was going for: she grabbed me.

I pushed against her with gold magic, but that did very little for me, because her grip was so tight. My arms were pinned to the sides, and I tried to apply the force of the gold magic so that I would slip right out, but she was squeezing me too hard, though not quite able to physically crush me, not with the combined force of gold magic and still magic.

She brought her head down to douse me in dragonfire, and I did something that was either clever or reckless or both: I went into Sable.

I was in there only for a moment, a second, maybe less, and then I pushed back out again, flying away in a random direction as soon as I was in the real world. I had worried that Sable would be ripped or otherwise burnt, but I spotted it floating in the air as I twirled away, and went for it at full speed. It was a risk, given that it took me so close to Perisev, but she was having a moment of confusion at my sudden disappearance and reappearance, and I was able to grab it as it fell down.

The void bomb was still in hand, but not yet cooking. I flew in close, trying to get to her, but she’d really been playing her injury up, and while she’d lost some mobility, she was still well-capable of fighting me off, though my speed advantage had only grown with her loss of mobility.

I hesitated for a moment, hung in the air far enough away that I only had to worry about her fiery breath. There was a chance that the one-hundred-twenty-five cuts plan was the way to go, at least with her so injured. Every moment that passed allowed for her to try another desperate trick, or worse, for her to call for help, or for help to arrive. I might be able to kill Perisev, but if a second dragon showed up, the best I’d be able to hope for was a stalemate.

I decided on a course of action and began a run-up to Perisev, building speed through the air. Just before I reached her, I blasted her with a bolt of lightning, courtesy of Ring of the Dragon’s Mouth. I had never been immediately next to a clap of thunder, and underestimated how loud it would be by quite a bit, maintaining my ability to hear only because of my defenses. Perisev wasn’t greatly injured, only momentarily fazed, but it gave me the opening I needed to race in without having to worry about being snatched again.

I planted the bomb on her and took off again, as fast as gold magic would carry me, looking back only once I was well clear.

Her body had blocked much less of the blast this time, and the void effect had stripped scales and flesh from her wings. She began to fall again, and this time, I didn’t think she was faking it. I was cautious as I went after her though, keeping my distance, waiting for a gout of flame to sear the air in front of me.

She had just enough control not to crater into the ground, but unless it was a ruse, it seemed unlikely that she would by flying anytime soon. She knocked aside trees with her landing, and lay there for a moment, body heaving and leaking blood.

“I yield,” she said, twisting her head to look at me up in the sky with some effort.

“Do you understand why I let Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle live?” I asked, amplifying my voice with vibration magic. “It was to help people. That’s all I wanted to do. If I need to work with abhorrent people to do it, I will. If I need to do evil in pursuit of good, I will.”

“I yield,” she repeated, then coughed up a glob of black blood.

I wished that I had another void bomb, but I didn’t, so I popped out my sword instead. It was a brutal, ugly way to kill a dragon, but it was what I had available to me. I flew straight at her with my full speed, breaking the sound barrier just to slam my sword as far as it would go into her skull. I was mildly surprised that I could even penetrate the bone. It wasn’t enough to kill her though, so I flew back up, reflecting the wound as I went, then came back down for another strike.

She tried to fight back, but she was weakened and bleeding out. Her claws were too slow to catch me, the gouts of flame from her mouth too easy to dodge, and after five minutes or so of repeated strikes, she stopped moving altogether.

I waited, watching her to see if she would move, or if this was another ruse. After enough time had passed though, I got my notification.

Perisev, the Wretched, defeated!

Level Up!

I felt nothing from it, just some residual healing as my body got back into tip-top shape. My attention was on Perisev, watching the blood continue to slowly spill out of her.

The body will be worth a fortune.

“Shut up,” I told the call of the gold. “But yes, fine. I need to go back to Poran, then we can return and claim it. Tommul’s body too. Carve them apart, take some for us, sell other parts, hope that the Draconic Confederacy sees losing half a percent of their members in a single day as a threat and a warning …”

I sighed, then went over to Perisev’s head, pulled a runed spike from Sable, and extracted her soul, a bloody affair that took so long that I was worried I had missed the window of opportunity. Once it was out, I slid it into a bottle, and stared at it for a moment. It wasn’t any different from any other soul, not special for having come from a dragon.

I lifted off into the air and tried to get my bearings. I was in an unknown land, with no familiar landmarks, and only a vague sense of direction, but Sable contained a large number of maps, and I was able to start flying on a more or less correct line back to Poran.

I felt empty. Perisev’s purity test wasn’t fair, and I knew that it wasn’t, but I still wished that I had passed it. Working with Blue-in-the-Bottle was gross, even if it was the sensible thing to do.

There was an undercurrent of anxiety running through my thoughts. Some of it was the call of the gold, that might ask me for something new at any moment, and which we had enough invested in that it would be painful to resist. A large chunk was Necrolaborem, and the enormous problems there that had no easy solutions. I was responsible there, and it was a responsibility that I couldn’t abdicate, not when I was so well-positioned to respond.

But the third part was more immediate than either of those: it was the smoke on the horizon, coming up from the Isle of Poran. That was how I had left it, and whatever had happened there was so far in the past that I had no chance of affecting the outcome. I’d told myself a lie, that everyone was fine, that there had been no off-screen deaths, but that was only enough to get me through the fight with Perisev. I knew my existence on Aerb well enough to know that sometimes people died, even if it didn’t make a lick of dramatic sense.

I landed next to the tree house, which had been spared dragonfire, and my eyes moved quickly between the people I saw, knocking names off my list. Grak was there, Raven too, a few of Amaryllis — and no Solace, though the locus had been visible from the sky, toward the edge of the domain.

“Is Solace okay?” I asked.

“No,” said Amaryllis. “She was badly burned protecting the locus. She’ll live, though.”

I let out a breath. “Good,” I said. “The locus?”

“Weakened,” said Grak.

I nodded. “Perisev is dead and the gold is on the moon. I leveled up.” The tension was releasing, a single source of anxiety having been removed, lightening the load. “We need to get back to Necrolaborem then.”

“We took some hits here,” said Amaryllis. “We’re healed back up, but most of that was due to Solace.”

“Okay,” I said, shifting slightly. “Look, there’s going to come a point very soon when I need to get off the wild ride of being a gold mage, so time is vital.”

Amaryllis stared at me, then nodded. “You’re right. There are things that need to get done.”

“It’s also possible that we pissed off a whole bunch of dragons,” I said. “That’s two in one day, and while I don’t think they’d want to commit their lives to killing me — I talked with Perisev, and I guess to her, it was about stories, or morality, or some stupid shit like that, and — we need to deal with the Necrolaborem stuff, preferably soon, but this is just fair warning that we might be kicking off the Dragon Wars arc.”

“We’ll be ready,” said Amaryllis with a nod.

“No, we won’t,” replied Raven. “We burned through two powerful strategies today. What do we have as a third?”

“Nothing,” I said. “Nothing yet, anyway. If I absolutely had to kill a third dragon, and I couldn’t do it before I have to ditch gold magic, then I would go to Blood God Doris and enlist her help somehow. We also have an unused rune magic exploit, we could leverage the Couch Potato … there are a few paths, but yes, none of them are particularly short paths.”

Get to work on carving up the bodies, said the call of the gold.

“How, exactly, does one cut up a dragon?” I asked. “Can we put someone on that?” I tapped my head. “I’m at risk of losing my gold mage license.”

“I have contacts that can help,” Raven supplied. “There might be some legal difficulties, depending on where both of the corpses landed.”

It was only after she finished speaking that I realized I’d last left her next to Tommul. She had made her own way back, as I thought she would, and quite a bit faster than I’d expected.

“Are you okay?” I asked.

“Fine,” she replied, though she really didn’t convey that with her tone.

“I never meant —” I began.

If you wait too long, others will claim the corpses.

“The gold calls,” I said with a grimace. “It’s a fortune we would be leaving on the table. We’re also going to want to find and control their hoards, if that can be done. Do we have any kind of right to them? Or can we press a claim?”

“We can on Perisev, not on Tommul,” said Amaryllis. “It’s a jurisdictional issue. Let us handle it, we’ve been preparing for a dragon death in abstract terms since the train ride to Headwater.” And by ‘we’, she meant her, now multiplied.

You still need to be a part of it. Amaryllis must be kept accountable.

“I still need to oversee and be in the loop,” I said. “Sorry, that’s by orders of the licensing board.”

Amaryllis nodded once.

“And we need to return to the NLEZ,” I said, feeling an internal twist of anxiety as I said it. “Sooner than later.” I felt like making a joke, or saying something to relieve the tension I was feeling, but there was nothing that wouldn’t just make me feel worse. “I frankly feel like I need a week in a time chamber to try to untangle everything, and another week to decompress.”

“Gold magic won’t allow it,” said Amaryllis.

“Fuuuuuuuuck,” I said. “Fine, let’s just get all this shit over with.”

There was an awkwardness in the group, one that I could keenly feel. Maybe it was the disconnect between me and them, the fact that I had soloed both the dragons without much in the way of help, or the battle they’d clearly been engaged in while I was elsewhere. I couldn’t bring myself to care that much about Solace, not when they’d told me she was going to pull through. It was a soft punch, compared to what I had been expecting, not inconsequential, but … close, compared to thinking about the death of a team member. And it felt like I’d been given permission to not care, to offload the social and emotional labor for another time. But the more I thought about it, the more I could see that things weren’t sitting right, not with me, not with the group.

“Sorry,” I said, unprompted. “I’m feeling off. Perisev — we talked. She had a point. Not a great one, not one that I could do a single thing about, I don’t think, but — I think she felt like the story of my time here wasn’t a proper story, or didn’t follow the same story rules, or was a reflection of,” I shrugged. Maybe she was insane, or viewing things through a different lens, but it felt like maybe she had a grain of truth. How things had gone with Blue-in-the-Bottle thus far were a sign that she was right, because it wasn’t how it would have been for Uther. “She surrendered, and I killed her anyway. Same with Tommul. I could have let him live. Neither felt, or feels now, like vanquishing an enemy, they felt like shitty things that had to be done, even though I didn’t want to do them.” Tommul, maybe, when I’d killed him, had given me a rush, but it had faded, leaving behind more complicated feelings. I paused, waiting for words of encouragement or absolution from the group, but they didn’t come. I was sure that Amaryllis, at least, would have said them, if she’d thought that was what was best, or what was needed, but she was silent, just watching me and waiting.

“Elisha Blue is a problem,” I said. “A real, honest, problem, one that can’t simply be punched to death. He’s got to be our focus. I don’t think that he’s honestly going to let us fully defang him and eliminate any reason to keep him alive, but we can’t just kill him, because without him, there are huge problems in just keeping all those people alive, nevermind all the potential people ending up in the hells by way of his necromancy. He thinks that’s not leverage over us, and he’s partially right, because the moment he starts issuing threats I’m just going to fucking end him —”

“Is this about how you’re feeling?” asked Grak.

“Sure,” I replied. “Lost, hopeless, afraid, with this weight of responsibility that can’t be shucked off onto someone else, and no real concrete plan as to what I can do — but it’s also about what’s going on at the object level, and —”

You need to act now on the corpses.

“And this dumb fucking gold monster telling me what to do is not helping things,” I finished. “So let’s get started shoveling this shit mountain, one scoop at a time.”

The Endless Toil

I watched as the work crew dismantled Tommul. Dragon deaths were incredibly uncommon, the kind of uncommon event where a government workgroup might put together a committee to make a thick binder with plans and contingencies, which would then get left on a shelf for twenty years without being used, until the time a new workgroup was created to update it.

It had been a hundred years since a dragon had died, and it hadn’t been since Uther’s time that more than one had died in quick succession.

There were, however, companies that specialized in cutting apart giant carcasses as quickly and efficiently as possible: whalers. Aerb had an enormous amount of water, and truly vast oceans, which were swimming with all kinds of creatures, some of them very deadly. Though they called themselves whalers, the industry actually dealt with all kinds of sea creatures, some of them quite large, with their biology varying considerably: whales were just the most common. (There was, of course, an alternate etymology, a folk understanding of these men and women as wailers, possessed of the kind of lunacy necessary to pull up massive creatures from the deeps. Having met a few of them, I was willing to give that meaning some credit.)

It had been a rather interesting time for whalers, who had, for the most part, put their dealings with sea creatures to the side. A bit less than two months prior, an absolutely enormous monster had appeared in Li’o, and many of the whalers had been teleported over at great expense to help cut it apart and harvest whatever could be harvested from it as fast as possible, before the flesh began to putrefy and as much of the corpse as possible was delivered by star magic to somewhere that wasn’t urbanized. Given how immense and powerful Mome Rath had been, there was a lot of money to be had in harvesting it, which would have been true even if there had been no magic involved, only enormous quantities of skin, fat, flesh, bone, and a hundred other things. Mome Rath was more than that though. It was possessed of its own unique magic, and people were trying their best to figure out how to exploit whatever was left now that the creature was dead.

The whalers had been making bank, given that this was mostly within their wheelhouse, and that there was a pressing need to get everything done before the less-stable parts of the body rotted. From what I understood of the situation, lots of the people who were homeless and jobless in the wake of Mome Rath showing up in Li’o were being put to work on whaling crews, rapidly trained in the finer points of taking apart a creature that was so big you might sometimes think you were on the plane of flesh.

We’d pulled two crews of whalers off from Li’o, where the work was winding down, or at least sideways (toward more industrialization), and promised them a portion of the proceeds. The two dragons had died in completely different places, but we had claim to both of them, and it would be a windfall, of sorts, even before we went after the dragon hoards. Dragons were one of the most intensely magical creatures on Aerb, and while there were some supposedly exciting applications of Mome Rath and the Momenagerie, the uses for dragon bone, dragon scale, dragon blood, dragon teeth, and so on, were well-known and decidedly less speculative. Once this venture was finished, we’d be flooding the market, and even with that being the case, it would be a substantial amount of money.

“I’m bored,” I said to Amaryllis, who was standing beside me. I wasn’t standing, but rather, floating, because that was something that I could do.

“Sorry dear,” she replied, not seeming like she was sorry in the slightest. Her eyes were on the work crews swarming Tommul. I wasn’t sure whether she knew anything about taking apart dragons, but she was sure watching the people working as though she was a supervisor rather than an observer.

“Maybe I’ll go help,” I said.

“Your job, as I understand it, is to look intimidating and kill anyone who gets out of line,” replied Amaryllis.

“I’m not going to kill anyone,” I replied.

“I know that,” said Amaryllis. “But if they see that you’re floating there in all your glory, they’ll be intimidated enough not to push things so far that you would be asked to kill them. Lending a helping hand is good public relations, and there’s some utility, but we need to keep you from being asked to assault or kill anyone.”

I frowned at that. It was true, after all. But the call of the gold was asking me to basically just sit in place and make sure that no one stole any of the dragon parts, which was incredibly lame, a 0/10 quest if I had ever heard one, unless we were going to be interrupted by a theft or a fight, which I didn’t think terribly likely, and was trying my best not to hope for, no matter how bored I was. I had my senses open and defenses up, just in case.

“Thoughts on the exclusion of soul magic?” I asked. She wasn’t the prime Amaryllis, which was important only in the sense that it meant she wouldn’t be any help in a potential combat scenario, and didn’t have access to entads.

“It’s bad for you personally, but probably a net good for society,” replied Amaryllis. “An exclusion of either or both of Scaphism or Skilled Trade would have been bad, but more understandable, and less net good for the hex.” She shrugged. “It takes those off the table for Fel Seed, but I’m not sure that it was lost because it was necessary to lose.” She gave me a bit of a disapproving look.

“Sure,” I said. “So you think that after killing Tommul, I should have dropped all the skills down to their baseline, then never used soul magic to boost skills again?”

“I don’t know,” said Amaryllis. “My read on the Dungeon Master is that he might have hit you with an exclusion anyway, since you had declared that you wouldn’t be using those aspects, but it might have been a partial exclusion instead of a full one.” She shrugged again at all the unknowables. “But like I said, it’s probably a net good for the world. There are, or were, almost certainly rogue soul magic practitioners out there, and now they don’t have the ability to keep resetting their thralls. It would be nice to think that they’ll get their comeuppance, but it’s more likely that they’ll kill the thralls before that happens.”

“Kind of hard to see it as a net benefit,” I replied.

“We’ll watch in the coming month for any sudden political upsets,” Amaryllis said. “My guess is that we’ll see one or two, possibly governmental, possibly corporate. The anolia are the primary defense against a rogue soul mage raping their way to the top, but there are limits on what they can do, or, I suppose could do. Anolia magic is presumably intact, I’m checking into it with another self. The services of the anolia are much less needed now, either way. Which is too bad for them, but again, is probably a net gain for the world.”

“Hrm,” I said. “No soul healing.”

“It was a relatively minor part of the package,” said Amaryllis. “Likewise soul linkage. In terms of the whole of society, it’s something of a relief.” She paused for a moment. “You know, people often talk about what the worst possible exclusion would be, but somehow they don’t focus on which one might be the best.”

“Are you mad at me?” I asked.

“No,” she replied. “There have been things I’ve considered missteps, but to extend a metaphor, they were missteps that I don’t think put us significantly off the path. Mostly I’m just feeling useless.”

“And how many things are you doing right now?” I asked.

“Oh, lots,” said Amaryllis. “But I had virtually no hand in killing the dragons. I think there’s a real opportunity to do good in the NLEZ, but it’s the kind of frustrating, abstract good that doesn’t satisfy that primal part of me that wants to physically punch evil into submission.”

“I don’t think Perisev was evil,” I said. “Tommul, maybe, but Perisev … if you view the world through the lens of stories, and you think that you’re living in some kind of postmodernist story, then I guess it makes sense to try to get the unconventional ending.”

“What’s postmodernism?” she asked.

I froze in place. “Uh,” I said. “Are you asking me because you don’t know, or because you want to see whether I know?”

“It’s not a word that came up a lot in my reading,” said Amaryllis. “For the most part, it seemed to be whoever came after the modernists, or was reactionary against them, but there wasn’t a cohesive and easy-to-digest definition. Why would you use the word if you didn’t know what it meant?”

“It’s not that I don’t know,” I replied. “It’s — this is not going to be even remotely relatable to you, but do you know that feeling of playing a game on one monitor while a video is going at one and a half times speed in the other monitor, and you’re kind of catching the drift, but it’s also just a bunch of words washing over you, and you’re in the game, so you don’t want to slow it down, and it’s not something that seems super important?”

“This would be … on your personal computer?” asked Amaryllis.

“Yeah,” I replied. “That’s the kind of understanding I have of postmodernism.” I paused for a moment. It would have been a good time for gold magic to tell me to do something. “I have no idea what postmodernism would mean in terms of tabletop games. If it were about books or games, then it would be metafiction, intertext, navel gazing, unreliable narrators, experimenting with timeline and chronology, stuff like that.”

“And you believe that Perisev believed that this was the kind of story we’re in?” asked Amaryllis.

“I guess,” I replied. “I mean, she couldn’t have known about it, but the Dungeon Master did show me a book that supposedly laid out our adventure.”

“And she thought that she could kill you because … it would be a postmodernist ending?” asked Amaryllis.

“Sure,” I replied. “I mean, probably, maybe. But she wasn’t talking about Earth postmodernism, and she never actually used the word, she was talking about the state of art on Aerb, which is … the same? Not the same? I really have no idea, because I’ve been sticking to non-fiction like my life depends on it.”

“Broadly speaking, I’m not sure that she’s correct,” replied Amaryllis. “It’s true that a lot of the new works of the last few decades have been self-referential and very aware of the idea of fiction in one way or another, but people still read Uther’s stories, they still go to his plays, and there’s a persistent trend in attempting to adapt and revitalize them. It is, in my view, absolutely fucking absurd to make claims about what media is like for a group of five billion people across two hundred species.” She paused, pursing her lips. “But I suppose the distribution of media is unequal, and I would imagine that a small core of a hundred works get the vast majority of exposure. Still. Dwarves are the second most populous species, and most of them don’t speak Anglish. You can’t talk about what the media is like on Aerb, not in a coherent way.”

“The dwarves are still influenced though,” I said. “I’ve only read about a dozen books in Groglir, and only a few of them were fiction, but it’s still possible to see Uther seeping in. There are occasionally Anglish words, or human gender stuff, or … I don’t know, little bits and pieces that have crept in. And I imagine there are translations and adaptations.”

“Well, sure,” said Amaryllis. She was tapping her foot. Tommul’s head finally came free from his neck, after considerable work, and they set to work pulling his teeth. “Let’s say that Perisev is right that you’re an agent of postmodernism, or some Aerbian understanding of postmodernism. How does that change anything?”

“I don’t know,” I said. “Guesses?” She nodded. I thought for a moment before replying. “Okay, narrative might fail at any moment, if it’s to make a point, or to make the point that there is no point. You’ve been looking at narrative like it’s what Uther had, narrative cycles, or a modified version of that where it’s narrative, but influenced by our understanding of narrative, a recursive narrative that’s still fundamentally narrative. But to take one example, time might not work like that, it might be — I don’t know what this would be like internally, from our perspective, but you can tell a story with time all out of whack, put the beginning at the end and the end at the beginning, thread different events however you want, constantly switch perspectives … you can do that in modernism too, but I think in postmodernism it’s partly to play with the form, partly to question the audience’s interpretation of events, all kinds of things. You’d expect a lot of metatext and intertext, I guess, which I think we already have covered, because we’ve played games within games, and as Perisev pointed out, we’ve crafted stories that were corruptions and refinements of the stories that we actually lived. I guess we’ve done a bit of intertext, or a lot of it, given how many movies we’ve watched together, and how many books I’ve read, and some of the conversations, and, naturally, the library. The defined breaks from traditional narrative would be things like stream-of-thought, random events that don’t fit in with narrative, playing with the expected narrative cycles or characterization … oh, and an unreliable narrator.”

“Hrm,” said Amaryllis. “Are you?”

“You’re asking me if I’m an unreliable narrator?” I asked. “I mean, I haven’t lied to you, except those times I did. There’s probably some alternate version of this story where I didn’t out myself the moment we met, and was able to keep the secret of being dream-skewered, or … maybe pretended that I was just dream-skewered, without all the weird Aerb-Earth interplay. But I’m also not a narrator.” To my knowledge, anyway.

“Okay,” said Amaryllis. “I know you don’t like to talk about narrative, but — Juniper, this might be really important.”

“It’s not actionable,” I said. “I mean, it’s even less actionable than regular narrative theory, because for all we know we might be side characters, or the story might be all out of order, or — it’s pointless. Like, more pointless than it was before, which was already pretty pointless. I don’t mean to shut down a conversation that I helped start, but sometimes you have to accept that you can’t actually understand the universe.”

“Alright, I relent,” sighed Amaryllis. “I’ll talk about it with Raven. I might already be talking about it with Raven.”

“How is she?” I asked, eager for a change in conversation.

“She felt sidelined by the dragon fights, in ways that felt unpleasantly familiar to her,” said Amaryllis. “She got her bell rung. She’s strong, she’ll survive.”

“Good,” I said. “I’ll … I don’t know. Show some empathy, I guess.”

“Which you’re finding hard, at the moment?” Amaryllis asked.

Through this, we were just standing (floating, in my case) there, watching teeth being pulled out of Tommul’s mouth, and a special machine was being hooked up to his opened veins to manually pump blood through his body and out an artery into waiting barrels. It was pretty grisly, but I was a bit numb to gore at this point in my career, perhaps helped by high WIS, which was supposed to help with not freaking the fuck out about things.

“I used to have this problem when I was a little kid,” I said. “I had this knowledge that the world was horrible, and that despite appearances, I was one of the lucky ones. I hadn’t been born into slavery, I would probably never directly experience war unless I enlisted, we had creature comforts, media, the internet, I never had to worry about where my next meal was coming from. I had two monitors, for fuck’s sake, even if one was a hand-me-down. I kind of got obsessed imagining all those other kids who had just gotten fucked by life. It wasn’t pity, it was this gut-wrenching sadness, like I was feeling the weight of every issue in the world, or as much as I could at the age of ten.”

“I know the feeling,” said Amaryllis, nodding. I looked over at her, and saw how set her face was.

“When I was feeling all that, I just gave so much less of a shit about everything else,” I said. “I’d get upset because I could hear mom and dad screaming at each other through the walls, but then I would go to bed crying because I was thinking about these poor unfortunates who were largely half a world away, who I could do nothing for.” I chewed on my lip for a bit. “Maybe it was just a coping mechanism, a way to equate my own pain to this other pain that felt larger and more important, to co-opt it. I don’t know. It was this feeling of hopelessness and helplessness.”

“And that’s what you’re feeling now?” asked Amaryllis.

“You can’t unfuck a whole civilization,” I said. Eight million people, born and raised underground. “You can help them, and we will, even if we have to move mountains, but they can’t be unfucked.”

“You see the scars and despair, because the wrongs can never be fully righted,” said Amaryllis.

“A fuckin’ trillion people in the hells,” I said. “Even if we can save them, even if I’m ever allowed to be god … the actual experience still happened, even if the memories are erased, or whatever we’re going to do about it.”

“You do what you can, then you move on, to do whatever else you can, and try not to look back, try not to glance at the horrors that can never be undone,” said Amaryllis. “Live in the present. I don’t know. We have such a different outlook on life and society. When I look at the people living below Necrolaborem, yes, it makes me angry, so filled with rage that it takes conscious effort to calm myself down and think straight. But I also see people that we can help, suffering that we can remove from the world, concrete ways that we can improve conditions. It might be meaningless, given that we’re planning on jumping to the end, but that’s not a bet that I’m willing to take. And in the worst case, we’ll have wasted a bit of effort while trying to help people.”

“Yeah,” I replied. “I guess so.” I squared my shoulders, and tried to look imposing for the work crew. I would have gone to help them without complaint, if the call of the gold had told me to, but it seemed more concerned with Amaryllis, and the possibility that she would try to deprive me of gold.

We talked about other, less heavy topics after that, which was a bit of a relief. Amaryllis had a breadth and depth of knowledge of Earth culture that sometimes seemed to rival my own (though some of that was just from reading synopses and printed-off Wikipedia pages), but she still liked to pick my brain on various aspects of my culture, and there were blind spots that I always had fun poking at. It might have been that she was trying to cheer me up, but if she was, it was working, so I couldn’t begrudge it. We focused on the kind of things that I considered to be postmodern, which for all I knew might have been a complete misreading of what postmodernism actually was. We stayed away from any discussion of our situation, instead focusing on what made Scream cool, the ending of Monty Python and the Holy Grail, and the ways that Cabin in the Woods had been one of the major inspirations of my Long Stairs campaign.

“It was a complaint that the group often had,” I said. “I would watch something, or see something, or learn something, and it would stir my brain up, then get put into a campaign within a week or two. It wasn’t always a movie or a book, sometimes it was just something that had sparked a moment of inspiration, but they never really understood with those, because I never said where I got my ideas from, if I even knew. I had to try to put up these mental flags on everything, to make sure I knew who was watching what, so that I could do my creative appropriation without getting called out, or making it too obvious.”

“Did that work?” asked Amaryllis.

“Yes and no,” I replied. “I mean, we mostly drank from the same well, you know? We would all go see the latest blockbusters together, we played a lot of the same videogames, a ton of the books we read got shared around, because you want to talk with your friends about them instead of just having them sit in your head.” I shrugged. “But there was always stuff that I’d stumbled across that I knew they’d never seen, and vice versa. It was kind of nice, to have this group, but also our separate lives that we only ever really knew about by contact.”

“You have a group of friends now,” said Amaryllis. “You barely know one thirtieth of what I get up to. But I suppose it’s not the same, our kharass ?”

“For as much as my group might have had differences of outlooks, we were all pretty solidly of the same culture,” I said. “The amount of variation between teenagers in Kansas is … compared to Aerb, it’s fucking nothing, and the Council of Arches has a level of diversity that still sometimes boggles my mind. Which is great, because there are always things to learn and appreciate, but a lot of our time has been in building up a common platform of understanding each other, and sometimes it’s difficult. Plus I’ve been putting in time with the tuung, and they have this entirely different culture that you made from the ground up, and it’s — a whole different thing.”

“You’re homesick,” said Amaryllis.

“Maybe,” I replied. “It’s been too long since we’ve had real, proper downtime. I want,” I paused, “I want a home. Not The Underline, not a palace in Anglecynn, just … somewhere that I can return to that’s mine. So homesick, but not necessarily for Earth, I guess. I feel like I’ve been couchsurfing for half a year.” I had never actually been couchsurfing, save for a week in junior year when my parents had been intolerable and I had slept over at different friends’ houses as much as I could, chaining sleepovers so I didn’t need to sleep in my own bed.

“I’ll see what I can do,” said Amaryllis.

“I don’t need you to,” I replied. “But it would be good to have an anchor, and if you can think of a way of doing that,” I shrugged again. “The closest we’ve ever had has been the bottle, I think, or maybe … the time chamber.”

“Are there any movies that give you that feeling of home?” asked Amaryllis. “Or books?”

I thought about it for a bit. It was a transparent ploy to change the subject, but I didn’t mind. “Books, definitely,” I replied. “Harry Potter, at least the early books. I really should talk with Valencia about them, the next time I see her. I’m sure she would like that.”

I didn’t stay for the entirety of the dragon disassembly, which was going to take anywhere from days to weeks, with the final sale of everything we weren’t going to keep taking even longer. It felt nice to have some alone time with Amaryllis though, before I had to go back to deal with the bigger stuff.

Even just taking a census of all the people in the underground portion of Necrolaborem would have been the work of hundreds of people going non-stop for a month. Organizing and implementing that census would have taken weeks, maybe more, because it would have to include training for all the census-takers, printing off any necessary materials, recruiting the people necessary to do it — a census was a complicated thing, but it was just a count of people, sometimes with vital stats about them. It still would have been a complete pain in the ass, even if we’d been doing a census with a compliant population who knew what was going on and consented to it all.

Instead, we were dealing with an enormous population that was hardly liable to greet us as liberators, who had been raised and educated in a completely fucked up society created by someone I was comfortable labeling a narcissistic sociopath. We were going to have a somewhat difficult time making sure that all of them could stay alive, nevermind getting them the kind of deprogramming and therapy they would almost assuredly need, nevermind actually turning them into productive members of society. I wouldn’t normally have worried too much about the ‘productive’ bit, but there were millions of them, and I just wasn’t sure that we, or the Empire, could handle supporting them if they weren’t working to support themselves. In an ideal world, I would have just said, ‘okay, the nightmare is over, this is the real world, you’ll have food, healthcare, education, people to talk to, and whatever else you need’, but that didn’t seem possible to me.

Most of the conversation was taking place in the NLEZ, in the palace that we had commandeered, and because I had been away serving my temporary master, I had to be brought up to speed on things. For the most part, we were still in fact-finding mode, trying to pin down the scope of the problem and the constraints we were working under. The crew, minus myself, had done a few forays into the complex in order to verify what little Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle had in the way of numbers, and found that it mostly checked out (though we had a hard time believing that he really kept his records so sparse).

“Seems to me our best shot of getting out of this is to find whatever resistance movement has been brewing just beyond the Captain’s reach,” I said, once I had gotten briefed.

“Ah,” said Amaryllis. “When has propping up the mujahideen ever backfired?”

She said it sarcastically, and I raised an eyebrow. “Not familiar,” I said.

She stared at me like I’d grown a second head. “Are you fucking serious?” she asked.

I looked at Grak and then Raven. Grak seemed just as clueless as I did, but Raven’s lips were set in a sour frown. It seemed unfair that I didn’t know, given how high my KNO was: I should have known pretty much anything that was common knowledge on Aerb, in my opinion, and most things that were uncommon knowledge.

“Sorry?” I asked, more of a question than an apology.

“The mujahideen were a resistance group,” said Amaryllis. “It was a proxy war, and they were given some training and assistance by a major player. The enemy of my enemy is my friend of convenience, yes? So after something like two decades and hundreds of millions spent, the mujahideen managed to more or less win, and it was at that point that it stopped being convenient. Unfortunately, the problem with using the enemy of your enemy is that after you’ve destroyed a mutual target, you’re no longer friends of convenience, and you’re not necessarily aligned. Go ahead, ask me what the mujahideen did that was so bad.”

“Uh,” I said. I really had no idea why this was getting her riled up. Amaryllis was perfectly capable of masking her emotions, and if she was being forthright in her anger, I must really have stepped in it. “What did they do that was so bad?”

Amaryllis looked me dead in the eyes. “On September 11th, 2001, they flew some planes into the World Trade Center.”

I stared at her for a moment. “Alright,” I said. “I’ll cop to not knowing very much about the Middle East.” I didn’t know enough to challenge her narrative, that was for sure.

“Didn’t your father go to war in the Middle East?” asked Grak.

“He did,” I replied. “Gulf War I. But — look, lets not get bogged down in a few gaps in my knowledge about Earth.”

“Wait,” said Raven, “Don’t you literally have an entire expression about that event? ‘Never forget’?”

I looked between Raven and Amaryllis. “I mean, if you’re saying that Osama bin Laden was given money by the CIA — is that what you’re saying?”

“That’s more of a history lesson than we have time for,” said Amaryllis. “The point wasn’t actually about those attacks, or the wars that, by some idiot logic, followed them, it was about how allies of convenience can become incredibly inconvenient. It was a lot more pithy before it needed exposition.”

“I don’t want to argue that the United States ever engaged in great foreign policy, that’s probably a losing battle,” I said. “The question is what the foreign policy of Miunun should look like, with this specific case as a microcosm. Starting with the people who hated Blue-in-the-Bottle and dreamed of freedom seems like a better starting point than, I don’t know, sycophants who never saw anything wrong with their way of life. And at some point, if there is a pre-existing resistance movement, we’ll probably have to grapple with them anyway.”

“So, no democracy then?” asked Grak.

“Lord no,” snorted Amaryllis. “Self-governance is important from both a pragmatic and ethical standpoint, but the form that self-governance should take is absolutely not democratic elections, or worse, direct democracy. Take the temperature of the room, sure, but we’re not going to foist a new system of governance on these people from the word go, and certainly not one that only works, when it does, with an educated and culturally cohesive population, which this is not.”

“Er,” I said. I sometimes forgot that Amaryllis was royalty, not that it necessarily impacted her views too much. She didn’t come from a place that put any particular value on democratic rule though, aside from the risk that the populace would break out the guillotines. “Okay, well, we need to do a full survey of what conditions are like, through all the different partitioned cities. We go in, talk to some people about what their lives are like, what they think, and try to go from there. We can read through all the spreadsheets and memorandums that we want, but that’s never going to be a substitute for actually talking to people, especially when Blue-in-the-Bottle might have faked … pretty much anything.” None of us trusted his accounting of things.

“And the Captain himself?” asked Raven.

“We use him, then … my instinct is to kill him,” I said. “No use in keeping someone dangerous alive. Some of it is going to depend on what his former subjects want. We don’t want to make a martyr, but we also don’t want to leave open a chance for him to return.”

Amaryllis nodded. “We’ll have the Empire’s help, for what it’s worth. OIDR has been called in, even though it’s technically outside their purview, and they’re already under stress. And we’ll have the tuung, en masse. Damage to our buildings in Poran was minimal, and I’ve made arrangements for the second generation.”

“Wait,” I said. “What? I’m on the second generation planning committee. What do you mean you’ve made arrangements?”

“I still need to talk to the committee about it, as do you, and obviously it won’t go forward without buy-in from the tuung themselves, who will be the ones doing the teaching,” said Amaryllis. “The arrangements I was speaking of were done with Bethel and Valencia.”

I frowned. “When?”

“I have a clone with them,” Amaryllis said with a sigh. “I live in a small apartment down the road from Bethel, not close enough that I’m within her sphere of influence. Valencia thought that it would be best if we could reintroduce and re-integrate slowly, and this way, we can have a better line of communication.”

“Oh,” I said. It made me feel a little queasy. I didn’t like the idea of Amaryllis being in trouble, not so far away, not when she was deprived of her magic. I didn’t begrudge her not mentioning it to me: I wouldn’t have disagreed with the decision, and all knowing would do would be to make me worry for nothing. “Well, be careful.”

“I think Val should come here,” said Amaryllis. “She’s the best person to vet people that we know, and if we have any hope of constructing a functional government for these people, we’re going to need a solid foundation, which comes from having good people more than good laws. That said, we’ll also need good laws so that the good people aren’t swept out by the legal and political structures we lay down.”

“Where does that leave Bethel, if Val is here?” I asked.

“With a small amount of independence,” replied Amaryllis. “I trust Val to know whether or not leaving her with that independence is wise, and she’s given the all clear, at least on this trial basis.” She was watching me carefully.

“Sure,” I replied.

“Can Valencia be trusted?” asked Raven. “Not to put too fine a point on it, but it was my understanding there have been problems in the past.” Raven and Fenn had never even met, which was weird to think about.

“Valencia hand-selected the entire teaching staff for the first generation,” said Amaryllis. “She vetted the tuung for positions of power and authority. She has a better track record than almost anyone at exactly the kind of problem we’re currently trying to unravel.”

“One part of the problem,” said Grak. “There is also the issue of food. It is all supplied by zombies at the moment.”

“Right,” said Amaryllis. “Barren bread is a possibility in the short term, though even then, it’s a tremendous cost and logistical problem, which would apply even if we set up our own operations in Barren Jewel with a direct line to Necrolaborem or wherever we end up settling these people. Narratively, that would be a good way to revisit an old location.” She was deep in thought, not really looking at anyone. “The other option is harvesting directly from the plane of flesh, which would take an enormous amount of labor and capital, but might provide better returns.”

“The Second Empire tried it,” said Raven, already shaking her head. “There was an imperial-funded project that attempted extraction from all the closer elemental planes. Flesh was promising, but in practice, the continued efforts of star mages to keep the portal open, the bottlenecks of the flesh mines, and the poor quality of what was taken out, all led to it being closed. It was also tried during the First Empire, somewhat more successfully, by a group of dragons that needed enormous quantities of meat, but it wasn’t sustainable.”

“We have Juniper,” said Amaryllis. “Narratively, it wouldn’t make sense to embark on the plan unless he was a key component anyway.”

“Stop bringing up narrative,” I said. I was still a little pissed off about the mujahideen thing, because I really desperately needed to read a book on the subject of the American involvement in the Middle East, or if not a book, then at least a print out of a Wikipedia article. I wasn’t angry, I just had that salty feeling that I got after losing at a game, the kind of low-key anger that needs to be managed.

“Narrative isn’t driving us, but it needs consideration,” said Amaryllis. “Let me ask you this: if you were a Dungeon Master and you included something like this in a game, what would the point of it be? How would you resolve it? What solutions would you accept from players attempting to resolve it?” She waited a tick after each of those questions, but I didn’t jump at any answers.

“Uh,” I said. “Alright, if this were me, and I put my players in a situation like this, it would probably be because I was in a bad mood, or in a funk, or something like that. And if I was aware of that, I would go along with whatever solution the players thought up so long as it wasn’t shit, because I wouldn’t want to mire them in depressing reality for too long. If I didn’t realize what I was doing, or if I was just being an exceptional asshole, I would rub their nose in it.” I sighed. “Does that help?”

“So a portal to the elemental plane of flesh as a long-term way of feeding people, yay or nay?” asked Amaryllis.

“I mean, it’s cool,” I said. “The fact that no one has done it, or worse, that someone has done it and found it unprofitable, does raise an eyebrow though.”

Grak gave a polite cough. “One might question the idea of doing what the Second Empire did,” he said. “Especially if you are saying you will implement those schemes better.”

“Eh,” I said. “I don’t know if that argument is germane. It’s definitely in line with what I know about the Second Empire’s, but yeah, the Second Empire sucked in a lot of ways, and most of that was down to ideology, which we don’t share with them.”

“Which you and Amaryllis mostly don’t share with them,” said Raven.

“We’re explicitly talking about self-governance here,” I said. “Wasn’t one of the central tenets of the Second Empire, ‘we know better’? We’re not saying that.”

“Not a tenet, no,” said Raven. “But a natural consequence of their tenets, yes.”

“We do know better, though,” said Amaryllis, folding her arms. “We have not just the entirety of Aerb’s history, but the entire history of Earth as well, and the assistance of Valencia.”

“We’re talking too broadly,” I said. “And we really need to be considering the people down there.” I was still feeling the weight of it, and all this abstract discussion wasn’t helping me. “Step one — wait, no, step zero is ensuring basic needs are met, which includes food, water, sanitation, and making sure that Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle doesn’t mobilize against them, all that in the short term, before we could even think about a portal. Then step one is ensuring that there’s a proper organization to this huge mass of people, because we can’t do anything without an org structure, even if it’s just a temporary one. From there, we can think about transitioning the population to somewhere that’s not a utilitarian underground bunker, or creating a proper government, or helping them to help themselves, or the food crisis that’s going to hit if we don’t have a solution. But since we’re likely to uncover things that might change the conversation, better to have that conversation later and focus on the groundwork now.”

Loyalty increased: Amaryllis lvl 27!

Loyalty increased: Raven lvl 5!

I took that as a good sign, but it did very little to lift my spirits. There was too much work to do.

Post

“What is this?” asked Amaryllis when I placed the uniform down on the table. It took her a moment to find the patches, and when she did, she stared at them for a moment, then looked at me.

“I have theories,” I said. “The top theory is that someone from Earth came to Aerb, not through a dream-skewer, but through some actual, physical means. And if I had to guess what that was, then given this outfit, I think it’s probably the one major campaign that I’ve never seen much sign of on Aerb, the Long Stairs. And if I had to guess where the Long Stairs are, then yeah, I would say that’s the dimensional tunnel in Fel Seed’s zone.”

Raven and Amaryllis stared at me.

“That doesn’t make sense,” said Raven.

“There are holes in the theory,” I replied. They were holes that I thought could be patched. “Which one, to you, is the biggest?”

“Sorry,” she said, rubbing her face. “Can you describe the Long Stairs again?”

“There was a forum post, on the internet,” I said. “It was for a setting idea, which was, basically, that when the first nukes went off in New Mexico or wherever, it opened up a rift to another world, a gigadungeon without any end, twisting and warping itself so that it was unmappable, filled to the brim with monsters and traps, with the military of the United States going in to clear it … it was one of those things where I read it, and then had a bunch of ideas that were different than the direction other people wanted to take it, so I just went off and built it on my own, and ran my players through it, taking from a lot of different sources, like the SCP Foundation. The short version is that I moved it to Oregon, dropped the nuclear weapons thing, invented a backstory for this facility, invented a component of the armed forces dedicated to studying, exploring, and exploiting it, invented monsters, features, things like that. It was a thresher by design, diegetically and non-diegetically. And it got worse once Arthur died.”

Amaryllis was still staring at the flag. “It can’t go to Earth.”

“Well,” I said. “It can’t go to my Earth, unless, unknown to me, there really was a facility in Oregon, which my campaign just happened to create a close-enough version of. Or maybe the Long Stairs go to Earth in some other way, or —”

“Why would Uther not tell anyone?” asked Raven.

“I have no fucking idea,” I said. “Why didn’t he ever tell anyone that he was really from Earth? I can make a bunch of uneducated guesses, but there are a lot of questions that I’m ready to ask him if we ever find him.”

“You put forward a theory with lots of inference,” said Amaryllis. She was examining the patch up close. She looked up at me. “You know that we have access to an entad that could make something exactly like this?”

“Do you think that’s likely?” I asked. “That Uther had an entad like the backpack, which he used to make this, and then put it into a hidden closet in a faraway castle, where it lay, forgotten? Honestly, he wouldn’t even need to use an entad, he could just do some sewing.”

“But why would he place it there, if it’s real?” asked Amaryllis.

“Proximity,” said Raven. “By ley line, Glassy Fields and Fel Seed aren’t far from each other.” She had a far-off look on her face. “I’m trying to place this in the timeline. That castle is in Terrormoor, or was before the exclusion, and he didn’t have that property until 22 FE. That’s the lower bound, unless he acquired it and then moved it later, though that would mean the proximity explanation doesn’t hold.”

“Are you taking this seriously?” asked Amaryllis.

“It’s the answer you were looking for,” replied Raven. She hadn’t touched the uniform, conspicuously hadn’t touched it, like it was radioactive, or laced with poison.

“Maybe,” said Amaryllis, frowning a bit. She looked up at me. “Does this help us at all?”

“In the scheme of things, no,” I replied. “If true, which it probably is, I think it tells us where Uther was going, and I think it’s not hard to understand why.”

“Conceptually, the Long Stairs are infinite, aren’t they?” asked Amaryllis.

“As I designed them … yes, no, it’s hard to say. My personal version of the Long Stairs, which is the direction I think this points, was inspired by this game called Rogue Legacy, which — sorry, computer game, a, uh, platformer — the map was randomly generated, but it was random within bounds. You would always know that this particular section would be north of that particular section, and even though it was different every time, you’d get some sense of where things were in relation to each other. There was a directionality to the gigadungeon, and if you thought of the individual rooms and hallways like node traversal on a huge graph, you could go ‘deeper’, toward where magic and threats were stronger. There were ‘stations’, usually cities with their own hostility and rules, places that you would come across on your way ‘down’.” I paused. “How much of this do you have in your notes already?”

“I’ll have to look,” replied Amaryllis. “I think I was focused more on the phenomena that were in that campaign, rather than the physical structure of the place. The notes are in Sable, I’ll put an Amaryllis on it next time I merge with Prime.”

“You’re not?” asked Raven.

“No,” said Amaryllis, shaking her head. “Prime is dealing with logistics right now. We’ll merge soon though, and I’ll do some other merges to put scholarselves on the Long Stairs, now that we suspect that it might actually be important. I don’t think that it substantially changes anything though, considering that to get there, we would still have to go into Fel Seed’s zone, and if not defeat him, then at least get past him.”

“It means we have a better idea of how to prepare,” I said. “And we have some idea of what we’re getting into.”

“And what we’d be getting into is bad?” asked Raven.

“I don’t know,” I said. “I mean, yes, it’s bad, but the Long Stairs weren’t meant for someone of my power, they were relatively low-magic. Actually, that directionality was a part of it, with magic increasing as you went down, so … I guess if the Long Stairs were woven into the patchwork of Aerb, and Aerb was the endpoint, then it would get easier as you went along a path back to Earth? Meaning that all the challenge was front-loaded, which is, uh, not how things are usually done.”

“But if we accept all this,” said Amaryllis. “That would mean that this specific uniform came down the Long Stairs by way of Earth, and then — it would be around the year 2500 there?”

“You might think that, yeah,” I said. “But my guess is that it’s Narnia rules, and if we came waltzing out of the Long Stairs at the facility in Oregon, and by some miracle we’re not immediately shot by the military forces there — I guess they have a policy of containment and analysis, but either way — Narnia rules would mean almost no time would have passed.”

“It can’t be Earth though,” said Amaryllis.

“Why?” I asked. I somehow felt like we should have been on different sides of this conversation.

“No, I understand,” she replied. “If the Dungeon Master is capable of creating Aerb, then he’s also capable of creating Earth, but — there has to be a higher level of reality.”

“No, there doesn’t,” I said. “Not one that’s accessible to us, anyway.”

“But what would it mean?” asked Amaryllis. “It would be one thing to dangle Earth in front of us, but to make an Earth that’s clearly under his dominion — if there’s something like godhood waiting for you at the end of this, would you be god of Earth as well?”

“Ugh, I hope not,” I replied. “I mean, on the object level, yes, I would prefer that Earth had a nice, loving, caring god, rather than no god at all, or, I guess … the Dungeon Master as a god.” I frowned. “Ah fuck, that would mean that the Christians were right all along.”

“We’re getting ahead of ourselves,” said Raven. “We don’t know what this means.”

“If going to Glassy Fields was a prayer, or a weird form of pilgrimage, then this was the answer,” I said, gesturing at the uniform and its conspicuous flag. “It’s a clear message saying that we can continue, full steam ahead.”

“Or it was sitting there all along, waiting to be found,” said Raven. “How many times now have you come across another thread that points back at an existing plot point that you already covered?”

“Lots,” I said. “And sure, that’s possible. But this isn’t actually pointing back at anything, it’s a uniform, nothing more, it wouldn’t be able to point us at the dimensional tunnel or Fel Seed.”

“That’s not technically true,” said Raven. “There’s an entad that can help track the worldline of any object.”

“Fine,” I replied. “Where and how can I get it?”

“I don’t think we need to,” said Amaryllis. “Where else would this uniform be from? Some wholly different line of quests?”

“The Long Stairs could be somewhere else,” replied Raven. “What’s the rationale for thinking that Uther left to go back to Earth?”

“He was fed up,” I replied. “He was done with the narrative and trying to end it. What more justification did he need?”

“He’d have been abandoning billions,” said Raven. “It might have been one thing if he was going to Earth for some purpose, if there was power there for him to grab, or some way to help Aerb, but we’ve seen nothing to show that’s true. The Uther that I knew — to say that he left because he’d declared victory? Or because he was homesick for a place he never once uttered a word of to anyone, somewhere he’d been gone from for forty years? He had a wife and three children.”

“We’ll get answers when we meet him,” I said. Nothing about her tone had been suspect, but taken together, the words held a lot of emotion. Raven still didn’t want to believe bad things about Uther, which I could empathize with, even if the weight of evidence seemed decidedly against him. What he’d done to Bethel, the murder of Vervain, the ways that he might have set in motion plots of misery for his companions in an effort to cultivate stories, it all cast an enormous shadow on a man who was often talked about with the reverence of an immortal god-king. Even if she believed all the points against him though, I wasn’t sure that the object-level truth would be enough. “Arthur, as I knew him, was pretty far from perfect. And as for Uther, he spent three full years of the Dark Lord’s reign being an actor, or maybe not even that, maybe just someone who traveled with the troupe. He wore himself down, doing what he did. The cracks definitely showed. I don’t know how or why he might have thought that going to Earth would solve things, but —”

“It’s the hero’s journey,” said Amaryllis. “The final part of the monomyth is the hero returning home.”

“Oh,” I said. “Right. And if you were the author of Degenerate Cycles, then you would probably fixate on that particular aspect, and if you found a way to go home, or a place that looked like home if you squinted at it just right … well, you would see that as the obvious endpoint of your adventure.” I looked at Raven. “Right?”

“Amaryllis has made the argument before,” Raven replied, lips thin.

“In any case,” I said. “I don’t think it changes anything. I can do another debrief on the Long Stairs campaign, if you think it will help, but if that’s what the dimensional tunnel is, then we still need to get there, which is a major fucking problem, because Fel Seed is in the way.”

“How sure are you of the Narnia conjecture?” asked Raven.

“The — what?” I asked.

“That time flows more slowly on Earth,” replied Raven.

“I’m not at all sure,” I replied. “But of the theories that we have for what the frick is going on, I think it’s fairly solid. I mean … the whole of Earth being on a roughly similar fictional level to Aerb actually resolves some questions that I had, like how some far-future civilization would be able to reconstruct Arthur once his brain was in the dirt. For me it made sense, because maybe at some point in the future my brain could be preserved, or this was some kind of reconstruction or regression built off of some later version of myself, but no, it ties things up neatly.”

“Except that then we have no idea what base reality looks like,” said Amaryllis. “That should alarm everybody.”

“If there even is a base reality,” I said. “Which there might not be.” I waved a hand. “Try not to get too bogged down in it, or if you’re going to, get a clone to do it.”

“Will do,” replied Amaryllis.

“I’m going to go speak with the tuung some more, if I’ve gotten a reprieve from the mandatory gold rush for a bit,” I said. “Let me know if there’s another mission.”

I flew off without waiting too long. It seemed like things with Raven were going to have to come to a head sooner than later, and I wasn’t looking forward to it.

Valencia, Grak, and an Amaryllis were gathered in the underground bunker, which sat in the heart of the complex at Necrolaborem. The room had been cleared of zombies, leaving just Blue-in-the-Bottle there, and he was behind thick wards that blocked his sight almost completely (which was obvious to me because I could see through his eyes).

“It’s not quite him,” Valencia said to me as soon as I came in.

“You should let me confirm that the wards are up first,” Grak grumbled.

“I know, from looking at you, that you’re confident in your warding,” said Valencia. “If you weren’t confident, I would have waited.”

“What do you mean it’s not him?” I asked.

“She means that she’s seen into Blue-in-the-Bottle’s soul and confirmed to herself that it’s not him,” said Grak. “The magical signature says otherwise, and the report from the Dorises does too.”

“Hang on,” I said. “What do you mean, ‘not him’?” I asked. “I mean, he’s not Blue-in-the-Bottle?”

“He might be,” said Valencia. “But the wards don’t contain him in some way. It’s him, but not the whole of him, in some way.”

“On what basis?” asked Grak.

“I don’t know that,” replied Valencia. “Amaryllis wanted me to come in here and see if I could pick up anything from him, so I did that. What I picked up was a level of unconcern that does not fit with everything else I know about him. He knows that he’s too valuable to kill, but he also has cards left to play in case we decide to kill him. We’re at least one contingency removed from having him backed into a corner, possibly two or three contingencies.”

“So you don’t know for certain that it’s not him?” I asked.

“No, I don’t,” replied Valencia. “But that’s what my considerable skill is telling me. If it is him, then he has some backup plan in case he dies.”

Grak frowned. “If that’s true,” he began, then thought about it for a bit. “It would have to be independent of his current body. Or only possible through some non-necromantic magic. Or not strictly linked to him in a way that’s detectable to me, which could hold off on activation while he’s wrapped in very complete wards.”

“Alright,” I said with a sigh. “This fuckin’ guy. Val, can you, I don’t know, interrogate him, get him to tell you all about what he’s actually up to?”

“I can,” she nodded. “I do have to warn you that it’s not going to be easy, given that it’s mediated by zombies. There will also be some risk if we can’t bottle him before he goes to the hells. If he did end up there, they would interrogate him, and it’s possible that they would get some understanding of who you are and who I am. Which would be bad.”

“Sure,” I said. “I trust your judgment.”

“You do?” asked Valencia, brightening.

I nodded. “You’re the subject matter expert. I would never second-guess Grak on wards. And … look, I’ve been practicing my forgiveness. The stuff with Fenn — so long as you understand my point of view, so long as you’ve changed the way you operate — at a certain point you just have to say that the past is the past, and the future will be the future. Because I really have missed you.”

Valencia beamed at me, and came in for a hug, which I accepted.

“Okay,” she said as she pulled away, looking at Blue-in-the-Bottle. “Time to see if I can crack him. No promises. Grak?”

Grak went over to the wards and removed some of them, allowing Valencia to speak with our captive. He had a single zombie standing next to him, helping him to speak.

“Who are you?” asked Elisha Blue, speaking through the zombie.

“Valencia the Red,” replied Valencia. “I’m the Republic of Miunun’s expert on large-scale logistics, my apologies for taking so long to come here.” I was mildly surprised that she hadn’t used a pseudonym, but she was a known quantity on Miunun, so I supposed it made sense.

“Ah, I see,” replied Blue, voice nearly monotone.

“I hope you’re not put off by the body,” said Valencia, gesturing to herself. “It’s a form I wear for convenience, though not much suited to the current moment. My day-to-day life, up to this point, has not involved particularly much in the way of house calls.”

She was putting on a voice and lying seamlessly. I was out of Blue’s view, and that of his zombie, and couldn’t see through Valencia’s eyes, but I had very little doubt that whatever her gambit was, he was buying it.

“You’re of the Second Empire,” said Blue. “You escaped the calamity and the purges?”

“No,” replied Valencia. “I’m second generation, sprefwent, the son of a stripped soul mage. Kershint Hellim, if the name means anything to you?”

Blue-in-the-Bottle’s zombie shook its head. “I never had the pleasure. You’ve come to talk logistics?”

“It’s the primary concern at the moment,” replied Valencia. “From their perspective, they want to ensure as much continued quality of life for the people who live here, while weaning off zombie labor.”

“I’ve been curious about that myself,” replied Blue-in-the-Bottle. “There are too many mouths to feed and not enough hands to pick up the work of harvesting kear.”

“That aside, you have processes and systems in place in order to handle distribution,” said Valencia. “The question is how best to take the reins from you and keep those pipelines flowing. From what you’ve told my associates, all of the movement of goods is accomplished by zombies through systems that you have set up but do not actually maintain.”

There was a moment of silence. “Do you doubt me?” he asked.

“No,” replied Valencia. “The scale of operations is too large for you to be handling everything by yourself, which means that the zombies must necessarily have some level of autonomy. Modern organizational structures are premised on a chain or matrix of command and reporting, but there’s no particular reason that you would be bound by that. The question is how things have been set up, how they can be altered, and how they can be replaced.”

“Replaced?” asked Blue. His zombie gave a small laugh. “They cannot be. A zombie can and does work continuously, without need for rest. To replace a zombie with a human would introduce all manner of logistical complications. Three humans working eight hour shifts would need changes of clothes, they would use hallways to return home, they would need resources that are not available at the kear sites. Each of those three humans would require training, and could hardly be counted upon to be as efficient, so you would need work crews rather than a rotating shift, and that’s simply to account for the replacement of a single zombie.” I could feel, more than see, a smile spread across his face. “I am, of course, ready and willing to help with whatever solutions to this dilemma your team can come up with.”

“Had you ever made plans for evacuation?” asked Valencia.

“Of the populace?” asked Blue. “No. The only things that would threaten us are attacks from outside and earthquakes, and we’re in a particularly stable region. There are, in fact, colonies that are nearly completely disconnected from the outside world, their initial shafts disconnected from the surface, with transport done almost entirely via teleportation.”

“That’s rather inconvenient,” replied Valencia. “It would also make replacement of labor much more difficult.”

“It would,” nodded Blue-in-the-Bottle’s zombie. “It is a fallacy of the propaganda against me that zombies are, simply, a replacement for human workers, alike in all regards aside from the fact that one is alive and the other dead. There are considerable advantages to necromancy which must be accounted for, and which will make disassembly of this nation quite a bit more difficult than if I had mere ‘slaves’.”

“There is some talk of simply murdering you and letting the whole enterprise go to rot,” said Valencia. “It’s not a particularly popular stance, given the times, but I have little doubt it’s what the Second Empire would have done, and in my view, they would have had the right of it.”

“The Empire of Common Cause would never go for it,” replied Blue-in-the-Bottle. He sounded smug, even speaking through a zombie.

“Oh, of course not,” replied Valencia. “But you’re certainly familiar with the moralists and how they operate. If you were killed, and your zombies with you, and there were some problems with even finding all the people you have hidden down here, let alone taking them out, then the Third Empire would wash their hands of the deaths easily enough. Or, perhaps, they might stage an investigation that would find a scapegoat of one kind or another, with the majority of the blame falling on you. The result would be that almost everyone involved would feel good about themselves, and the deaths of millions would be swept to the side with people breathing a guilty sigh of relief.”

“Is that a threat?” asked Blue-in-the-Bottle. His zombie’s eyes narrowed, but his face was still.

“Oh my, no,” replied Valencia. “The people I work with are moralists, and for the time being, they’re in charge. I’d be a fool to threaten something that my colleagues wouldn’t follow through on. I don’t even mean to point out that you’re in a precarious position, because I don’t particularly think that’s true. You have all those irreplaceable zombies as leverage, their labor, even now, helping you immensely. My guess is that the logistics will never be worked out, not with the costs involved, and that will mean that at least for the basics, food, water, washing, cleaning, and so on, we’ll need your undead labor. Obviously the pregnancies will be stopped, no more new zombies will be made, and the existing cohorts of children will be placed into the world with some socialization and training. That will take twenty years though, minimum, and I believe you’re secure until then, though my companions would desperately like to hear otherwise.”

“And after that twenty years?” asked Blue-in-the-Bottle.

“The world will probably end long before then, one way or another,” Valencia replied with a shrug.

“It will?” asked Blue-in-the-Bottle. I could only hear a twinge of emotion, but that twinge was fear and confusion.

“‘Ever onward, against the dark’,” replied Valencia. “The dark is coming for us, and if we manage to defeat it, it will be for good, the final victory that the Second Empire always dreamed of. The moralists are distracted by this current crisis, which is a shame, because these lives are ultimately meaningless in comparison with the fate of all sapients.”

“Do I know you?” asked Blue-in-the-Bottle. She was getting to him, I could tell, enticing him, making him curious.

“You knew a mentor of mine,” replied Valencia. “And I’m quite familiar with your work. But if you’ll excuse me for a moment, my companions have found some of this conversation quite troubling, so I must adjourn to assuage their petty morals.”

She stepped out from behind the wards and moved over to us.

“How did that go?” asked Amaryllis.

“He’s definitely got another body,” said Valencia. “But my guess is that it’s a single factor of backup, even if there are multiples of it. One method of coming back, multiplied. He’s playing it relatively cool, but he’s on the back foot. Disaffection is his strategy, pretending that he has us dead to rights, but he knows that it won’t be a winning move in the long term. He’s made active efforts to sabotage his operations so that reform and rescue will be extremely expensive, if not outright impossible, but I think he underestimates us. He’s been lying, sometimes to himself, other times with what he’d characterize as understandable ‘fibs’. He will do whatever it takes in order to extend his own life, and believes that when push comes to shove, almost everyone else in the world is the same, which is clearly nonsense. Let me know if there’s any more insight you need, I think I have a fairly good read on him. This is little more than confirmation of what we’d already expected.”

“Where would the other body be?” I asked. “I mean, it seems like he has a phylactery, right?”

“I am not convinced that such a thing exists,” said Grak, folding his arms.

“But if it did exist?” I asked. “Like, assuming for a second such a thing is possible?”

“It would require some unknown property of necromancy, or a specific entad,” said Grak. He seemed to think for a moment. “I can vaguely see Blue’s connections, and I’m capable of severing them. It is possible that if he died in that state, he would not live on. If he did, it would be because there is some necromantic magic that exists apart from his physical form.”

“Which is possible,” I said. “If necromancy is related to spirit in some way, then … I don’t know, this is mostly intuition.”

“Follow it,” said Amaryllis, watching me.

“Traditionally,” I replied. “Traditionally a necromancer hides their phylactery as best they can, so that when they die, they don’t actually die, they get reborn. Right? Or their soul, probably spirit in this case, goes into a new form, or was already stored somewhere for that eventuality. The question we have to ask is where he would put it. My guess is at a site that’s miles from here, a vault that you could only exit from the inside, a place that we’d have to use the Dorises to even find. But if that were the case, then … I don’t know why he would be confident.” I looked at Valencia. “Can you work on him?”

“Of course,” she nodded. “What do you want? He’s already convinced that I’m a fellow traveler, just one that doesn’t really care about him, which he respects.”

“Wait,” I said. I looked over at Amaryllis. “Fuck, I think I have it.”

“Have what?” asked Grak.

“The solution,” I said. “The butler did it.”

“Oh come on,” said Amaryllis. “That can’t be right.”

“Who is the butler?” asked Valencia.

“One of Blue-in-the-Bottle’s hands,” said Amaryllis. “We’ve met him twice.”

“Third time’s the charm, right?” I asked. “It’s him.”

“I have seen nothing from him,” said Grak. “If it’s somehow him, or he is a part of this, then it is cloaked somehow.”

“Here,” I said. “Let’s get him, I’ll show you, it’s dumb.”

“Dumb?” asked Amaryllis.

“If I’m right,” I said. “And if I’m wrong, I can explain it to you.”

It didn’t take long for us to find Terrence, who was looking more pale than he had been before, perhaps because he could see the writing on the wall, or maybe because he knew that we would have questions that he wouldn’t have an easy time answering. I regretted the threats I’d made against him.

“Hi Terrence,” I said. He squirmed under my gaze.

“Hello,” he replied.

“I have some very easy questions for you,” I said.

“Okay,” he replied, swallowing hard.

“First, what’s your last name?” I asked.

“Oh,” he said. “It’s … it’s Terrence, technically, sir.”

“Right,” I said. “Because you’ve got someone in your family who puts surnames first?”

He nodded slowly.

“Of course you do,” I replied. It was reasonably common on Aerb, though not expected here in Necrolaborem, and not necessary for the conclusion I’d already come to.

“Fuck,” said Amaryllis, who had always been pretty quick on the uptake, to put it mildly. “Oh fuck off, that’s moronic.”

“I’m missing something,” said Grak, looking between me and Terrence. It was clear from his face that Terrence knew he was missing something too, he was just staying quiet about it.

“His surname,” I said. “Which he never gave us. It’s Phylac.”

“How did you know that?” asked Terrence, staring at me with wide eyes.

“Phylac Terry,” said Amaryllis with a groan. “That motherfucker.”

Terrence, or Terry, was looking between us. “I’m … sorry?”

“This was a pun?” asked Grak.

“Yup,” I replied. “Not just a pun, but yes, we probably could have solved this whole thing a lot faster if we’d just asked this manservant his name in the first place. Maybe that’s the moral.”

“I,” said Terrence, then seemed like he was debating whether to say it. “I’m a butler, not a manservant.”

“Right,” I replied. “As I said, the butler did it.” It was almost funny.

“What?” he asked.

“Hold him down while I look inside,” I said.

“Wait,” said Valencia. She stepped forward and looked Terrence over. “Terrence, something was done to you by Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle, likely at a very young age. That fear and uncertainty you feel, that you felt long before we came here? We think that we know what’s been driving it. There have been times in your life when you felt different from other people, like you were struggling to follow a script that they seemed to have memorized. If we’re right, we can fix that, but we need to find out whether you’re really as special as we think you are.”

“Okay,” said Terrence, letting out a breath. He rolled up a sleeve and held out his arm to me, then closed his eyes tight, so he wouldn’t have to watch. I gave Valencia a look, but she put her finger to her lips.

It took me some time to get into Terrence’s spirit, given the exclusion of soul magic. Blood magic and bone magic were still available, but I couldn’t get to the soul through them, and neither of them were connected to the spirit directly (or at least, not until they were in active use), meaning that I couldn’t cross the bridges that I was used to. Spirit had its own magical connections though, most obviously to passion magic, and connecting to Terrence was relatively easy once I tried to put myself in his shoes, to think and feel, as best I was able, what he was thinking and feeling.

Once I was in, it was obvious that Blue-in-the-Bottle had, in fact, done something. What, precisely, was not obvious. There were more threads than there should have been, far more, and the more I looked at them, the more it looked like Terrence had a whole second person’s spirit inside of him. He hadn’t acted like it though, and it was the kind of thing I would have expected Valencia to catch, so I was left to delve deeper in order to get an understanding.

Without access to the soul, the spirit was a lot more complicated. I wasn’t exactly flying blind, not quite, but it was harder to make sense of what the individual threads were doing, because I couldn’t reference the soul for more concrete examples. I could tell where threads were touching values, but not what those values were, and I could see interactions with skills in those places where concrete knowledge got turned into reality by way of actual thought. In the programming/computing metaphor I was used to, I was trying to figure out what the code did without having access to the source.

Elisha Blue had figured out a way to access spirit, which for all I knew, might have been a core part of necromancy from the very beginning. That he could do things to a living person was a bit shocking, but his power was such bullshit that I didn’t really question it. He had, after all, had a long time to learn things, especially when he’d had the benefit of necromancers who could do theory but no longer practice.

My best guess, based on what Valencia had said and what I suspected, was that Blue had copied over his spirit, rigging up another dead man’s switch of some kind so that he would take over Terrence. But that didn’t quite make sense to me, because you weren’t just your spirit, you were a combination of spirit, soul, and potentially (in some ways) body. It was true that you could use spirit to do almost anything that soul could do, because it could touch all of the values, but even then, if I assumed that Blue-in-the-Bottle had independently discovered spirit, and that he had become more proficient with it than anyone in the whole world had ever been, then that still wouldn’t have let him extend his life, because Terrence wouldn’t be him, he would just be —

Well, I couldn’t properly argue that it wouldn’t be him, because I didn’t actually believe that, but if I’d been Blue, I would be worried that I wouldn’t come out the other side quite the same. It would also mean that he would lose necromancy, if our understanding of enpersoned exclusions was correct. Maybe he was fine with that though, given that he had been trapped in a depressing country of his own making for hundreds of years, and this, maybe, would be a way out.

I wasn’t sure what would happen if we took Terrence across the border. My guess was that nothing would change, but it was worth trying anyway. If I were Blue-in-the-Bottle, willing to hijack someone like this for my own purposes, then I’d have made the changes I wanted to make with necromancy, however that had been done, then I would make sure that they wouldn’t simply be reversed by going beyond the border. And if he were really clever, he would have figured out some way to collapse or replace Terrence in the event that Terrence left the zone, on top of having one that would activate when Blue died.

“Hrm,” I said, pulling out.

“What’s going on?” asked Amaryllis.

I sculpted vibration magic so that Terrence couldn’t hear me, and faced away from him in case he could, against the odds, read lips.

“There’s something in his spirit,” I said. “It might take some time to figure it out and strip it from him. My guess at this point is that he’s capable of doing this to others as well. At this point, I think we have to assume that he’s been using necromancy to copy himself into other people.”

“By getting to them when they’re technically dead?” asked Amaryllis.

“No idea,” I said. “It would make sense though. And it would give us something to look for, some childhood trauma or surgery that would be the cover for something invasive and necromantic.”

“This would go beyond the borders of the EZ?” asked Grak.

“Maybe,” I said. “Probably.”

“But that would mean that he would be able to send agents out,” said Amaryllis. “He would be able to take a fraction of the people down in his cities and send them out into the world to build organizations, learn magic — do anything.”

“It’s not clear to me that he would,” said Valencia, frowning a bit. “I would have to talk to him more.”

“Why wouldn’t he?” asked Amaryllis. “It’s the logical thing to do. He could fill the world with versions of himself and cooperate in order to set up shell companies on the outside that would distribute his goods. Everyone would win.”

“He doesn’t care if everyone would win,” said Valencia. “He would only care that he wins. It would be about the risks and benefits of this imperfect, difficult duplication.”

“Probably not the time and place to talk about it,” I said. “We should either head back to Blue’s room, or get out from under his presumed panopticon altogether.”

“He’s limited,” said Valencia. “His lack of knowledge has been setting him on edge. He’s placing faith in his planning and preparations, as well as your moralism.”

“Okay,” I said. “Good to know.”

“We need more information,” sighed Amaryllis. “But I think we’re close to cracking this.”

There’s gold near. The voice of the call of gold was eminently unwelcome. Leave the complex, now.

“There’s gold near,” I said. “I need to get going.”

“We’ll handle it as much as we can,” said Amaryllis. “We’ll look for the cracks and follow the breadcrumbs.”

Bureaucratic Melees

An Amaryllis had taken up position next to the manor entrance, which was now a large, burnt hole in the building. They had been lucky that the long elevator was untouched, because it would have complicated descent into the complex if it had been turned to slag. Unfortunately, the dragonfire was a mar on the building, which was, to some of the citizens, a symbol. It would need to be repaired, and it was clear that there would be a lot of work to be done in terms of cosmetic changes to Necrolaborem. Amaryllis was hoping that external repairs could be completed inside a week, so that they could launch a public relations offensive that would tout this as a place transformed. Only one of her would be working on that though, because there were other problems that had more to do with ground truths.

This particular instance of her was idly talking with the tuung, who looked up to her no matter her missteps. Imposter syndrome had never been a particular problem for Amaryllis, which was good, because the culture that she had been the primary architect of placed a fair bit of importance on her. She hadn’t wanted anything like hero worship or a cult of personality, because those were unstable forms of leadership, but she had done her best to weave herself into the lessons that the tuung were given, and during stints in the time chamber, she had devoted a good deal of time to writing to them, mixing personal stories with civics lessons and life advice (though much of the life advice was, frankly, obvious stuff). Aerb didn’t have a term for parasocial relationship, but that was what she’d cultivated, trying her best to be as authentic as possible. She didn’t want to exploit or manipulate in any way that would come back to bite her later.

She had worried a lot about the tuung, given how little time she could devote to their upbringing. She had left them in the hands of people that Valencia had screened, but a devil’s insights were imperfect, and extrapolating how a group of people would work together for years at a time wasn’t something that Valencia had been terribly confident about, even with the check-ins they’d used. The tuung had an unexpected stress test at Li’o, emerging from their indoctrination and training much sooner than planned, all their half-finished training put to a much harsher reckoning than anticipated.

The tuung were, by far, the most successful project of their sort in the entire history of either Aerb or Earth.

This did not mean that they were without their flaws.

“I waited too long to read them,” said Monique. “They weren’t part of the canon, so I set them aside for free reading, and didn’t get to them until last year. But what you wrote in Meditations on Power really changed my perspective on a lot of things, particularly our sexual politics.”

Amaryllis nodded. She remembered Meditations on Power, which was a series of essays she’d written that were largely about power dynamics. They weren’t much more than a collection of pamphlets, and to some extent they repeated things that Amaryllis had read from other sources, a synthesis of Earth and Aerb, with a few thoughts that were likely original thrown in. Altogether, the collection had been the work of spare hours over the course of a week, and Amaryllis hadn’t been too happy with how it had turned out, which had meant that it was left out of ‘the canon’, the set of works that all tuung were expected to read, which expanded as they grew older. Part of how the culture had been structured was with a strong emphasis on community, and ‘the canon’ was a way of ensuring cohesion.

“The tuung are unique in many ways,” said Amaryllis. “There are power dynamics that are etched on your biology. It’s something that I’ve given a lot of thought to.” So far, there had been no un-sanctioned primings, and no sanctioned ones, for that matter, which would change with the second generation. Amaryllis had her fingers crossed that it would remain that way. The penalty for un-sanctioned priming was death, and was one of two crimes that automatically carried that penalty (the other being treason). “How have you been handling it?”

“Oh,” replied Monique. She seemed a bit flustered to have Amaryllis actually respond. “Like you say, there are things about our society that we might find upsetting, burdens we’re forced to shoulder. Inside, I struggled a bit.” ‘Inside’ was what they called their time in Bethel, which accounted for almost the entirety of their life until the last few months. “I thought about the ways that I would have structured society differently, so that the problems wouldn’t happen, but I never came up with anything that really resolved it, other than limiting the number of females in society, since we’re the ones that have most of the burden.”

“I did think about that,” said Amaryllis. Obviously. “But there’s variability in terms of tuung biology, much more than there is in humans, and the spread we chose was based on a crude analysis of the roles we would need to fill. The second generation project is underway, and while I’m a bit worried about changing things too much, we have a better idea of what the ideal social construction looks like given the data we’ve already gathered.”

Monique had been nodding along the whole time, and seemed ready to give a contribution, but before she could, she must have heard something.

“Incoming,” she called out, and the twin fireteams that formed Amaryllis’ guard boxed her in to protect her.

Two seconds later, with a zwrish, six people stepped into being not far from the manor.

Amaryllis dismissed the tuung with a hand signal, and they fanned back out, taking up the most strategically sound positions around her.

“Greetings,” said Amaryllis, stepping forward. She recognized three of the six, and at best guess, all of them were from the empire. “I’ve been waiting for your arrival, there are a number of things we’ll need to discuss in terms of situation management.”

“You’re damned right,” said Elias Satyr, the Captain of the Officer of Imperial Disaster Relief. He looked distinctly unhappy, as did most of the others. It was only the shortest of them, a gnome, that had a grin: Figaro Finch had come along, and he seemed delighted that this was a mess he probably wouldn’t have to clean up.

“Introductions first,” said Alcida Divona, Head of Uniquities. “You obviously know myself, Figaro, and Elias.” She gestured at them with blue hands. She was dressed down from what Amaryllis had seen her wearing before, perhaps because she’d had less time to put on something striking. A broad hat covered her bald head. “I don’t know if you’ve had the pleasure of the others that are joining us, this is Ragusa Allron, Head of Special Threats, Tangli Ferst, from the Accountability Office, and Foster Bragg, who is on loan from the Kingdom of Tern. It’s thought that he’ll be our logistics head, though we’re still working that out.”

They were a motley crew, made of different species and wearing wildly different outfits, with a suit for the gnome, Figaro, a plain, austere dress for the vitric, Alcida, and traditional garb for Ferst and Bragg (Ferst with a sweeping neo-traditionalist dress in orange and white, Bragg with a gray suit which prominently featured a thick wrap around the waist): they were both sharp-beaked likoni. Satyr was wearing entad armor with shifting blue waves on it, and Ragusa Allron, an orc, had on an entad of his own, a long robe studded with twinkling, multi-colored stars.

“And I’m Amaryllis Smith nee Penndraig,” said Amaryllis, when it was clear that she would get no introduction of her own. “I’m a princess of Anglecynn, on several committees there, and Advisor on Industry to the Republic of Miunun.” She was accruing responsibilities and power at a rate that anyone with a brain would find frightening. In Anglecynn, her power was close to unchecked, and it felt like with another month behind her, she would be the de facto ruler.

“Did you kill Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle?” asked Alcida.

“No,” said Amaryllis, hoping that was still true, because, after all, Juniper was down there, and it was very possible that the plot was progressing without her. “Elisha Blue is still alive. He has ceded the entirety of his authority to us and peaceably handed over control of Necrolaborem.”

“Peaceably?” asked Ragusa Allron, looking at the burnt manor.

“The damage there was an unrelated incident,” said Amaryllis.

“I’ll be plain,” said Ragusa, his voice grumbling slightly. “This is a problem.”

“How so?” asked Amaryllis, raising an eyebrow.

“The Empire is stretched thin,” said Satyr. “I mean that in both a material sense and a psychic one. The exclusion in Li’o was a blow, not just because of the disaster and the refugee crisis, but because of how it has impacted people. Since getting word of what’s happened here, we’ve been working together on the broader implications of the fall of Necrolaborem, and there is general agreement that the bad news is coming too fast.”

“By rights, the people of Aerb should rally,” said Amaryllis. “The exclusion is weeks away from being cleared. Within the next twenty-four hours, the zombies he’s held captive as assurance against threats will be defused, leaving only those that are currently vital to the functioning of this society. Within a month, even those will be gone.” That was an extremely optimistic timeline, but the situation seemed to call for optimism.

“And the people?” asked Alcida. “What of them?”

“They’ll be free,” said Amaryllis. “They can form their own society here, their own polity that will initially exist within the footprint of this place. My industries have need for labor at the moment, and in the interim period, while they find their footing, they can add value in that way, which will help to offset the costs of bringing their standard of living up.”

“The optics are bad,” said Ragusa. “Reporters are sure to come, and the radio waves will be filled with talk of the horrors here.”

“Horrors that have come to an end,” said Amaryllis, looking between them. “You cannot honestly be suggesting that the world would have been better off not solving this problem.”

“That’s the feeling,” said Figaro Finch. He pulled a cigarette case and began going through the process of lighting up.

“Well, it’s done,” said Amaryllis. “We’re not leaving and telling Blue that we’re fine with him continuing operations after all.”

“We’re not suggesting that,” replied Ragusa. “But you have no authority here.”

“I do,” said Amaryllis, staring him down.

“You do not,” replied Ragusa.

“Very well,” said Amaryllis, spreading her stance slightly. She took a breath. “In 511 FE, the Empire of Common Cause entered into negotiations with Elisha Blue, granting him status-in-fact authority over the exclusion zone per extant case law, especially with regards to Bolkin. By right of conquest, and his own submission, the Republic of Miunun claims transfer of status-in-fact from Elisha Blue, in accordance with extant case law, especially with regards to Livingston, Coase, and Braithe. Following that, I hereby declare this to be our colonial territory, pursuant to section 409 of the EIC, and grant myself full power as colonial governor. Necrolaborem is now a formal part of the Republic of Miunun, which is an imperial non-member, and it is you who has no authority here, except on my say so. I will grant you permission to stay, and would welcome discussion of the problems that face our colony.”

“Can she do that?” asked Ferst, leaning over slightly to speak with Bragg. “I wasn’t sure that I followed it in its entirety.”

“Special Threats has authority over exclusion zones through the full force of imperial law,” said Ragusa. “You cannot wave that away.”

“We are not a part of the Empire,” said Amaryllis. “And you’re simply incorrect, because for Special Threats to have authority over a polity which has been recognized by the Empire, member or otherwise, requires formal approval by the full legislature.”

“The Empire has formally recognized Miunun,” said Ragusa, shaking his head. “The same cannot be said for this — whatever this is.”

“I gave specific case law,” said Amaryllis, folding her arms. “The only reason that I’m continuing this conversation is because I have dozens of myself working on the actual problems. If you’d like, we can go through the legislature, but as the Republic of Miunun is only a recognized polity, not a member polity, it’s you that has no authority.”

“Let’s be calm here,” said Alcida. Amaryllis had no problem with that, she had only been changing her tone to match the aggression she was seeing. Because of her age, and sometimes also her gender, there was some expectation that she would be deferential. “Can we agree that for the rule of law to work, we cannot have independent parties coming into exclusion zones and taking them over with a show of force?”

“No one else has the capacity to do what we do,” said Amaryllis. “And if they did, I argue it would be a net good for all those involved. We’re saving millions from the hells. We’re removing people from under the thumb of an insane dictator who planned to torture them even after their deaths.”

“There was no discussion with the Empire,” said Satyr. Amaryllis didn’t look at the two people from Uniquities when he said that, because they had definitely known something, and clearly hadn’t communicated it, not that she’d wanted them to. “We cannot absorb half a million people. Given a month’s lead, it might have been possible to build the framework, but as it stands, we don’t have anything in place, especially not after events in Li’o, which are still ongoing.”

“Two things,” said Amaryllis. “First, you can still have a month, if you’d like. Elias Blue is under our thumb. There is no pressing need for intervention at the moment, so far as we can assess that, aside from the general poor conditions. Second, he set up a number of cities beneath the EZ, with a total population somewhere in the range of eight million, most of them children.”

That was met with a moment of silence.

“Eight million?” asked Ragusa.

“As best we can currently tell, yes,” said Amaryllis. “This obviously represents an enormous failure on the part of Special Threats.” Ragusa was the head of Special Threats, and she was making an enemy of him, the better to serve up a head on a platter for the rest of the EoCC. In reality, Ragusa’s hands had probably been tied, and gaining access to top tier surveillance entads had probably not been a priority for his tenure, especially not for something like the NLEZ, which had been somewhat quietly not bothering anyone for many decades. Institutions like Special Threats tended to rot over time, and that couldn’t necessarily be blamed on the person sitting at the head. Perhaps if Amaryllis had been in charge of the department, she would have noticed how old their knowledge was and called for it to be updated, or if not that, she would have hired or trained someone directly in charge of the NLEZ, who could have seen the problem.

Either way, if they were ignorant of the true conditions in the NLEZ, that fell on Ragusa, and if the EoCC needed an institutional villain, rather than just the actual villain, Ragusa was the logical choice.

“I need to speak with those on the ground,” said Ragusa, going slightly pale.

“Of course,” said Amaryllis with a nod. “I’ve been in conversation with them for the past day or so, and have kept them informed. If they didn’t keep you abreast of the facts, I would put that down to the problems inherent in cross-continental communication.” There hadn’t been any manipulation on her part, though she hadn’t offered any advice to the group from Special Threats.

It was at that moment that I arrived on the scene, ignorant of pretty much everything, including the identities of everyone that Amaryllis was talking to. I’d gotten, at most, the last few sentences, and didn’t have enough context. I wasn’t floating, as much as I wanted to be, and I had shifted my armor to be a non-threatening steel.

The gnome has the gold. Get it from him.

I looked at Figaro Finch, who was looking at me with a faint grin.

“Sorry,” I said, walking over. “Figaro, can I talk to you?”

“Who is this?” asked the same man who’d been arguing with Amaryllis.

“Ragusa Allron, this is Juniper Smith, husband to Amaryllis,” said Alcida, stepping forward slightly. “Juniper, this is Ragusa. He’s the head of Special Threats.

Get the gold from the gnome.

“Pleasure to meet you,” I said. “I don’t think I really need to be a part of this conversation though. Figaro?” I raised an expectant eyebrow at him.

“Oh, did you want this?” he asked, pulling a thick gold coin from his pocket. It was comically big in his hands, and clearly had enough sheer weight that he couldn’t hold it casually. “I strongly suspect that Juniper is a gold mage,” he told the crowd.

“That’s dangerous,” said Alcida, frowning.

“And illegal,” said another voice from among them, a tall lodona woman who was chewing something idly.

“The legality is complicated,” said Amaryllis. “We spoke with our lawyers before making the decision. But if we’re speaking of jurisdiction, then surely you have to acknowledge that the only person here with any authority to arrest Juniper is Figaro Finch.”

Take the gold, now.

“I decline to attempt the arrest,” said Figaro Finch. “Here, you’re looking pale.” He tossed the coin to me, and I caught it. My heart was thumping. I’d been pretty nervous about just taking the gold from him. I had no clue why he’d brought a gold coin with, and assumed that he’d kept it in extradimensional storage until the time was right. If it was to out me as a gold mage, then it was a dick move.

“How much gold does he have?” asked Alcida, looking at me.

I looked to Amaryllis, and she gave me a nod.

“Roughly a hundred million obols worth,” I replied.

There were two reactions to that, the first being confusion, because it was probably difficult to figure out what that meant in terms of raw power, and the second being astonishment at the sheer cost and power.

“Why?” asked Alcida.

I looked at Amaryllis again, and she hesitated a moment before nodding. “I had to kill some dragons.”

“I was going to get to that,” said Amaryllis. “But to be fair, if you had adequate intelligence networks, you would have known by now.”

“Multiple dragons?” asked Alcida.

“We need to bring External Affairs into this,” said the lodona woman.

“It was actually just two dragons,” I said. “Multiple dragons makes it sound more impressive than it was.”

“How is he going to sustain that level of power?” asked Alcida.

“I’m not,” I replied.

“Where is the gold?” asked Figaro Finch.

“Nunya,” I replied.

“Nunya?” he asked, that fool, that absolute moron.

“Nunya business,” I continued.

“It’s beside the point,” said Amaryllis, after a moment had passed. “It has virtually nothing to do with the situation at Necrolaborem.” She said that with a straight face, despite the burnt manor behind us.

“I don’t mean to be a bother,” I said. I was intruding on politics, and aside from being outed as a gold mage by Figaro Finch, for whatever asinine reason, I didn’t feel like I had all that much to contribute.

“Stay for a moment,” said Amaryllis. She turned to the others. “Your main force is arriving by train shortly. When does everyone else come? We watched the portal that brought in OIDR, when can that be activated again?”

“Three days,” replied Satyr. “But it’s not clear at this point that we’ll be able to provide much assistance. I could pull my best men off Li’o to lead, but the manpower just isn’t there.”

“And if we can handle that?” asked Amaryllis.

“There would still be the problem of who would be in charge,” said Satyr. “Having a non-member polity command OIDR, or even just set the agenda, would be a dangerous precedent. That’s especially the case because you and your husband are only agreed upon as agents of a non-member polity through a legal fiction. To have Anglecynn commandeer imperial forces in contravention of imperial law is, to put it mildly, troubling.”

Alcida had been nodding along. “Yet I think there are arguments to be made,” she replied. “It was no mistake that Uniquities was included in this working group. When circumstances are unique, we are the ones who have dispensation to do what must be done. However this intervention is structured, we would serve as intermediaries.”

“That leaves the question of manpower,” said Satyr.

“We’ll have one hundred thousand trained tuung,” said Amaryllis.

“When?” asked Ragusa. “How? Our estimates of your population there were much lower.”

“We’re scaling up,” said Amaryllis. “We’ll still be outnumbered eighty to one, but that will at least be manageable, assuming that we can deputize some fraction of the population.”

“And Blue himself?” asked Ragusa.

“We keep him alive,” said Amaryllis. “Ideally, we would kill him, but I’m perfectly fine with his survival in perpetuity if that will ensure his cooperation.”

“I don’t believe that will be palatable to the people of the Empire,” said Ragusa. “Though I should note that you have no authority to kill the man.”

“That’s beyond the scope of discussion,” Amaryllis replied. “I know that you’re beholden to the legislature, who are in turn beholden to the people, but what matters is helping everyone down there. It’s going to be ugly either way. Clemency for Blue is one of the key ways to make it as pretty as possible.”

I didn’t like that. I also didn’t know whether she was telling the truth. Obviously granting Blue eternal life was a carrot we could dangle in front of him, but actually giving him that carrot at the end of it … blegh. Better not to lie, better not to break your contracts, in part just due to following sensible rules for life, but also because other people might see that you were perfectly willing to go back on your word.

Interrogate Amaryllis on the location of Perisev’s vault. The call of the gold in my head was unwelcome. There were too many requests, coming too fast. I had hoped that I would get a few days between errands, but it didn’t seem like that was going to happen.

I caught Amaryllis’ eye, and began signing to her in Gimb. She signed back before I was even finished with the sentence; apparently, she’d anticipated this and already had a clone at the site, which was four hours' flight away.

“I need to get going,” I said.

“Good seeing you,” said Figaro Finch with a wave.

I nodded, but didn’t make a big deal of my departure, instead floating high up, gathering speed as I went, until I was far enough above that I wouldn’t be splitting eardrums when I applied my full power. Once I was at what I judged was a safe height, I blasted away, using vibration magic to sculpt the shockwave away from the people that were standing down below.

A Dragon's Roost

“We need to talk,” I said as I flew through the air. “You’re supposed to give me a break.”

You couldn’t really carry on a conversation with the call of the gold, at least so far as I’d been able to find. It would give instructions, for some people as a voice in the head, for others as a feeling about what they should do. It knew everything that I knew, along with some things that it knew for itself but hadn’t yet felt the need to share.

“My best guess is that there’s a lot of low-hanging fruit right now,” I said. “The gold inside the glove, definitely easy to grab. The coin from Finch, that too. The materials from the dragon corpses, okay, sure, but I think Amaryllis can be trusted to be honest.” In this particular case, I wouldn’t have cared if she lied to me, and maybe that was why it had been important to check up on her, or show that pressure would apply. That was surprisingly sophisticated reasoning for whatever was on the end of the call. “So if that’s the case, and you’re just having me grab things that are easy to grab, and will slow down after that, then okay, that’s fine. But I can’t keep running errands at this rate. I’ll have to cancel out the contract.”

There was no response. I hadn’t really expected one, though it would have been nice. Absent that conversation, I was more or less on my own, screaming across the sky, alone with my thoughts.

I wanted downtime. I hadn’t seen Val in what felt like a very long time, and I wanted to just hang out, watch some movies, talk about things, and not really think that much about the ways in which the world sucked, and how big a percent of it was my responsibility. I wanted a vacation, and it didn’t seem like I was going to get one, not while I still had the call of the gold active.

The other thing weighing on my mind was Bethel, whose help we were enlisting in order to raise the second generation of tuung. The thought of her still made my heart beat a little faster, and it was becoming a familiar source of anxiety that I kept pushing down, which wasn’t a good thing. The party would probably do their part in keeping us from each other, but that was only a temporary measure, because if we were going to try to sneak past Fel Seed, we would want to have every tool in our toolset.

It probably wouldn’t be as bad as I was building it up in my head. Whenever there were things that were weighing on me, I would think about them and wargame them, imagining all the possible scenarios, all the ways that it could go most wrong. When Tiff and I had been doing our secret dating thing, I’d thought about all the ways that it might blow up in my face, and sometimes I would get a knot in my stomach just thinking about the eventual fallout. When I’d punched Victor Clark, I’d thought that I would get arrested, or expelled, and after I’d had a chance to think about it, to cool down, I’d felt the blood drain from my face. Every time I fucked up, I felt like a weight was pressing down on me.

I was thinking about Bethel in the same way, though I tried hard to convince myself that it wasn’t my fault. In my imagined version of events, she would blame me, or try to extract concessions, or at least make excuses for herself, painting herself as eminently reasonable. It probably wasn’t going to be like that. If Valencia had been able to get any kind of a change in mindset out of her, and had been able to bring about any kind of empathy, then I didn’t know what it would look like, but it would be really unlikely to be the worst case. Maybe she would apologize. Maybe she would voluntarily keep her distance from me, limiting how much we talked to each other, giving me space and time I still apparently needed.

“You know,” I said. “Technically you didn’t tell me to go to Perisev’s, you just told me to ask Amaryllis about it.”

Go to the dragon’s lair, said the call of the gold.

“Alright, fine,” I said. “We have the time, we can have a chat. Surely you’re more complex than just wanting me to mark more and more gold for you. Let’s at least have a discussion of what this relationship is going to look like in the long term.” I didn’t really expect an answer to that.

We will gather all of the gold that is easy to gather and rightfully yours, replied the call of the gold. Once that is done we will venture out to capture gold stores. After that, we will convert any funds or services into permanent sources of gold income, or liquidate those in exchange for gold that cannot be acquired. We will mine out gold from ore. We will acquire all gold on the face of Aerb and Celestar. We will generate new gold through entads and magic. We will open a gate to the plane of gold.

“Huh,” I said. That was a lot more information than I thought I would get. The end goal of opening a portal to the elemental plane of gold was pretty much never going to happen, because it would require lots and lots of star mages working together, or boosting my own skill in star magic, which I couldn’t do now that Essentialism was gone. Portals to the elemental planes were very rarely done, and a portal to the plane of gold was, if not impossible, then so hard that I knew of no successful attempts at it.

I didn’t do a whole lot but think during the trip, though I did briefly stop to pee, which I did while floating two hundred feet above a prairie (and this was a complicated process, given that I was wearing heavy armor). I wondered whether Superman ever did that, and decided that he probably followed the law and found a bathroom somewhere.

I arrived at the mountain just after nightfall. There was a gaping hole in the side of the rockface, large enough for a dragon to make a landing, but next to it was a cable with a car attached, leading down to a village at the base. There, a train snaked out away from the village, through the woods. Some dragons had their own lands, micronations, but others, like Perisev, had some kind of status within a polity, an arrangement that would allow mutual benefits.

I blinked on warder’s sight for a moment, then landed in the mouth of the mountain entrance, doing a small zig-zag once my feet were on the ground to create a marker in my worldline for future teleports.

The mouth of the place was done on a grand scale that couldn’t help but remind me of some of Bethel’s designs. Perisev had been massive, though smaller than Tommul, and her lodgings had been sized to suit her. I was thankful that I had flight and speed, because otherwise, it would have taken a considerable amount of time just to traverse the entryway.

There were no doors, and I floated through, looking around. The tunnels were huge, but must have been just barely wide enough for Perisev. They were unadorned, smoothed-down bare rock, something dark and igneous. Gabbro, maybe, though I had no idea whether that was actually a rock, or what dark recesses of my mind the knowledge was coming from. When there were doorways, they opened out into much larger rooms, but I couldn’t help but feel that the whole place would have been claustrophobic to something the size of Perisev, and wondered whether she’d run up against engineering challenges, or whether this place had been carved out when she was smaller, or if she was just less sensitive to small spaces than I was. There were lights in the ceiling, but they were fairly weak, only bright enough that the corridors and rooms weren’t swallowed up in darkness. They must have been for the benefit of someone else, because dragons could see in pitch black darkness.

Eventually I spotted someone, a young woman who was driving a small cart along the corridors. She didn’t seem to see me, so I called out to her, and she slammed on the brakes so quickly that she almost hit her head on the front of the cart. I landed in front of her, far enough away that I was hoping I didn’t seem like a threat.

“I’m looking for Amaryllis Penndraig,” I said.

“Oh,” said the woman. “Oh, uh, sorry.”

“If you could just point me in the right direction,” I said. “If you know where she is?”

“Oh,” she said again. “I was — yes, I can.” She spun the wheel of the cart and then stopped for a moment. “Did you … need a ride?” Her eyes flickered down to my feet, which moments ago had been high up off the ground.

“Sure,” I said. I climbed over and sat in the seat next to her.

We puttered along in silence for a bit, moving down the corridors of this mountain complex. Up close, I noticed that the smoothness of the stone was glassy in places, and it occurred to me that rather than hollowing out this place in the normal way, Perisev might have come in here with her dragonbreath, though that still left the question of where the molten stone would have gone.

“Are you,” began the woman next to me. “Are you the one who killed her?”

“Oh,” I said. “Yeah.”

“That’s me out of a job, I guess,” said the woman with a nervous laugh. She had a tight grip on the steering wheel. “You kind of expect,” she said, then sat on the silence for a bit. “You expect, when you get a job with a dragon, that it will be for life, that you’ll be a little mayfly, coming and going.”

“Sorry,” I said. “She tried to kill me.”

“Oh,” said the woman. “No, I don’t blame you, she was a dragon, they have their nasty sides, we all knew that.” She cleared her throat. “Not everyone sees it the same. Among the staff, I mean.”

“Alright,” I said.

“I’m just warning you,” she said. “We’re going to have to figure out what to do. We’ll land on our feet, for the most part, but —”

“We’ll try to make sure you’re taken care of,” I said.

“Thank you,” she replied. She let out a low breath, and loosened her grip on the steering wheel, seemingly by conscious effort.

The room we came to was one of the larger ones, and it took a moment for me to realize that it was a stage of all things, built for an audience of perhaps a dozen at the front, and an enormous place for a dragon to sit at the back, near the big opening.

There were nearly thirty people in the room, most of them on the stage. In the middle of the group, looking rather small with the men looming over her, was Amaryllis.

“You’ll have to take it up with the Kingdom of Pellico, which never removed the conquest stipulation in its documents, and which yes, does apply to dragons and applies even in the event that she had made a will, which as you say, she did not,” said Amaryllis. She was calm and resolute, and I felt oddly proud of her. She was a clone, without any magical power or entad support, yet she was here, alone, and holding her own against an enormous amount of pressure.

I stayed at the periphery, watching but not making a move to come closer, unnoticed by anyone in the center of the verbal melee.

“It is not yours to take,” replied a taller man with an impressively long grey beard. “Perisev, the Wretched, made this place what it was, but it represents the blood, sweat, and tears of hundreds, thousands of people over the course of many centuries. You cannot simply come in here and grab it.”

“I’m sorry,” said Amaryllis. “While we lay claim to the entirety of this complex, and all property once held in the name of Perisev, that doesn’t mean we’re going to leave you all homeless or without a safety net, even beyond whatever the Kingdom of Pellico provides. We’ll help pay for relocation, in whatever form that takes. But to be frank, this private retreat, and the community here, cannot survive in its current form.”

The people around her were angry. Whatever they’d had going here, this way of life, was coming to an end, and I could get that. Not everyone was taking it as well as the woman who was still standing next to me. The ones surrounding Amaryllis were the angriest, their rage visible in how they held their bodies. I was sure that there was some grief in there, given that they were Perisev’s staff, and even if they weren’t exactly like family —

One of them clenched his hand into a fist and raised it against Amaryllis. I was watching and waiting, not actually thinking that he was going to, and then I saw Amaryllis close her eyes, as if accepting it.

And then I was there, holding his wrist, with his fist an inch away from her skin. We stayed like that for just a moment, with the wind of my arrival disturbing clothes and blowing back hair.

“Excuse me,” I said. I released his arm. “I didn’t mean to interrupt.”

“I have this, Juniper,” said Amaryllis. She was still staring ahead at the man who had been about to hit her.

“Of course,” I said. “I’ll be nearby. Let me know when you have a moment to chat.” I stepped off the stage, floating above the seats, and switched my armor over to lava mode. The lava had a sound to it, mostly from the way it heated the air, and I amplified the sound, just to give me a bit of presence.

“Let’s all calm down,” said Amaryllis, talking to the man in front of her, but probably also a bit to me. “There’s a power disparity here, we all understand that, but it’s similar to the situation your community has been operating under for its entire existence. The truth is, we can’t keep everything going how it was. We don’t have the voracious desire for stories that Perisev had, we don’t need a theater filled with actors, and we don’t need an oversized retreat. But with that said, we will do everything in our power to make sure that you can have a normal life once the transition period is over.” She looked around, waiting for dissent, then nodded once when there was none. “I need to speak with my husband for a moment, but I’ll be right back to talk about what the transition will look like.”

She stepped out of the crowd and across the stage, then hopped down and began walking through the seats. I descended to meet her, and switched my armor over to iron, which didn’t run the risk of burning everyone.

“Mute us,” she said.

“Already done,” I replied.

“I wasn’t expecting you,” said Amaryllis, looking me over. “I’m actually not sure why you’re here.”

“The call of the gold told me to come,” I replied. “Looking to extract value, I’m guessing. It’s not clear to me whether that’s a good thing.” I wondered whether we would have to go back on the promise of giving these people a cushion.

“I would have been fine,” said Amaryllis. “I saw the hit coming. It would probably have hurt, but it would have been good, on balance. I’m a young woman, and they would feel bad about hurting me, which would help bridge the gap.”

“Sorry,” I said. “I did restrain myself. I could have snapped his arm.” Or worse.

“Why didn’t you?” asked Amaryllis.

“Too much power differential,” I said. “I had a flash of rage, but it would be like crushing a mouse to death. Also not instrumentally useful.”

“Well, thank you for not going that far,” said Amaryllis. “I do think it would be better if I had some wounds to lick, but the moment has passed, and I can work from a position of power.”

“I’m surprised that you didn’t have backup,” I said, frowning a bit. “You should have backup.”

“I have a fireteam of tuung with me,” said Amaryllis. “They’re just not a part of these negotiations. I thought it was better not to have the threat of violence here. Besides, the humans here don’t take to outsiders. They’re imperial citizens, but their culture is decidedly not cosmopolitan.”

“How did you get here so fast, anyway?” I asked.

“By leaving two weeks ago,” said Amaryllis. She allowed herself a smirk.

“Devious,” I replied with a nod. “Dispatched from Anglecynn?”

“Yes,” she replied. “The goal was negotiation, or if I wasn’t able to get an audience, then at least some very diplomatic spying on Perisev. I’m one of the tangent clones, not meant to sync up every day. Primary made an exception a few hours ago, for obvious reasons. There’s not a lot for you to do here, aside from being a demonstration of force. The anger will subside and be replaced with hopelessness.”

“Grim,” I said.

“I’m allowing myself to feel for these people,” said Amaryllis. “We destroyed what appears to have been a fairly relaxed life for a lot of them. Perisev had librarians here, and this theater was home to her own private acting troupe, who would put on plays on demand from within a wide repertoire.”

“And that’s your job here?” I asked. “Picking up the pieces?”

“Somewhat,” said Amaryllis. “One part public relations, one part management, one part resource extraction. Legally speaking, the entire complex belongs to you, since you were the one who killed her. I have a standing order to act as the executor of this place, in your name, which is another fringe benefit of our marriage.”

“And there’s a lot to loot?” I asked.

“Perisev had an extensive library and many unique works,” said Amaryllis. “Some of it we’ll be able to sell, but I imagine quite a bit will only be worth the value of the paper. A lot of it goes back to dragon psychology. There are stories here that would only ever have held value for Perisev. It will take some time to work out. We’ll also have to worry about the staff robbing the place blind, which is part of why I mean to dismiss them down to the village as quickly as possible. It’s also very possible that we’ll be the target of robbers or other bad actors, which might include the kingdom itself.”

“Well, I’ll be here for a bit,” I said.

“It’s probably not necessary,” Amaryllis replied with a sigh. “As far as our overall priorities go, this one comes in fifth or sixth.”

I thought about that for a moment. “Sorry, can you give me the order?”

“Fel Seed, Poran, Necrolaborem, Anglecynn, and then possibly the hells, depending on whether there’s any merit to the rumblings down there,” she said. “Most of those aren’t about you, they’re just bookkeeping and administration that will go on quietly in the background while the core team is off doing quests. The point being, you should only spend time on this diversion to the extent required by the call of the gold.”

“Hrm,” I said. “Fair. Seems a waste to spend so long in the air just for that.” I paused. “You know, bookkeeping is one of my favorite words.”

“Why?” asked Amaryllis.

“Because it’s one of the very few words in English that has three double letters,” I said.

“I really hope that’s not what you took from that,” replied Amaryllis.

“No,” I said. “Just making conversation. It’s the kind of thing I wish we did more often.”

“Just talking?” asked Amaryllis. “Me too. Sorry, I didn’t mean to criticize.” She paused as we kept walking. We’d left the theater, and we were going down one of the corridors, with her leading the way, our destination unknown to me. “I think the best I can do is moonnoonnookkeeper.”

“What?” I asked. “Oh. But that’s not a real word.”

“Of course it is,” replied Amaryllis. “It’s someone who keeps the nook at moonnoon.”

“Moonnoon is,” I began, then stopped for a moment, because as soon as I thought about it, I knew that it was, in fact, ‘a thing’. Moonnoon was the time when the moon was highest in the sky, though we’d probably use the term lunar noon instead. “It’s contrived. And should maybe be hyphenated.”

“Well, take it or leave it,” said Amaryllis.

“And nookkeeper is … I’m not sure if it's permissible,” I said.

“It’s part of the keeper cluster,” Amaryllis replied. “Brookkeeper, creekkeeper, rookkeeper, weekkeeper, hookkeeper, spookkeeper, and so on. All perfectly fine.”

“Remind me never to play Scrabble with you,” I said.

“And what is that?” asked Amaryllis.

“It’s a letter game,” I said. “You lay out words on a board, with the words crossing over each other and sharing letters, and certain spaces worth bonuses.”

“Ah,” replied Amaryllis. “We should try it sometime, though I imagine the Anglish/English problem would cause a significant amount of confusion.”

“Probably worth playing just for that,” I said. “Hey, when are you going to sync with Primary?”

“I don’t know,” replied Amaryllis. “There’s no cross-contingency, at least so far. It might be as long as a week. We can communicate through other methods, there’s no need to sync if she needs those ten minutes. Why?”

“Just thinking,” I said. “I’m not sure how the experience of it is for you. I had this idea that I would be able to give you a surprise that you wouldn’t ‘discover’ until later, but it probably doesn’t work like that.”

“It does, sometimes,” said Amaryllis. “The longest I’ve ever gone was two weeks, and some of the memories were little surprises, things that I brought new context to when I thought of them. The merge doesn’t include full synthesis of all ideas and experiences. If I’m reading a book on the lives and times of Imperator Kim, I won’t automatically connect it to a different book in another instance about the failures of the Second Empire’s occupational pipelines, because I never experienced either with each other’s context. There are gaps. I actually have a single instance of myself devoted just to drawing connections between lives.”

“Okay,” I said. I took off one of my iron gloves, which turned back into plain leather, then stuffed it into Rilke’s Strap. With my hand uncovered, I took Amaryllis’ hand and threaded my fingers into hers.

She looked down at it as we walked. “Holding hands?” she asked.

“Let me know if you hate it,” I said.

“No,” she said. “No, it’s … affectionate. In a good way.”

“There’s something really impressive about the way you toil away,” I said. “There’s no self-interest, no rewards, just your nose against the grindstone. Leave aside for a moment that you’re competent and capable in ways that almost no one is, the way you put yourself to work is really admirable.”

“Thank you, Juniper,” said Amaryllis. Her voice was soft. She squeezed my hand. “I mean, you’re wrong, there are rewards. I only do this because it’s the optimal thing to do. The rewards aren’t directly tangible, but I believe they’re there. I don’t love work like this, especially when I have nothing but my words. Thank you all the same.”

I nodded. “Where are we going?” I asked.

“Here,” said Amaryllis, gesturing to a small door that could clearly never have fit a dragon. “I thought you would want to see this.”

The doorway was too small for a dragon, but still large by human standards. Unlike the corridors, which were sparsely lit, this room was fully illuminated, with that light spilling out into the hallway. When I stepped in, I realized what this room was, and why Amaryllis might have wanted me to see it. Books were lined up on tall shelves, in long rows that stretched down into the center of the circular room, which was at least a hundred feet from us. I could see there, in that central room, that we were only on the ground floor, with the area stretching up at least another two stories. This was Perisev’s library.

“What’s in it?” I asked, looking over all the books.

“Stories,” Amaryllis replied. “This isn’t even the bulk of her hoard, most of it is down in deep storage, packed away in boxes. These are the ones that she actually liked, or wanted to reference. She had a staff of two dozen personal librarians.”

“Jesus,” I said softly. I waited for a beat. “Compared to the Infinite Library … it has that beat, but not in terms of volume. Opulence, and probably selection, definitely.” I started walking forward, through the shelves, and Amaryllis followed just behind me.

“I’m planning to keep on some of the librarians, if I can,” said Amaryllis. “But that will come with its own costs, and it’s not clear to me who or how many will stay.”

“Anything unique, from what you know?” I asked. “Clues?”

“This collection largely predates Uther’s invention of the printing press,” said Amaryllis. “There are bound to be books that never had a second copy made, which would mean that they didn’t make it into the Infinite Library. We’ll have to get Raven here at some point, if there’s time. I think the librarians will be the bigger assets. It’s hard to believe that Perisev would have gone as far as she did without consulting people she specifically paid to keep her informed.”

“Assuming that they’ll even talk to us,” I replied.

“We’re unpopular, for the moment,” said Amaryllis. “I’m still hoping that there’s something to be gained. I’ve already had an initial conversation with the librarians, and I’m hopeful that their academic inclination will carry through where there might be hard feelings.”

We reached the center of the room, which went up nearly ten stories and showed the extent of the stacks. There was even a little elevator built in, probably because going up more than four stories would be a pain in the ass. The whole place reeked of understated opulence, mostly in the woodwork and places where brass had been used at the joints or for protection. There was a certain level of stylistic cohesion that I’d come to associate with money, and it was on full display here: whoever had made the bannisters had also made the lamps, the tables, the elevator, and everything else.

I had expected a wizened old man for the head librarian, but instead we got a young woman. It took me a moment to take note of her pointed ears and human teeth, and another moment to realize that she might be a half-elf, like Fenn. She was on the taller side, only a few inches shorter than I was, and dressed in a very conservative red robe that hid her shape and looked ceremonial in nature.

“Juniper Smith?” she asked as she stepped forward. There were other people, probably also librarians, who were together in the stacks.

“Yes,” I said with a nod.

“Vella Greypalm,” she said, not stepping any closer to me for a handshake. “I run the library here, or did, apparently, until earlier today.”

“I won’t be in charge of any staffing changes,”  I said apologetically. I wasn’t even sure what I was doing here, except that the call of the gold had told me to come. Presumably I was supposed to be looking over what was of value, to act as a check on Amaryllis, but like hell I was going to do that if not directly prompted. “What can you tell me about Uther Penndraig that I don’t already know?”

“I don’t know what you know,” Vella replied. “Should I assume you’re a layman or a scholar?”

“In between,” I replied. “I travel with Raven Masters, who knew him personally, and I’m married to his most direct descendant, Amaryllis, which probably has let me in on a number of things that I would otherwise have remained ignorant of. I’ve also read a few biographies.”

“Hrm,” replied Vella. “It seems to me that you probably have more to teach me about Uther than I have to teach you,” she replied. “There is a rare book written by Uther, Degenerate Cycles, never widely published —”

“I have a few copies, and have read it,” I said.

“Ah,” she replied, thinking for a moment. “His daughter, Dahlia, disappeared when she was eleven. In reality, she used an entad to disguise herself as a boy and became Uther’s squire, Helio.”

“And after that she became the Red Mask in Cidium,” I said, nodding.

“She did?” asked Vella.

I nodded. “I heard that firsthand from some of those involved, so it’s no surprise that it never made it into any books.”

“Am I supposed to be able to tell you things that Raven herself didn’t know?” asked Vella.

“I had hoped so, yes,” I replied. “Or, not to besmirch her, things that she wouldn’t have told me, for one reason or another.” Also, nothing that ever appeared in a book that had two or more copies.

“Uther’s supposed murder of Vervain?” asked Vella.

“The rumors are known to me,” I replied.

“The mass dracicide?” I asked.

“Revealed by Perisev, confirmed by Raven,” I said. “I don’t really care too much about the details of that.”

“Uther’s connection to exclusion?” asked Vella.

“I mean … do you know much more than that there probably was a connection?” I asked.

“Not particularly,” replied Vella. “I could talk about the theories, including Perisev’s, but there’s nothing concrete.”

“She had theories?” I asked.

“She did,” replied Vella. “She understood them as essentially narrative in nature, though the theory is complex and in my opinion, not really worth going into.”

“Please,” I said. “Indulge me.” I grabbed a nearby chair and sat down, and after a moment, Vella did too.

“You’ve read Narrative Cycles, correct?” asked Vella.

I nodded. “That and Degenerate Cycles, though both of them only once.”

“I have marked up copies of both,” said Amaryllis as she took her own seat.

“Uther doesn’t specifically talk about the phenomenon of exclusion in either,” replied Vella. “But he does talk about the needs of the story, and to Perisev’s way of thinking, these needs corresponded to exclusion in a few key ways.”

“To be clear,” said Amaryllis. “Do you subscribe to this theory?”

“I think there’s something compelling in it,” replied Vella. “But I wouldn’t uncritically present it as something true, as Perisev did, nor do I think that it has enough explanatory power.”

“Alright, go on,” said Amaryllis.

“In Uther’s view, an essential component of ongoing narrative was a return to the status quo,” said Vella. “That’s the first and most obvious element that exclusion serves, by returning the world to normalcy in ways that would otherwise be difficult or impossible to accomplish. Many of Uther’s adventures ended with the climactic decapitation of enemy forces, literally or otherwise, and the return to normalcy was accomplished by a complete break in morale, along with structural and political changes. In some cases though, exclusion was the only possible way for the world to return to anything like it was before. That brings us to a second element of how exclusion might serve narrative, which is de-escalation. Uther talks about this extensively in Degenerate Cycles, the ways in which an infinite series of stories would require periodic down-scaling of stakes in order to compensate for what he saw as the inevitable rise in power, what he termed ‘power creep’. But of course, this breaks down when we look at exclusions which occurred outside of and unconnected with Uther’s time on Aerb.”

“What did Perisev think?” I asked.

“She had complicated theories,” replied Vella. “She believed that Uther himself was a force of narrative, that narrative itself was elemental to the world, a magic beyond all power and reason, of which Uther himself was only a single instrument. If exclusion was a narrative force, then the removal of the nominal protagonist from the world might have caused it to misbehave, or to only fire when it was necessary to ‘preserve’ the world in some way. Yet it’s clear that the world was not preserved, given numerous advancements in magic, society, and technology. The post-Utherian exclusions present the biggest problem with exclusion as narrative force, so long as you have accepted that narrative force is a real and coherent element of the world.”

“Huh,” I said. “Did Perisev ever posit that perhaps exclusions were a way to set up narratives?” I asked. “Zones of adventure where some future narrative could take place?”

Vella was silent for a moment. “She did. Is that … true?”

“Unknown,” I replied. “But it seems likely at this point.”

“And you’re the protagonist?” asked Vella.

“Yeah,” I replied. “Probably.”

“Oh,” said Vella. “Well.”

“Anything else about Uther?” I asked.

“There’s been ongoing speculation about where his stories came from, and where he went to, if he didn’t just die,” said Vella. “You’re familiar with the dream-skewered?”

“A bit,” I said.

“Perisev thought that many of his stories were adapted from Earth,” said Vella. “Either taken from the dream-skewered themselves, or through some other mechanism that connected to the same place. I was actually sent to Speculation and Scrutiny, about a hundred years ago,” she looked like she was in her mid-twenties, at the oldest, “to converse with the dream-skewered there, but they seemed to have a paucity of culture. The timeline is also not correct, as Uther’s discovery of the dream-skewered post-dates much of his creative work.”

“Unless Uther himself were dream-skewered,” I said.

“Yes,” nodded Vella. “This was considered and discarded. Unless … you have more information?”

“Why was it discarded?” I asked, ignoring the question.

“I spoke with the dream-skewered,” said Vella. “Their society wasn’t that different from what existed on Aerb prior to Uther’s birth. It’s tempting to believe that Uther’s advancements in sociology, language, art, technology, governance, and a number of other areas were the result of him bringing foreign and future ideas into the world, but that’s simply not the condition of the dream-skewered. Their world is not, in so many words, ‘real’ in that way, even if something like Earth can be said to, somehow, ‘exist’.”

“But Perisev didn’t find that persuasive,” said Amaryllis.

“There’s a much broader argument,” said Vella with a slight sigh. “I have my own writings on those arguments, streamlined versions of the dialogs that she had with me and other thinkers in this complex. It was enough to fill a short book. Much of it has to deal with the nature of the stories that Uther told, the variance between them and what they had in common with each other. He was imaginative about the role of magic and technology, but rarely if ever considered things outside the human frame. That’s speaking very broadly, of course there are counterexamples.”

“And as for where Uther went?” I asked.

“If he came from Earth in some respect, as seems plausible but unlikely, then that’s where he returned,” said Vella. “He was human, so would be long-dead by this point, but from what we know of the dream-skewered, Earth is timeless anyway, if it exists as a real, physical place.”

“But there’s no evidence for that,” I said. “I mean, no evidence that he actually did go back to Earth, just speculation based on what he believed about narrative.”

“That’s not quite true,” said Vella. “Are you familiar with Collections, his work of speculation? Perisev claims — claimed that hers was the only copy.”

I looked over at Amaryllis, and she frowned. “No,” I said.

“It’s not a proper book,” said Vella. “The title was applied to it only after the fact. The provenance is murky, but we believe that it was stolen from Caledwich Castle, where it was hidden behind wards. Further, it was enciphered in a way that took years of work to undo.”

“And what was in it?” asked Amaryllis.

“You can read it yourself,” said Vella. “Perisev was adamant that no copies be created, but we’ve kept it in good condition, and obviously we have copious notes that were made from examination of it. For the most part, it seems to be flights of fancy, at least partially inspired by his adventures and companions, but there are several sections of note that directly speak of Earth. Specifically, he imagines, or perhaps had knowledge of, a method of linking Earth to Aerb via a long corridor of challenges somewhat reminiscent of the Chthonic exclusion zone.”

“Long Stairs,” I said, smiling just a bit.

“You know of it?” asked Vella.

I nodded once. “The imaginings in this book, do they include the phrase Magus Europa at any point?”

“You know all this?” asked Vella, raising an eyebrow.

“Just a guess,” I replied. “He used the phrase Long Stairs?”

“He did,” replied Vella. “Only in the heading though.” She was watching me, and I sat there in silence, waiting for her to continue. “The way he spoke of it was … odd. You’ll have to read it yourself, but he speaks of the titular stairs as descending down from Earth, and speaks only in speculative tones about how these metaphorical ‘stairs’ might connect to Aerb, and provide a passage back.”

I looked over at Amaryllis. “O ye of little faith,” I said. She raised an eyebrow. “Right, for you that conversation hasn’t happened yet.”

Vella was staring at me. “It … hasn’t happened yet? Are you … a time traveler?”

“Oh,” I said. “Nothing so interesting as that.” I looked at Amaryllis for a moment. “We had a hypothesis about the nature of the extradimensional corridor,” I said. “There’s some supporting evidence that you wouldn’t be aware of yet. So I guess it’s a good thing that I came here.”

Liquidate everything.

“Ah, and there’s some input from my special friend,” I said.

Give the command to Amaryllis.

“Amaryllis, liquidate everything,” I said. “Sell all the books for whatever you can get. Sell everything that’s been collected here. Make a copy of the new book, duplicate anything else that’s original, or suspected to be unique.”

“Hrm,” she replied. “Okay.”

“All the books?” the librarian asked. “You don’t even know the vastness of this collection, the unique pieces of it, that which is irreplaceable.”

“I’ll discuss it with you more later,” said Amaryllis.

Discuss it now.

“Sorry, just as a ballpark,” I said. “You would surely have been in charge of acquisitions, right? And have some knowledge of the worth of this place?”

“I … I do,” she said. “I had hoped that it wouldn’t come to that.” She spared a glance for the others, who were still congregated in the stacks, periodically looking at us but pretending that they weren’t.

“I just need a number,” I said. “Some dollar — some obol amount that you would expect to get from a nearly complete sale of the books.”

“It would depend,” said Vella, looking around. “To say now would be irresponsible.”

Force her.

“I’m afraid I need a number,” I said. “You can take five minutes or so. If you need help with math, I can do sums virtually instantly.”

She thought for a moment. “Most of the value comes from a minority of works, perhaps a hundred works that have a combined value of … three hundred million, let’s say. I believe that’s my answer.”

“Thank you,” I said. I wasn’t sure what the next step in escalation was for the call of the gold, but I was glad that I hadn’t been asked to break her fingers or something like that.

Leave for Necrolaborem.

“I need to go,” I said, frowning a bit. I had been enjoying myself in the library, especially with the promise of new, never-before-read books. It was hard to tell from the brief description I’d been given, but my guess was that Collections was just a fancified notebook that Uther had been using to write down whatever scraps he could remember from our campaigns.

I trekked back out of the library, then began flying once I reached the corridor, and went supersonic once I was out.

“Now why did you do that?” I asked the wind, not really expecting a response, and after a minute or so, realizing that I wasn’t going to get anything like a dialogue.

My best guess was that while I’d been looking around Perisev’s place (which probably had a name, now that I thought about it, and was too far away to ask anyone), the call of the gold had been looking too. It knew what I knew, after all, which meant that until we’d actually gone there, it had been ignorant of what was valuable. I had no idea whether it was tracking the conversation about the Long Stairs, but perhaps it had just reached the point where it felt like I had gleaned enough information, and needed to get back to something approximating work.

The idea of the call of the gold gathering information was a bit frightening, but I tried to put it out of my mind, and instead focus on what the next few days would hold.

Doecent

I wasn’t planning to be in the same place as Bethel. I didn’t want to be around her, and there was really no compelling reason for us to be in the same place at the same time. I tried, briefly, to think about how she felt, what emotions were stirred up inside her by briefly renewed contact with the team, but I couldn’t summon up enough empathy to get any kind of insight.

I had put a ton of work into our plans, leveling almost all of my non-combat skills up to their caps, and getting new virtues in the process. There was something that felt honest about what I was doing, even if the game system allowed me to cheat. I was building something, crafting a way forward for the people of the NLEZ, helping to mend the enormous societal trauma that they had faced from the moment they’d been born to undead mothers. Grak had talked about the way wards sometimes felt alienating to him, a product created without a clear connection to its ultimate goal, but I was feeling nothing like that when working on the systems we were going to put in place. I wasn’t even sure why I felt so good about it, but I did. When the team was done (or as done as we could be given that some work would be finished within the time-dilated facility, and other parts would need more information or iteration), we had a thick stack of papers that outlined every way in which the NLEZ would be taken over, stripped of zombies, and then slowly bled of its population, all while making sure that everyone would have the necessary food and water.

There had been additional work needed for the second generation of tuung, since this go-around was going to be somewhere in the range of a hundred thousand of them, a full city that would run for a significant amount of time before they came out into the real world. Stored time in the time chamber was effectively a non-issue, given that time had been accruing while Bethel had held the bottle, the room designated as the time chamber being fucking massive. There needed to be systems in place though, water, air, electricity, and waste, though much of our problems could be completely solved through a combination of entadic effects, and I helped work on a lot of those problems. There were still concerns about housing for the tuung, what the classrooms would look like, how they would be shuttled from one place to the next, what kinds of personnel it would take, the kinds of ratios we would run, and while I had virtually nothing to do with the adaptation of lesson plans and the writing of material for dissemination, I could help with the engineering, logistics, and numbers.

“Can we talk privately?” I asked Liam, the day before Bethel was due to arrive. “Just for a moment.”

“Of course,” he said with a nod.

I liked Liam. He was one of the tuung that I had worked with the most closely, which was partly due to him being fairly important. He was one of the few that had been mentioned frequently in the books that Cypress had written. He was straightforward and to the point, diligent and studious, always with facts and figures on hand. The tuung had been raised that way, but at least so far as I could tell, not all of them hewed so close to the archetype. My interaction with Elizabeth, days earlier, had given me an inkling that there was a fair amount of tuung society that I wasn’t seeing. Most of those I came in contact with were elites, either members of fireteams guarding party members or clones, or the ones who had been selected or promoted to various committees. I was meeting bodyguards and politicians, not janitors and porters, though those certainly had their place in this crafted society.

“What did you want to discuss?” he asked.

“Figure there are a hundred thousand people in the second generation,” I said. “What happens to those that are below average?

“We follow the Lake Wobegon model,” he replied. His lips curled slightly in the tuung version of a smile.

“Uh,” I said. “I’m not familiar.”

His face fell, just a bit. “You never read the Lake Wobegon tales?” he asked. “I was under the impression they were from your Earth.”

“Ah,” I said. “But the gist of it is … ?”

“Everyone is above average,” he said.

“Huh,” I replied. “And how is that managed?” I asked. I was getting a nervous feeling.

“Adequate nutrition and education are the primary components,” he replied. “It is my understanding that in Anglecynn, as well as your Earth, children are often left to starve, and even if nutrition is taken care of, their schooling and attainment is dependent on the wealth of their parents.”

“But with a hundred thousand tuung, you’re bound to have people who are at the bottom of the bell curve,” I said. Liam was obviously somewhere near the top. “What happens to them?”

“They take lesser roles,” replied Liam. “If there are persistent problems, we offer aid and advice, or medical intervention if that’s required. You’ve seen the hospitals that will be a part of this scheme.”

“I’m asking more like, will they be happy?” I asked. “Will they have some control of their own life, or just be consigned to menial work?” I didn’t think there was anything wrong with being a janitor, per se, but I could see where it would weigh on you to be doing that vital function when others in your cohort were going into battle, or solving huge production line problems, or engaging in diplomacy.

“Your frame is wrong,” replied Liam. “That’s not our understanding of our place in the world, on several counts. No work is ‘menial’, work is either necessary or unnecessary, and everyone does as much as they can. If you are within a command structure, you follow orders, and if you are in mutual cooperation, you attempt to maximize your impact. No one has control; that is not the frame. Your decision on what to do is predicated on your understanding of the situation. There is no element of choice, only an understanding of conditions.”

I tried to think about that. It was clear that I was going to have to read, at a minimum, a half dozen books to really ‘get’ the tuung and the culture that Amaryllis had invented, and I had only read two, both introductory ones. Of course, aside from reading a lot of ‘the canon’, I would also have to do some immersion, because culture wasn’t just the books that people took as sacred, it was what they took from those books, and the rites and rituals that they built up around those. You could go into any church in the Midwest and read the Bible and a hymnal book, but that wouldn’t tell you much about Christianity in practice. (I was making progress in my reading of the Bible, but a lot of it was just not all that relevant, including a bunch of outdated rules and lists of lineage that made my eyes glaze over.)

“I want the tuung to have a feeling of power,” I said. “I want them to understand that their life is under their own control.”

“We are not so individual,” replied Liam. “That way of thinking is antithetical to us. We studied both Anglecynn and America, Juniper. We understand the way that you think. It’s just not the way that we think. It’s a cultural aspect that we’ve examined and rejected.”

“Alright,” I said, frowning. “How sure are you of that?”

“What do you mean?” he asked.

“How sure are you that the feeling I’m describing isn’t shared by the tuung?” I asked. “You’re an apex citizen, most suited to the work. You don’t think that those in the lower half, tasked with less important work, feel a bit put out, or like they have no direction?”

“Juniper, we don’t have the time for this,” said Liam. “We have the time for a few conversations on the subject, but the second generation needs to be aging up as quickly as possible in order for us to solve the issues with Necrolaborem, and after that, shift our focus to industry.”

“You’re planning to be a part of the mentorship contingent?” I asked.

“If cleared by the committee, yes,” replied Liam.

“Then just keep what I’ve said in mind,” I said. “That’s all. You’re right that we’re under a crunch, but from my understanding, you’ll have time once you’re under dilation.”

“That’s true,” nodded Liam. “We have time for further plans while we wait for the eggs to hatch, and during those early years when not much is required in the way of education or socialization. We value the analysis and incorporation of other beliefs. Your input will be taken seriously.”

“Alright,” I said. “Thanks.” I was a bit worried that I was throwing a monkey wrench into Amaryllis’ plans, but she was the one who had put me on the second generation committee, presumably for a reason. Liam was right that I was talking to and about a culture that I didn’t fundamentally understand, but I was hopeful that what I was saying would stick with him, if only a bit. A whole lot of the tuung were going to be part of the second generation project, and I was hopeful that he would be able to seek out those who had other perspectives.

“Can I ask,” said Liam, as I was about to go, “Was any of what you spoke of influenced by your unique understanding of the future?”

I hesitated. He hadn’t been read in on the Infinite Library, at least to my knowledge, and I didn’t know whether he was talking in code, or whether he only had a bare inkling of what was going on. “It’s true that I have some insights,” I said. “But no, the advice comes from my personal understanding of the world. Though — I can’t tell you what the future brings, because I don’t know that, but I do know a bit about what might have been, and the need for independence was manifest there.” The tuung had broken from Amaryllis in the Cypress timeline, and it hadn’t been quite clear from what Cypress had written in her books what the root cause of the issue was, aside from a general desire for autonomy and self-determination. It had always been planned that we wouldn’t rule the tuung in perpetuity: there was a reason we styled ourselves as an advisory council.

“Thank you,” he said, giving a little bow.

When the time came for Bethel to come to Necrolaborem, I left for Poran, ensuring that I wouldn’t have to see or speak with her, or even have the knowledge that we could perceive each other. Valencia had endorsed this behavior, so I didn’t feel too bad about it, but it was entirely possible that Valencia had endorsed the behavior because she didn’t want me to feel bad about it.

I was getting better at flying, though I was capped on Gold Magic. Most of it was just making my body as aerodynamic as possible, which let me increase my speed. I wanted to fly higher, where the air was thinner and there would be less friction, but I wanted to do my best to not get a dragon called down on me, even if I thought there was a good chance that I would be able to win that kind of fight. It had been a few days, but we’d heard nothing official from the Draconic Confederacy, and our contact within it, Sweet William, had given the opinion that nothing formal would come from the deaths of two of their members. As outcomes went, it was one of the better ones, since it meant that I probably wasn’t going to get in another tussle with a dragon.

I touched down in the domain of the locus and was greeted by the six-eyed doe almost as soon as my feet were on the ground.

“Hey there,” I said, patting her head as she bowed down to poke me in the chest with her nose. “Miss me?”

The doe gave what looked like a nod.

“Well, I missed you too,” I said. “I’ve been having a longing for the old days lately. No offense to Raven or Val, but sometimes it feels like we hit our peak early on, back when we weren’t in charge of any institutions, and no one cared about our existence.” The doe flopped down, and I went to her side, continuing to pet her. “You were a good home. A welcoming place for us to stay and recuperate. Not that you’re not that now, but everyone knows you exist, and Solace is trying to bring in new druids, and it’s all different in a way that’s hard to describe but that I don’t particularly like. I wanted you to be wild and free.”

Loyalty Increased: Six-Eyed Doe lvl 21!

That was a surprise. Usually I needed more, some kind of understanding of the doe, some acknowledgment of that side of me that was locus-like, but this was just simple empathy and mutual feeling.

“How are things with Solace?” I asked.

The doe snorted.

“Yeah,” I said. “I saw how you see her, and — you know that she’s doing everything in her power to get you back to who you were before the Second Empire came in and ruined everything, right?”

There was no response to that, only closed eyes and soft fur beneath my fingertips.

“I can see how it would rankle,” I said. “You go through this trauma, and you adapt to it, change from it, and then when it’s over, not that it’s ever really over, people are trying to hammer you back into shape. They want you to return to who and what you were before, as though that’s what you should want, or do want, even though everything has changed, and you’ve changed.”

I was speaking as though it was a metaphor for something in my own life, though what, I wasn’t sure. There were a lot of obvious parallels to be drawn, like to the way things had been different for me after Arthur’s death, or after Fenn’s, or after being raped by Bethel. The levels and kinds of pressure to return to normal were different, the situations similar only in strokes so broad that they couldn’t actually paint a picture.

“So,” I said. “Let’s say that I’m right. What does your future look like, to you? What is the next step, if we don’t accept that you’re just going to die shortly after Solace?”

The doe had no particular response. It reminded me of talking to my cat, who was much more interested in being petted than listening to what I had to say.

“I don’t know if it’s possible to untie you from this place,” I said. “I mean, I know it’s probably possible if you have the power of a god, but … I was trying to envision some future for you that’s just completely unlike anything a locus has been before. There’s some inherent commonality between loci, at least from what I’ve heard from people, and that might be what you’re chafing under. It’s a hard square to circle.” I sighed. “You know, I was going to say something dumb, like maybe that commonality represents something that’s definitively, categorically true about a locus, but it’s really not. Like, elves show up in a lot of fantasy worlds, including this one, but you couldn’t point to that omnipresence of elves and say that they gave you real and true information about what a fantasy world was, or that they represent any kind of constant. At best, they represent something common to humanity, or how human brains work, but you’d have to do some kind of cross-cultural comparison to make sure that it wasn’t just a strong meme. So maybe all the understanding of what it means to be a locus, the tradition of inducting druids, that kind of thing, is all just optional.”

Loyalty Increased: Six-Eyed Doe lvl 22!

And that was a surprise again. I didn’t know whether the message was an indication that I was fundamentally right, or whether it was just a line of thinking that the locus enjoyed, or if it represented a change in how the locus thought of me, but it had come hot on the heels of the previous loyalty increase, and presumably that meant something.

“Do you want to go somewhere?” I asked. “You can come with me, we know that you can, so I was just wondering whether there was anywhere you wanted to be. Maybe, if it wouldn’t be too painful, the site of your old domain, where you lived before the bottle? It wouldn’t be hard for me to find, I don’t think, and as I am now, I can fly really fast.”

The locus flicked an ear in response.

I used the crown to look through its eyes, and saw us together as a doe and buck, with her laying down, resting, and myself curled up next to her with my neck across her back. There was something affectionate and familiar about it, in a way that made me a bit heartsick. When Tiff and I had been dating, we had sometimes laid together like that, and if I was more awake than she was, I would talk on, getting nothing more than delayed nods or murmurs of assent from her as my mind wandered on and sleep eluded me.

It was possible that the locus was just enjoying being petted, happy with being talked to but not particularly caring what noises I was making with my mouth.

I went silent for a bit, and then just lay there.

I must have dozed off, because I was awoken by Amaryllis, who had sat down next to me. I was in my armor, so I wouldn’t have guessed that it was terribly comfortable, but she was curled up next to me, with her back against the locus, like mine was. She was a clone, naturally, since I’d left the original back in Necrolaborem. She wasn’t sleeping, but she was definitely resting.

“I’m synced,” she said once I began to stir. “I did it right after you left, so there shouldn’t be discontinuity.”

“Good,” I said. “You’re very considerate.”

“Yes, well,” replied Amaryllis. “There will be some burdens to bear in the coming days, I’m just trying to do my part.”

“I know,” I said. “I’m prepared for it. It’s necessary. I am capable of doing the necessary thing, you know.”

“Being capable doesn’t mean that it’s without costs,” said Amaryllis. “Sometimes it hurts to do something that you know is the right thing to do.”

“Hmm,” I replied. “I don’t really want to talk about it, if that’s alright with you. We could talk about the next steps, but I’m frankly pretty sick of the call of the gold, and too much is contingent on how long I can ride it.” I had hit up a few places that Raven had marked, sites of old caches of items, which seemed to appease the call of the gold, at least so far. It would take some time for those items to go to auction and see material gains that could be translated into actual gold, but at least at this stage, the call of the gold showed some patience. Even Aumann, who had been a gold mage for quite some time, hadn’t been compelled to sell off his factories and enterprises for more gold, and we were hopeful that we wouldn’t have to liquidate the money-makers. “Going after Fel Seed with gold magic is attractive for obvious reasons, especially if we can blitz the dimensional tunnel, but Fel Seed cheats, so I think there’s a good chance he would have some kind of counter for passing through his territory at twice the speed of sound.”

“The next step is clearing exclusions,” said Amaryllis. “Unfortunately, there’s not that much of a point in doing most of them, except in terms of extrinsic rewards. You could likely kill Rove, but no one lives in that exclusion zone anymore, and the best we could say was that you would be bringing him to justice. There’s no bounty on his head, no reward to be gained from his death, not unless you count whatever the game is using in place of experience points, if anything. People would be able to reclaim the land, but that’s not worth much.”

“It might be, to them,” I replied.

“The villages there are gone,” said Amaryllis. “The land is all that remains. There’s no heritage to restore, and it’s been long enough that I doubt most of the people who escaped would care to go back.”

“Okay,” I said. “But Rove isn’t the only one of the Thirteen Horrors that I could potentially take on. Before he went wherever he was going, Uther cleared as much off his plate as he could, wrapping things up as best he knew how. Seems like that might be something I would want to mimic.”

“I’m not actually sure that it would matter,” said Amaryllis. She had a kind of far-off look in her eyes. “I’ve been reading a lot.”

“Oh yeah?” I asked. “About?”

“It’s entirely possible that Perisev was right,” said Amaryllis. “I was convinced by narrative arguments, focused on cycles and degenerate cycles, and —  what she said, about what kind of story she thought you were in, was something that had occurred to me, obviously it did, but I’ve been coming to accept that it’s very possible that we’re in the kind of story that exists only to comment on and subvert other stories.”

“Uh,” I said. “First off, I don’t agree, I think we’re in a tabletop game, which tries to be a story, but sometimes fails because the players don’t do what the DM expected, and the rules aren’t always clear or well-written, or not conducive to story beats, or something like that. But second, would it really be cause for despair if this were a postmodern story?”

“How does a postmodern story end?” asked Amaryllis.

“Dunno,” I replied. “I haven’t read enough of them, I guess.”

“The story circle begins in a place of comfort, there’s an inciting incident, the hero picks up a mentor and/or some companions, goes through a number of trials, journeys through the underworld, then comes back out, wins the day, and returns home, having changed,” said Amaryllis. “I know that you know this, give me just a bit of patience.”

“Sorry, my darling wife, go ahead,” I said. I was enjoying being with her, as I often did, and could have listened to her talk about nearly anything, even politics.

“In a postmodern story, you’re allowed and expected to break things,” said Amaryllis. “You see and critique the story circle. If you think about it in the right way, it might even have applied to Uther, the way in which he stalled out on endlessly repeating narratives over the course of what would have had to be a whole bookshelf of novels. But do you see the problem with that, from my perspective?”

“I might not win the day,” I replied. “I could die and lose. I’ve been saying and believing that for pretty much my entire time on Aerb.”

“You’re thinking of it differently than I am,” said Amaryllis. “You’re thinking of failure as a thing that might happen to you, if you don’t do well enough, or worse, if you have a series of bad rolls. I’m thinking of failure as though it might be the whole point.”

“In which case there would be nothing that we could do,” I said. “So why worry about it? As a train of thought, it seems even more useless than narrative thinking.”

“I can understand that point of view,” Amaryllis replied. “And we’re obviously not going to be putting in place any plans that depend on your death in one way or another.”

“Good,” I said. “I mean, I wouldn’t mind dying, if it were for a good reason.”

“I know,” replied Amaryllis. “And I appreciate that about you.”

“Look, don’t worry,” I said. “Whatever is happening up two or three levels above the actual object level, just forget about it. Easier said than done, I know, but if you can’t predict what kind of meta structure exists, or whether multiple ones exist, or what has precedence, then the best you can do is to focus on what’s right in front of you.”

Amaryllis let out a breath. “Thank you,” she said.

“For what?” I asked.

“I think this might be the first time you’ve ever talked me around to being reasonable,” she said.

I smiled at her. “Well that’s a backhanded compliment if I’ve ever heard one. Also, completely not true. This is the third or fourth time, by my count.”

“Are you counting the time you let me beat you up?” asked Amaryllis.

“I’m not not counting it,” I replied. “Come on, just give me a little bit of credit? I could use it.”

“Of course,” replied Amaryllis. She turned to the side and kissed me. “Sorry, I was just poking fun.”

“Well, whatever gets you in a better mood,” I said.

“And you?” she asked. “So far as I know, you’re not on the clock right now. Anything I can do for you?” She had an eyebrow slightly raised, and there was something in the way she was looking at me that seemed particularly lewd. I was getting better at not overthinking things with her, of accepting our relationship for what it was, but I still paused for a moment as I let the usual thoughts flow through me.

I was changing my mind, slowly. We still hadn’t had sex (not sex sex), primarily because she hadn’t pushed it and I hadn’t brought it up. Every time things got sexual though, it was less surprising than the time before, less worry on my part about whether it was okay. Still great, but more routine. Maybe her intent was to wear me down, or maybe that was just what was naturally happening, but it was feeling less like a problem to be solved, and more like a comfortable part of our relationship.

“Can we find some place more private?” I asked, looking back at the locus, which I was still resting against.

“Of course,” replied Amaryllis. She glanced at the doe. “You know the locus doesn’t care, right?”

“I know,” I said. “The locus has probably seen more sex than any other entity on the planet.”

“Not a planet,” said Amaryllis.

“On the plane,” I corrected.

“And I don’t care either,” said Amaryllis. “Do you?”

“Er,” I said. “You know, I’ve lately been trying out different frames on things, trying to shed all the dumb and bad parts of my generically Midwestern upbringing. So, yeah, there’s a part of me that’s a little bit uncomfortable about just doing it outside, but that part is dumb and bad, so why listen to it? I should just do the thing and hope that the old ways of thinking erode away when there’s continued evidence that no, it’s not the end of the world.”

“I think it’s all the flying,” said Amaryllis. “It’s made you more contemplative.”

“Sure,” I replied.

“Did you want a blowjob or not?” she asked.

“Yeah,” I replied.

I hadn’t seen Solace in the last few days, not since before all the crap with the dragons. I had known that she’d been injured in the fight with Perisev, but had rushed off to the dragon corpses before I’d had a chance to see her, and after that, had spent barely any time in Poran. I’d had things to think about, and hadn’t inquired into the details of the injury, because I’d been told that Solace would be alright.

It was quite a surprise to see that she was walking with a cane, her skin still scarred from dragonfire. She was wearing a cloak, but the damage was clear on the left side of her face, which had a melted look, reminiscent of photos of acid attacks I’d seen online and only half-remembered. Her left leg was incredibly skinny, the muscle having been melted away, leaving only skin wrapped around bone. It must have been functional though, because she was using a cane, not a crutch.

“Juniper,” she said, voice weak. “You grace the domain with your presence? To what do I owe the honor?”

I stared at her for a moment. “There’s some stuff happening in the NLEZ that I don’t want to be a part of,” I replied. “How have you been?” She gave no immediate answer. “I’m sorry, I didn’t think — when I was told that you would be fine, I’d thought that meant you would make a full recovery.”

“You’re wondering how it is that I haven’t healed myself,” said Solace. There was something of an old woman to the way she moved around the tree house, but her body was that of a teenager, at least so far as I could tell with a crantek. There was something profoundly sad about the combination of youth and injury.

“I was,” I said. “Either it’s something about dragonfire that you can’t fix, or … a statement, of some kind?”

“A statement,” nodded Solace. “But not a statement of my own.”

“The locus,” I said, frowning a bit. “Dare I ask why?”

Solace looked away for a moment, and I shot a look at Amaryllis, who was standing there without much expression on her face. I was tempted to shoot her a few sharp words in Gimb, but I could already guess why she hadn’t told me, and further, why she hadn’t warned me. For the first, she wouldn’t have wanted to bother me with something I clearly didn’t want to deal with, and for the second, it was a bit of rebuke.

“Just as a cleric is not a perfect representative of their god, so too with druids,” sighed Solace. “I am being punished with this maiming. That’s clear enough, given that my powers are otherwise intact.”

“Hrm,” I said. “But they’re not your powers, are they?”

Solace stared at me for a moment, one eye drooping a bit. “What insights do you have?” she asked.

“None,” I replied. “Just some thinking that I was doing while next to the locus about her essential nature, and how even the rules we think might exist for her are inventions of the people who interact with her. I was thinking that the paradigm you want to return to, that of an expansive domain filled with druids, might not actually be what the locus wants, not anymore.”

“And where does this insight come from?” asked Solace.

“I don’t know,” I said, feeling defensive. “I was just … thinking things. Thinking about trauma and moving on from it, and how that can be hard. How you have trouble getting back to the same exact shape you were in before, how that’s not really necessary, even if it might feel that way. That’s all.”

“And then what?” asked Solace. “I’m the last druid. When I die, there will be no more. The locus has only this limited domain, with only the raw natural processes that work on it. At the end of the current path lies death, for me, and for the locus.”

“Maybe,” I replied. “Maybe it’s just going to become something unique, and different, and new. You have to admit that it would be on brand.”

“It would,” said Solace. She leaned against her cane. “I can’t even say that you’re wrong, that’s the frustrating part.”

“And it would be hard to act on,” said Amaryllis, finally injecting her own opinion into the conversation. “The best we could do would be to let the locus do as it pleases while leaving options open to it, which is exactly what we’re doing now.”

“Respectfully, no,” I said, looking at Solace. “You act as the guardian of the locus. When the two of you were on the ship, you were trying to push the locus to come back here, and my guess is that you were also trying to make sure that the locus wouldn’t go in the first place. And honestly, you’re in charge of the domain, you’re putting yourself in place to decide who does and doesn’t get in, what happens on the land, that kind of thing.”

“And I should stop?” asked Solace. There was a bit of an edge to her voice.

“The domain would be overrun,” said Amaryllis. “There has to be someone who stops tourists from stepping foot in the domain, and businessmen who want to make money, and parents who want cures for the deadly illnesses that are resistant to all other healing and will claim their children before adulthood. It absolutely is not feasible for the domain to be open to all. Besides, most of the enforcement is being handled through the Republic of Miunun, and secondarily, through the Conservation Bureau.”

“So you’re saying that I don’t have a point?” I asked. “Or do you think that I’m correctly understanding the nature of the locus, but that the locus is incompatible with a wider world that’s as interconnected as Aerb is?”

“You might be right,” said Solace. “It’s possible. It is.” She looked off to the side, frowning. “I’ll need to think about it.”

I glanced at Amaryllis, who had her arms folded in front of her.

“Let me know if there’s anything that I can help with,” I said. “Amaryllis and I will be around.”

“Of course,” replied Solace, not really focused on me anymore.

We left the tree house and got far enough away to talk, though of course I could have muted us, or we could have switched over to Gimb.

“I’m not sure that was the best way to approach that,” said Amaryllis. “Solace hasn’t been well, as you could obviously see.”

“I know,” I replied. “I’m not blind. The subtext, or subtexts, of that injury was also not lost on me.”

“And yet you proceeded,” replied Amaryllis.

“It’s not clear to me that the locus can explain what it wants,” I said. “And it’s actually not clear that it knows what it wants, if I’m allowed to project my own problems and insecurities onto it.”

“I really wish that you wouldn’t,” she said. “Especially not when Solace is in a vulnerable place.”

“I told you how the locus sees her,” I sighed. “I don’t know if that’s information that Solace needs, but it seems to me that their relationship isn’t quite what it should be, right? And if you wanted to be delicate about it, then,” I shrugged. “I don’t know what to tell you. There was time for you to bring it up with her. Correct me if I’m wrong, but you have multiple instances here that are devoted purely to Solace and the locus, right?”

“We do,” said Amaryllis. “I didn’t think you’d go in so hard, otherwise I would have done work on those particular aspects. But it should also be clear that there are certain things that I see as my job, and other things that simply aren’t.”

“Oh,” I said, as realization dawned on me. “Holy shit, you’re avoiding doing plot relevant things with the clones.”

“That’s not quite it,” replied Amaryllis. “Things have been rocky between Solace and myself, and yes, this seemed like one of those situations where it was better to have you deal with talking to her on your own. The bigger problem was that you felt like you had some grand revelation and didn’t elect to share that with me before speaking to Solace. I could have helped.”

“Well,” I said. “I don’t actually know whether I’ve had a grand revelation or not, I might just be talking out my ass, or confusing things that feel right for things that are actually true. So no, I probably shouldn’t have said any of that to Solace unless I had something more firm, but … you know, it seems like how the locus exists, and waiting, gathering more evidence, being really optimal about things, that’s just … I don’t know. Sorry, I have this specific mindset that I try to get in when I’m in this place, a way of being that I’m hopeful is in sync with the locus. Sometimes it feels like it’s working, sometimes it’s just me basically talking to myself about injecting some artistry into worldbuilding, but — sorry.”

“It’s fine, Juniper,” said Amaryllis. “If you owe anyone an apology, which I don’t think you do, then it would be to Solace. And if you’re right, then it’s just a matter of how the message was delivered, not the content.”

“Okay,” I said. “Sorry again, for bungling it.”

“I don’t think it was bungled. Sorry, I’m trying to see things from your perspective,” said Amaryllis. “You were taking the locus’ side of things, at least as you saw it. That’s good. I know that as companions go, the locus hasn’t always been easy, especially given how separated the locus is from the rest of us, and how hard the locus is to understand. I’ll content myself with believing that you’re starting to get what the locus means to us.” Us, in this context, meaning the people of Aerb, of which I was clearly not a member.

“I’m not,” I said. “Really, really not. The modern world putting so much importance on the loci, on the druids, still makes very little sense to me, or only about as much sense as any bit of cultural ephemera. It’s probably one of those things that I could read about in a book, or ask Raven about, I guess.”

“I looked up the answer,” said Amaryllis. “If you’re curious.”

“Sure,” I said. “I mean, to the extent there is an answer.” I was a bit surprised that she’d put it like that.

“It’s a disappointing answer,” Amaryllis replied. “The answer is propaganda. This was shortly after the fall of the Second Empire, when the remnants of their faction were being pulled out by the counter-imperial forces all over Aerb like so many rotten teeth. The counter-imperialists didn’t have much in the way of cultural power, especially since a lot of them wanted to reclaim their kingdoms, though reclaim is a strong word given that the Second Empire stuck around long enough that whole generations had passed. They were grasping at straws, looking for symbols, tools that they could use to make sure that the cultural war would be won, and stay won. Soul magic was a representation of everything that was vile about the Second Empire, though I don’t think that actually gets to the heart of it. Soul magic probably only serves as an obvious symbol that anyone looking to resurrect the Second Empire would avoid. But the counter-imperialists needed a face of goodness as well, some symbol of righteousness to go with their symbol of evil. There were lots to choose from, heroes and victims, but the loci were good because they were neutral entities, not affiliated with any polity or faction. Some of this was utilitarian effort at swaying public opinion, some of it was just people who genuinely believed that the Second Empire had been evil, attempting to put that evil in their own terms. The counter-imperialists put out books, created artworks, made plays, all kinds of things.”

“And now everyone treats the locus like it’s a victim,” I said.

“The locus is a victim,” said Amaryllis.

“But it’s not only a victim,” I replied. “It’s not how it would define itself, if it were given to definitions. That’s just … part of what I’m talking about. I’ve been dealing with this gold magic stuff, basically being made to run errands. The entity wants me to watch out for you because it thinks that you’re going to steal from me, and when people see me, they see a gold mage, which is ridiculous, because I’m willing to drop it basically at a moment’s notice.” I sighed. “Maybe I have been spending too much time in the air, thinking to myself, because it feels like there are all these threads that I can only make sense of by weaving them together.”

“Such as?” asked Amaryllis.

“I don’t know,” I replied. “The tuung, for example. They have their own culture, which you designed, and their own place in the world, which is largely defined for them, —”

“That’s not quite right,” said Amaryllis. “Their place in the world is defined by the needs that they can fulfill, following a principle of greatest utility, and with a strong caution against working themselves to the bone or thinking in the short term.”

“Distinction noted,” I said. “But in terms of how they think of themselves, their role in the world? Compare that to those people at Perisev’s place, the actors, librarians, and staff. Or compare to the people in Blue’s hellhole, who have been subjected to their own engineered culture. Or Grak, who is pretty clearly suffering under the burden of being our warder in a way that I don’t think he would if he were just doing contract warding work in a big city somewhere.”

“Grak would likely be depressed either way, because Grak is a depressive,” said Amaryllis.

“Seems harsh,” I said.

“It’s fundamental to understanding him, I think,” replied Amaryllis. “Grak tends toward depression, so the state you’ll commonly find him in is basically that.”

“And what, it’s just impossible for him to be happy?” I asked.

“No, that’s not what I’m saying at all,” replied Amaryllis. “Sorry, I know you’re fond of him, I should have chosen my words more carefully.” She took a breath, thinking for a moment. “Being happy, for Grak, is a matter of attempting not to regress to the mean. It requires constant attention from himself and help from the people around him. Beyond that, physical exercise and a proper diet. And yes, it would also help to not have enormous amounts of pressure and stress placed on him, like, for example, being at least partially responsible for millions of lives in a situation that on the surface resembles the one that damned his childhood friends and family to the hells. It would also probably help to not have one of his closest friends using gold magic, which is historically reviled by his people.”

“I guess,” I said. “But Grak’s issues aside, you understand what I’m pointing at? The different ways that people make a compromise between what they want to do and what they’re compelled to do? And I’m just trying to make sense of it, especially in the context of myself, and Uther.”

“The compulsion to narrative?” asked Amaryllis.

“For him, sure,” I said. “But obviously while he had his narrative obsession, that wasn’t all there was to him. He devoted himself to making the world a better place, in a lot of ways. I wonder how much of that he had a thirst for, and how much was just done because it had to be done, or because he thought it had to be done.” I was silent for a moment, staring off into the distance. It was making me sad, and I could feel my eyes wet with the start of tears. I really had been spending too much time in the air. “I just want to talk to him.”

“I know,” said Amaryllis. She came close to me and touched my arm a bit before leaning against me. “We need to be cautious about running headlong towards where we think he is.”

“You don’t think we’ll find the Long Stairs in Fel Seed’s exclusion zone?” I asked. “You don’t think that we’ll find Uther somewhere down there?”

“I don’t know, Juniper,” said Amaryllis. “You know where my head is at. I don’t think it will be straightforward. I think there’s a twist coming, and I don’t know what it will be, but my gut feeling is that I won’t like it.”

“Hrm,” I said. “Thank you for everything, by the way. I feel like I don’t say that enough.”

“You’re welcome,” replied Amaryllis, still leaning against me. “We’ll make it through all of this, together. I hope.” The hedge felt unnecessary, but I knew Amaryllis well enough to know that she had a hard time giving out platitudes.

“I love you,” I said.

Amaryllis was silent for a moment. “You know, I was hoping that we could save it for some appropriately dramatic moment. Something with some narrative weight? Rather than just a quiet moment between the two of us when we’re not doing much of anything.”

“Alright,” I said. “I take it back.”

“You can’t just take it back,” said Amaryllis. “It’s been said, it’s out there.”

“No,” I replied. “It was all part of the ruse, the fake marriage. Obviously I don’t actually love you, that would be absurd, taking the game too far. I just said it because someone might somehow be listening in, despite the precautions and the fact that we’re on hallowed ground.”

“I love you too,” said Amaryllis.

“Oh,” I said. I felt a warmth rush through me on hearing that. “You know, it’s pretty dumb that I had even the slightest shred of doubt.”

“Well, no need to be full of yourself about it,” said Amaryllis. She kissed my arm, which she was holding (technically, my armor). “Are you curious when I undid the modifications?”

“A bit,” I said. “Right away, after you got the message from the Library?”

“Yeah,” she replied. “That obvious?”

“Hells no,” I said. “But there was a bit of subtext to the books that you wrote, times when it felt like you were talking directly to me, and not just in a literal way. Turns of phrase, I guess. It never really felt like you were different though, not really. I mean, different, kind of, in the sense that you were maybe a little bit more ready to touch me, or cuddle up on a couch together.”

“Can we talk about Fenn?” asked Amaryllis.

“Yeah?” I asked, stiffening slightly. “In the sense of … ?”

“I’m worried she’s going to come back,” said Amaryllis. “That’s the next obvious step, once things are stable between us. Or if we win, and you’re god at the end of this, then I guess you would bring her back, wouldn’t you?”

“You don’t consider her to actually be dead,” I said.

“I’d be a fool to,” replied Amaryllis. “Not that I’m calling you a fool.”

“This is a world where death is pretty much permanent,” I said. “I’ve made a lot of worlds, and people coming back from death … there are ways to make it work, but having death be cheap really alters things, and you can put in a bunch of exceptions where death is costly, or where death is sometimes for real, but Aerb pretty clearly went with a model where you can either die forever or live forever while being tortured in the hells. So no, I don’t think that Fenn is coming back.”

“Hypothetically, if she does, what are we going to do about it?” asked Amaryllis. “Assuming that it happens before godhood.”

“I don’t know, give her a hug, tell her we’re happy she’s returned?” I asked.

“And then say that we’re married?” asked Amaryllis.

“I get what you’re saying,” I replied. “I just … gaming out how to break an uncomfortable truth to someone is not really what I want to be doing right now. I don’t know if she’ll be pissed off, or if she is, whether it will be the kind of pissed off the fades quickly, or the kind that seems to last forever, and yeah, she might see it as a betrayal, but, I don’t know. I don’t know, okay?”

“Okay,” said Amaryllis. “It’s probably an irrational fear of mine.”

“A fear?” I asked.

“Of her coming back,” said Amaryllis. “Of interpersonal drama that I’m perfectly well equipped to handle but somehow won’t. I pride myself in being level-headed, but sometimes that just pisses people off, and Fenn meant a lot to me. I think about her being angry at me, and how I would deal with that, but trying to map it out on my own is fruitless because I have to consider you as well, and how you would interact with her. It’s so much easier to navigate people when you only have to navigate one of them at a time, or when their interests are material instead of emotional. I dealt with people a lot when I was a princess. I do it more now that I’m effectively running multiple different polities. It’s so much easier to do when it’s not about the internal mental states.”

“You never really talk about it,” I said. “Just here and there, I guess. I don’t have a firm grasp on the meetings or anything like that.”

“It’s boring,” said Amaryllis. “Even I think it’s boring sometimes. There are hundreds of people that I need to keep track of and talk with, each with their own beliefs, values, and personalities, some who need management, others who I need to make deals with — a lot of it is just keeping people aligned, or negotiating deals. I won’t say that it’s easy, because it’s not, but people have their levers. If I’m doing things right, there should be no thrill or excitement, because everything goes according to my meticulous plans. Every once in a while, someone will know something they weren’t supposed to know, or they’ll reveal something that I didn’t know, but that’s rare.”

“Huh,” I said. “Even the tuung?”

“Especially the tuung,” said Amaryllis. “I don’t think I ever told you this, but I have dossiers on all of them, looked over by Valencia, compiled by their teachers, and read through in their exhausting entirety by me during a three week stint in the time chamber when I did practically nothing else. They have their own needs, which need to be managed, but they have a culture that works well for that, one that I’m very proud of.”

Ask her about exclusion bounties.

I frowned. “Sorry for the interruption, but the call of the gold wants to know what you know about the exclusion bounties.”

“Ah,” said Amaryllis, backing away from me slightly. “I’ve been in negotiations with both Special Threats and Apportions about it. These things take time though. There are good reasons that there are no standing kill orders on any of the exclusions. If you dangle money in front of people, they’re liable to muck it up.”

Push her on that. Ask whether she has a rough estimate of income.

“These negotiations,” I said. “You’ve come up with some dollar amount though?”

“Obol amount, yes,” said Amaryllis. She was watching me, and a lot of the earlier warmth had evaporated. “The problem is that the financial value of ending some of these exclusions is, as in the case of Necrolaborem, actually negative. Exclusion zones have a way of making the land worthless. Very few of them have infrastructure, and in a few cases, they’ve already been cleared out. Most of the value to the empire is in the form of public relations, rather than any concrete monetary incentive. The incentives are a bit higher for polities that neighbor an exclusion, but negotiating with those would require additional legwork on my part. Legwork that I’m happy to do, but if we’re trying to extract money from exclusion slaying, it will, again, take time.”

“I think it’s looking for a precise obol figure,” I said. “What’s the value of the ones that I could, in theory, kill with only a few moments’ notice? That means Rove, the fleshsmiths, the Guardian, possibly whatever’s happening on the pink spot on Celestar, and maybe Pai Shep.” Everyone else ran the risk of me getting stuck, them no-selling me, or me outright losing.

“The best offer for Rove was a hundred thousand obols,” said Amaryllis. “That’s a pittance, I’m sure you’ll agree, but his exclusion is effectively a wasteland, and at least some of the stipulation of that offer is that we would come in and have first pick of whatever valuables he’d left in his wake. The empire has no interest in getting into the salvage business, apparently.”

“And the others?” I asked, not wanting to get another prompt from the call of the gold.

“Low sums, if at all,” replied Amaryllis. “Pai Shep is straight out, they don’t actually want him gone. Most of the people he killed have been dead for so long that no one really cares about them anymore, and he sends out produce, seemingly of his own volition, to the edge of the exclusion.”

“Shit, people don’t actually eat that stuff, do they?” I asked.

“Of course they do, Juniper, they’re people,” replied Amaryllis. “It’s free food at festival time. The empire allows it because they’re dependent on the kingdoms in question to lease land for monitoring, and the kingdoms allow it because it helps people believe that the exclusion zone isn’t a problem.”

“Which it’s arguably not,” I said. “The only reason that it qualifies as a major exclusion is that he kills anyone who crosses the border, and there are all kinds of nations that already do that.”

“I know you’re being hyperbolic, but it’s important to me that I clarify that’s not the policy of any polity, imperial or otherwise,” said Amaryllis.

Tell her to give you direct numbers that she knows.

“Alright, I don’t personally think you’re deflecting, but the gold entity would like some numbers, right now,” I said.

“Twelve million obols for the fleshsmiths, if they’re killed to the last, or otherwise deprived of their magic, five million for the Guardian, but I’m not actually sure you can beat him,” said Amaryllis. “Twenty million for destroying whatever destroyed Celestar, but you would have to bring back proof, and payment wouldn’t be through the Empire, it would be through the elves. I’m not confident that we would be able to actually get payment. Is that enough?”

“No complaints so far,” I said. “I think that was just fact finding on the entity’s part. You don’t think that I could take the Guardian?”

“I’m doubtful,” said Amaryllis.

“But he’s mostly an unknown, right?” I asked.

“That’s why I’m doubtful,” said Amaryllis. “It should go without saying, but it’s nothing against you.”

“Of course,” I replied. I waited for a moment. “I was really thinking that I would get a mission to go kill all the fleshsmiths.”

“You already have a quest,” said Amaryllis. “And if the entity knows everything that you know, then it knows that it probably won’t be as easy as nuking their city center. In fact, if it knows what you know and is particularly clever, then it knows that its best bet is to ensure that you keep doing more or less what you’re doing so that you can become a god and satisfy its needs in perpetuity. That probably personifies it too much though.”

“If it were capable of that kind of long-term planning and plan execution, I doubt that gold mages would look like they do,” I said. “They get pushed and pushed and pushed, until finally they either die trying to meet some objective, or give up entirely. That’s the same fate I’m going to reach, but I’m much more on the side of giving up entirely.”

“So you say,” replied Amaryllis. “It’s a whole lot of money to give up, just so you know.”

“It’s a quest-in-waiting,” I replied. “So the store is on Celestar, so what? Like we couldn’t figure out a way there given a cram session?”

“Still,” replied Amaryllis.

“I do think that we should be pushing harder, while I have the power,” I said. “This is literally a once-in-a-lifetime opportunity, and I feel like I’ve mostly been on standby, or running petty errands, or telling you to liquidate assets and transform them into gold. I mean … why shouldn’t I clear out the fleshsmiths of Pendleham? If nothing else, they have a lot of conceptual overlap for Fel Seed, so it would be a good trial run.”

“They’re still people,” said Amaryllis. “You’d be fine dropping down in there and blowing everything to pieces? Even with the thought that they might, in some way, represent a part of you?”

“Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle has thoroughly disabused me of the notion that everyone is worth saving. He’s worth saving for the greater good, but that’s it. That guy isn’t literally the worst, but he’s close.”

“So you would start killing, sight unseen, with no preamble?” asked Amaryllis.

I frowned. “Okay, you’re right.”

Kill them all, claim the reward.

“Fuck damn it,” I said. “I’m being told to. You’ll need to get cracking on completing those negotiations.”

“Are you actually going to do it?” asked Amaryllis.

“Looks like it, yeah,” I replied. “Might take Grak with me though, since I figure that’s the only way that I’ll actually get a chance to speak with anyone there, and if gold magic fails me, then that’s the only way that I’m getting out.”

“And your rest and relaxation is done here?” asked Amaryllis.

“Seems like it,” I said. “Get word to Grak, I’ll be in the air once I’ve had a chance to look at a map. We can use the Fourfold Flask to communicate and figure out a spot to pick him up at.”

“Sure,” replied Amaryllis.

Clerical Errors

The gods of Aerb were, in some respects, extremely important, but in most others, could be ignored entirely.

Gods were a real pain in the ass when it came to worldbuilding for tabletop games, at least for most of the systems that we’d played. The big problem was that gods had a real presence in the world, namely through clerics and paladins. They, in turn, provided real and true powers that no one could ever contest. That in and of itself wasn’t a huge issue, but it left the question of who these gods were, what their agendas were, why and how they had empowered people, and in general, a whole bunch of baggage that there weren’t all that many ways of filling, given how rigid the rules systems for divine magic typically were. The gods were also important to the characters, and thus had to be invented and defined early on, which I hated. I had, naturally, tried doing it a whole bunch of ways: from the nearly-atheist version where anyone could have clerical powers, even if they didn’t have faith or devotion, to gods-as-managers, always looking over your shoulder and ensuring that you were carrying out their will.

The gods themselves were tricky to do, because they were almost by definition the most important people in whatever setting they were in. That meant that the agendas they set would be of overriding concern for all the lesser players, and in turn, it would all trickle down. This was a problem for worldbuilding specifically because sometimes you just wanted to have a world that ran in a different direction, without concerning itself with matters of the divine, even if there was a cleric in the party (and there was typically a cleric in the party, because they tended to be great healers). If you wanted to cut gods out, or at least make it so that the religious concerns were of the more practical human social variety than the singular-figure-of-enormous-power kind, you needed to make them distant, or aloof, or ineffable, or something so that gods didn’t crowd out all the other fun stuff.

The gods of Aerb went far in the direction of aloofness, but it was a special kind of aloofness that played into their ineffability. Put simply, four of the five gods of Aerb didn’t really give a shit about people, and while they all had their domains, and granted limited powers within those domains to people who were recognizably clerics (and called such by the people of Aerb), their interests in those domains hewed very closely to the status quo.

Invreizen was the god of Ice and Sea, or more precisely, the god of Ice, Sea, Wind, Water, Rain, Clouds, Air, Birds, and Fish. What Invreizen wanted, so far as anyone could tell, was for the ice to be the ice, and the sea to be the sea, and so on through all his domains. Sailors rarely prayed to Invreizen, because why would they? It was the nature of the sea to sink ships, and thus, part of Invreizen’s agenda as well. Invreizen was the god of good weather and bad weather, and so far as he was concerned, weather was based on the fundamentals of high and low pressure systems, moisture and dryness, winds and evaporation and all that stuff. To change the weather would mean to make the weather go against the fundamentals that drove the weather, and thus make the weather unlike itself. Invreizen wouldn’t stand for that.

Where the gods acted, they acted against what they saw as fundamental attacks on the basic nature of their domains. Where the clerics acted, it was in the liminal spaces of definitions, or what they called the dialectics, those places where two aspects of a domain were somehow in tension with one another. A cleric of Invreizen couldn’t cast a spell like create water, a D&D mainstay, but what they could do instead was to heighten certain aspects of water. This was, to be plain, incredibly weak, but each god had enough domains to their name that being a cleric of a god got you access to a wide variety of weak powers. Clerics were still typically at the bottom of the barrel, at least as far as magical might went, but there were a few exceptional rule benders among them, and even a weak cleric could still earn a living, especially with the support of their church, namely because of their deep understanding of the domains, which came with extra senses that couldn’t easily be replicated.

When I’d created Invreizen, he’d been one of seven gods, an attempt to create an extremely broad pantheon. Aerb only had five gods, and I had no idea what had happened to the other two. Sonkrag had been a pretty classical sun god, possibly cut because of his secondary focus on mortal affairs like honor, justice, order, and law. Kennis had been the god of civilization, innovation, books, and metal, and my guess was that he likewise just didn’t make the cut. That left four gods with domains that were more focused on the natural world, and the last of the bunch, Truuk, who was a trickster god, not sprung from the same mold as the others, and the kind of god that people tended not to talk about unless it couldn’t be helped.

(The names of the gods were all Afrikaans. I want to be clear that I wasn’t at the level of being lazy by naming gods using Google Translate: I was at the level of naming gods using Google Translate, and picking Afrikaans because it was alphabetically first.)

The God Botherer quest I’d gotten ages ago could have, for all I was concerned, been put off indefinitely. I had personally named and designed all of the gods of Aerb. I knew their deal. From everything that I had read, they’d barely changed in their translation to Aerb, and that meant that they were, in a word, worthless, except for the fact that they nominated clerics, and on very rare occasions, would intercede in the world.

It was that last one we were hoping for. It was a slim hope, but Invreizen’s temple was very close to an errand I had to run, and it seemed like it was worth a shot, at least relative to what it would cost us.

The last time Invreizen had acted was one hundred and twenty-six years prior. Someone had invented something that they called ‘dry water’, and the following month, the edge of the sea had lifted up and then slammed down on his coastal city, killing roughly one hundred and fifty thousand people. Among the gods, and those who followed them, this was known as ‘answering heresy with heresy’, a god’s way of saying, “Oh, you think that water should not behave how it does? Then let’s see how you feel about a gross violation of the behavior of water.” This almost always meant death on a large scale, not because the gods weren’t capable of fine control of their domains, but because ‘fuck everyone in your general vicinity’ was just the way they operated.

Of course, they weren’t monsters. Part of the function clerics served was to use their understanding of the various domains of their god in order to advise on and police ‘godly matters’, which were mostly those areas where something impermissible might happen. For the most part, gods didn’t take drastic action, because for the most part, things obeyed their fundamental natures simply by definition, and virtually all magic that altered that fundamental nature was included within the domain.

Aside from his proximity to our destination, there was another reason we’d chosen to attempt the God Botherer quest. First off, Amaryllis had actually ‘met’ him once, which amounted to little more than a brief conversation at a dinner, which she assured me was more face time with a god than almost anyone got, and was much more impressive than I understood it to be. Second, I was an air mage and a water mage, both of which fell under his broad umbrella, and it was possible (though extremely uncommon) for him to grant boons on the worthy.

The city of Frustbury looked like it was spilling down into the plains from the top of a cliff, with the biggest buildings sitting on the clifftop, and the whole of the city getting smaller and less significant as you descended the gradient. The biggest of those buildings was the Yshuis, the primary residence and place of worship for Invreizen. It was unlike anything that I had seen on Aerb thus far, built at ridiculous fantasy scales that my brain had trouble making sense of. At the top, fifty stories up, protruded three thick, sculpted arms that were themselves a hundred yards long, and they held a glass bowl with a lake’s full of water.

It was ostentatious, and I was pretty sure that on Earth, it would have been impossible to do, since there was nowhere in the glass bowl to hide structural supports. It would also probably never have been allowed to be built, because if the bowl shattered, it would be a complete calamity for the city. Still, it was awe-inspiring, and I could see why it had been built, because as soon as you saw it, you felt something. Because of its position high up on the cliff, the building could be seen from miles away, both out at sea and anywhere in the surrounding countryside.

We made our way through the city, our core group of four: me, Grak, Amaryllis, and Raven. With Blue-in-the-Bottle dead, the situation in Necrolaborem had gotten worse, but it was being handled by the second generation tuung and the Amaryllis clones that she’d left behind, using the systems that we’d put in place. There were also contractors and imperial agents as well, probably thousands of people all told. It was in the back of my mind, but I was hopeful that it wouldn’t take up too much of our attention in the coming two weeks, because we were doing everything in our power to get ready for Fel Seed. That included meeting a god.

Up close, the outside of the Yshuis was just as impressive as I’d expected it to be. The walls were covered in ornamental sculpture, actually covered, every inch, except where there were windows. All I could think of, when looking at it, was the man-hours that it would have taken for all of that to get done, my mind barely taking in the subjects of the sculptures and bas reliefs themselves, which were endless scenes of Invreizen’s domains, everything that he controlled and watched over, all the adjacencies and overlaps, everything at increasingly high levels of specificity. There were barnacles, mollusks, sharks, squid, pretty much every creature of Aerb’s many seas. There were ships of many sizes, seaweed that had been sculpted so that it almost looked like it was in motion. When viewed from a distance, there was a pronounced difference in how the sculptures had been done so that even when you couldn’t see the individual pieces, you could see a picture writ large on the side of this enormous building: it was a map of Aerb, but just of the seas, oceans, rivers, and major lakes, and no attention paid whatsoever to anything like mountains, cliffs, forests, roads, or cities.

I tried not to be awestruck. I had no love for the gods of Aerb, but I could at least respect that they were open about how evil they were, rather than pretending at benevolence. The expected outcome of the meeting with Invreizen was that he would tell us no, or just not say anything and allow his head cleric to tell us no, and the whole trip would have all been for nothing. It was low cost, low risk, and a low expected reward, but the best outcomes were really really good. You couldn’t talk a god into killing Fel Seed but you could potentially talk him into providing a boon, or a distraction, or some information, if you were lucky. Failing that, he had clergy, who were semi-important movers and shakers on Aerb.

I’d had a penchant for designing supremely powerful religious organizations into campaign worlds, partly as a counterbalance to the rough wilds I liked to include, partly as mildly antagonistic forces that could contain rogue sects and other complications for the players. There were all kinds of fun things you could do if you had some equivalent to the Catholic Church at the height of its power, like inquisitions, crusades, and conspiracies driven by religious fervor. The religious orders on Aerb were, by comparison, nearly powerless, paling in comparison to the athenaeums, most major countries, and the empire itself. A big problem for them was that their gods were demonstrably apathetic toward the mortal species, and there were few levers that they could press in order to bring the populace around. People still prayed, and occasionally went to temples or churches, but a lot of that was just the normal rhythms of community life.

This city was the heart of Invreizen’s power though, and this building was a representation of him in all his glory, a massively expensive structure that was meant to be beyond compare, as if it were a way of saying, ‘Yes, gods exist in this world, and they are Important, so don’t you go forgetting it’. Of course, if the gods really had been all that important, their clergy might not have felt the need to use awe-inspiring architecture in order to reinforce it.

In the center of the Yshuis was a huge courtyard, with all the building’s elevators running up the inside walls. Three large, vertical aquariums that ran up the sides as well, each of them filled with fish, corals, seaweed, and bright colors that contrasted the grey skies above us. It had a beauty to it, and the walls weren’t smooth, they looked like waves, not just textured, but with rooms bulging out and windows curving. As a work on art, I was there for it. There was something transcendental about the building, and there was something aching about the fact that we didn’t have time to explore and appreciate it. I was sure that whatever team had designed this place, they had left fractal points of interest, details, symmetries, concordances, on and on. It just seemed like that kind of place.

There were lots of people around, divided up into the clergy, who mostly wore shades of blue, and everyone else, who wore the usual riot of styles common through the empire. ‘Clergy’ was a broad role, because it included people who were definitely not clerics, those in charge of various aspects of running the building and organizing the religion. We were guided by one of those clergy, a man in a royal navy suit that had a button flap thing across the front I was sure Amaryllis would know the name of, if I cared enough to ask.

We had the elevator to ourselves, and twice when it stopped on the way to the top, people took one look at us and begged off. It wasn’t likely that they recognized us by sight, but we had the look of rich and important people, decked out in entads and looking like we were ready for war. No one had asked us to remove our weapons, but I wasn’t sure they knew we had weapons, since almost everything offensive was packed away in some kind of extradimensional space or another, ready to be in our hands at a moment’s notice.

We came out in the upper area, just beneath one of the giant arms that held up the fish bowl. I could feel the weight of it above me, a catastrophe waiting to happen, and wondered about the brass balls of the people who had conceived this and made it into reality. Our guide answered a question from Grak that I hadn’t been paying much attention to, and explained that the bowl had been filled over the course of a few years by natural weather, and that keeping it clean was a full-time job. The bowl was filled with fish and other ocean creatures, but they must have done something to the inside of it, because there was no way that it would have stayed as clean as it was even with intervention, and there was a noticeable lack of fish poop on the bottom of it.

Invreizen himself was up there, which I’d have known even if I hadn’t been told, because it would have been hard to explain the fifty-foot long dolphin swimming around in there otherwise. The scale of everything was disorienting, which was probably part of what the architects had in mind.

There were lots of people milling about, most of them (from what I understood) either tourists or self-styled pilgrims, there in order to get a look at a god and maybe, if they were lucky, have some kind of story to tell when they got back home. There was something like Earth-standard religion, in the way that people could see this concrete source of immense and awe-inspiring power and take some solace in the fact that there was some order to the world, someone who was responsible for the way things were. Invreizen had killed people, sure, and sat by while even more died in ways that he clearly could have prevented, but if you had Invreizen, then you could believe that there was some great and grand order, some protector that was there as a guiding hand to make sure that nothing went too far off the rails.

Some of how I saw the gods on Aerb was colored by how I’d seen Christianity on Earth, but I didn’t think that I was making a mistake when the rapturous expressions on the faces looking up at Invreizen seemed similar. It was something I’d seen often enough at church, a giddy excitement about the greatness of god that I wasn’t sure I’d ever felt myself.

“When you speak to him, be very respectful,” said Amaryllis.

“I will be,” I replied. “I can’t promise that my acting will be good enough to fool a god, but I can try.”

“It’s extremely unlikely that you’ll have a chance to speak with Invreizen for any length of time,” said our escort.

“Sure,” I said. I stared up at the big bowl of water, watching the god idly swim around. If I looked closely, I could just barely see holes in the palm of one hand holding up the bowl, which must have been either access or piping, with water or personnel being carried down through a hollow arm. I was extremely interested in the logistics of this absurd work of art, but in a way, it felt like trying to figure out how a magic trick was done. My eyes kept going back to Invreizen. He wasn’t quite a dolphin, because he had a more rounded nose, and the tail was slightly different.

I froze for a moment as my brain made the connection, and it was noticeable enough that Amaryllis shifted her stance slightly, preparing herself to take some drastic action.

“So,” I said, my eyes not leaving the god’s form. “When you become a cleric of Invreizen, you might say that you’re called to serve a higher porpoise?”

I grinned at him, and Amaryllis shot me a scowl. I was pretty sure she was going to stab me in the stomach the next time we had a quiet moment together.

“Ah, yes,” our escort said. He looked at Amaryllis, then back to me. “I was told that you would only be here for a few hours? Is there anything that we can help you with in that time, if Invreizen elects not to take company?”

“Help how?” I asked.

“With information, perhaps?” he asked.

“Ah, no,” I replied. “We’ve done our own research, and Raven here is the best librarian that the world has ever known.”

“Most likely fifth best,” Raven replied. “But likely the best living. I don’t have enough information about the goblins to say for certain whether they might have someone better. Regardless, there’s unlikely to be any information you could share I don’t already know, and I’ve personally been in attendance at conversations with all five gods.”

“All … five?” asked our escort. Visiting all four gods wasn’t too uncommon, if you had the time and money to do it, and if you visited often enough, then eventually you might get something approaching a conversation with one. The fifth god was special though, not a part of the normal worship of god botherers, not with any stable base of clerics, not with a city built around him, and not even what you’d call the same type of being as the other four, save that they claimed him as one of their own. It was considered best practice not to say his name.

Raven only nodded, and the subject was dropped. Our escort looked like he wanted nothing to do with us, and I didn’t think that was because of the porpoise pun.

“Fewer people than I thought, actually,” I finally said, looking at the crowds that stood on the ring, most of them staring up at the bowl. I was really hoping that we didn’t have to wait for hours for this all to come to nothing.

“The fee is calculated,” said our escort, seeming happy to have something to contribute. “We try our best to make sure that on normal days, there are only as many people as you see now, enough that it doesn’t feel too crowded. On holy days, the fees are lowered, so that more might come, though Invreizen rarely makes his presence known at those times, save at a distance, or through his domains.”

I said nothing, because what I was thinking was that this was all probably precisely calculated to make the church as much money as it possibly could. Given Invreizen was, at best, extremely negligent about mortals, it all seemed like kind of a rip off. There was a better case to be made for him if you considered the works of his clerics to be his doing as well, but they didn’t exclusively work in his service; they had their own goals that were more closely aligned to that of mortals in general. In a lot of ways, Invreizen and the others were closer to Great Old Ones who mortals made their own deals with, hoping not to suffer for it.

I was watching Invreizen when he transitioned, changing from an oversized porpoise into an oversized octopus in an instant. Normally if entads did something like that, there was some kind of effect, a melding, a shimmering, something, but with him it was sheer discontinuity, like it had happened in the gap between two frames of a movie, albeit in a way that didn’t even slightly disturb the water he was in or fish he was swimming around with. The octopus swam to the edge of the huge bowl, next to one of the immense arms, heaved itself up, then began crawling its way down the forearm, wrapping its tentacles around the beautifully sculpted muscles.

“It looks like you’re in luck,” said our escort, smiling a bit. That smile faded when the octopus reached the roof and began slowly and deliberately moving our way.

When Invreizen reached us, he changed form again, this time to something humanoid, one of the aquatic species with webbed feet and hands. He was much smaller, and it occurred to me that if he really was like the gods I’d designed, then he was a cheater, because he should have been a regular-sized porpoise, or a regular-sized octopus. My second thought was that perhaps Aerb had creatures like that in its expansive oceans, propped up by magic and special adaptations. The merman he’d chosen was tall, probably an exemplar of the species, but not unreasonable.

“Juniper Smith,” he said, then gave me a low bow.

I stared at him, and Amaryllis yanked at my arm, pulling me down to my knees, prostrate in front of the god. In response, Invreizen bowed lower, until his nose was pressed against the floor.

I stood up, despite Amaryllis giving me every signal at her disposal that I shouldn’t. When I did, Invreizen got to his feet.

Around us was silence.

The silence stretched on for what seemed like too long, and I got the distinct impression that he was waiting on me, though I had no idea what for.

“Water you waiting for?” I thought but didn’t say.

“Is there a reason you wanted to sea me?” I didn’t ask him.

“It seems a little bit fishy that you know my name,” I didn’t reply.

(Look, a lot of blame for these thoughts can be laid squarely at Amaryllis’ feet, because she’d had us spend three hours in a meeting trying to think up Fel Seed puns, in case one of them was the key to this whole ordeal and could give us victory in some way by figuring it out ahead of time. It started out fun, but by the time we’d gotten twenty minutes in, I was ready to be done, and by the time the meeting finished, it felt like I’d gone through a whole character arc.)

“We have been watching you with great interest,” he finally said.

There was some commotion about that, because everyone who’d been on the ring with us had come to hear what Invreizen had to say (though the building was big enough that people were still making their way over). Most of them had probably been expecting the god to talk in slightly cryptic language, or to wax rhapsodic about some aspect of one of his domains, which he often did. They most likely weren’t expecting this to be about me personally.

“You sent your clerics to watch me?” I asked.

“No,” he replied. “I speak of communication between myself and the other gods.”

There were more murmurs about that. The gods didn’t openly admit to communication very often, as they lived in a state of rather frosty diplomacy (especially frosty in Invreizen’s case (har har)).

“You think that I’m the next Uther?” I asked. I was a little on edge. He could kill in the blink of an eye, with no possible defense against it, given that I was mostly made of water. In the past, people who thought that I was Uther reincarnated had a habit of trying to kill me, with only a few exceptions. Maybe it just felt that way, because I dealt a lot more with the people trying to kill me than the people who were trying to stay out of my way.

“We do not know what you are,” replied Invreizen. “You are a hole in the order of the world, a force which we cannot account for.”

“In what sense?” I asked.

“I am the ultimate master of my domains,” replied Invreizen.

“Okay,” I said, when it was clear he wasn’t going to continue. “And?”

“Where you go, the water does not speak,” said Invreizen. “Where you go, the water continues along on its own, with no shepherd to guide it if it goes astray.”

“Uh,” I said. Fucking cryptic god bullshit. “You’re saying that your powers … don’t work on me?”

He nodded, slowly.

“Well, look,” I said. “That’s not anything that I did, and so long as the water is still water, so long as it fulfills its water essence, so long as I’m not interfering with it being water, that’s not a problem, right?”

“There is no way to answer any heresy,” replied Invreizen. “There is no way to even tell that heresy has been committed.”

“Well, I haven’t,” I said, feeling a little worried. “I’ve been using water like water, same with ice, with the seas, with all of your domains. I’m not a heretic.”

“My brothers and sisters report the same,” said Invreizen. “We can tell where you are by paying attention to where we are deaf, dumb, and blind.”

I waited. It sounded like an accusation to my ears, but it obviously wasn’t anything that I had done. More to the point, it was pretty obviously Dungeon Master interference, either directly, or through some mechanism he controlled. Was it important for some future plot point that I be invisible to the gods? Or was it just to stop them from helping me? If I was hearing Invreizen right, then it was impossible for me to get smacked down by the angry hand of a god, which seemed like a boon, but … well, let’s just say that I always looked gift horses in their mouths where the Dungeon Master seemed to be involved.

Our conversation felt incredibly awkward, because I was trying my best to interpret what he said, and wanted to make sure that I wasn’t speaking out of turn. Unfortunately, someone took the silence as their moment to interject.

“Your worship,” said a man who was standing near me, dressed in clerical blues. “Is communion with other gods —”

Invreizen raised his hand, a very casual gesture, and the man’s water was blasted backward, out of his body. The desiccated corpse fell to the ground with a sound like dry twigs, and then the screaming started from the people around us, which I muted out with vibration magic. It was only because of multithreading that I was able to do that and keep my focus on the god.

It was undeniably frightening, not just that Invreizen could do something like that, and would do something like that, but that he had done it. It took the intellectual understanding of his abilities and disposition into the realm of the real and concrete. From what he’d said, he couldn’t do the same to me, but I had no clue whether that extended to my companions, and obviously there were levers to use against me, like my basic desire for other people not to die.

“Amaryllis,” I said calmly. “Bottle him, please.”

Amaryllis hesitated, maybe worried that it would put her in danger, but she moved all the same once she saw that no one else was moving to ensure the dead man’s soul wouldn’t wind up in the hells. Bottling him was basic decency, but it also wouldn’t do for the infernals to get a hold of this conversation. I glanced nervously at the people near us who were still holding their big, bulky recording devices and worried a bit about how far and wide this conversation would reach. I should probably have been muting the whole thing right from the start, but that had seemed presumptuous. Better late than never though, and I layered the effect of restricting the conversation to just the two of us on top of locking out the screams of panic, which were now dying out.

“What can I do to allay your concerns?” I asked Invreizen.

“There is no need for you to do anything,” he replied. “By your nature you have nothing to worry about.”

“Call it empathy then,” I said. “I’d like it better if the gods weren’t fretting about me. Is there anything that I can do or say? Some promise you’d like me to keep?”

“I would like to see you, as deeply as I can,” he replied.

“Very well,” I said, after a moment’s thought to what that might mean.

He changed, all at once, with the same utter lack of transition. It should have at least caused a little pop from displaced air, but there wasn’t even that. One moment he was an oversized merman, the next he was a creature I had never seen before, and which very possibly didn’t exist on Aerb at all. He had three mouths and eighteen different eyes of all different shapes and sizes, some of them mounted on tentacles, others set into what passed for his face. It was an utter Cronenberg nightmare creature, asymmetrical and ugly, so much so that I wondered whether it had been selected for exactly that purpose.

Invreizen looked at me, and through the Crown of Eyes, I did too.

There was a point to having all those different eyes, and it must have been in order to get as full a picture of me as was possible. My guess was that he’d taken eye designs from every sea creature, living or extinct, as well as some that were theoretical, biological apparatuses from sea birds, and from other creatures where they fell within his domains. I didn’t get access to anything that wasn’t a proper eye, or at least an eye within a degree of reasonableness, but it was still a lot.

Invreizen could see the magic all around me, and see straight through my armor and clothing. He could see hidden patterns on my skin, anatomical stripes and whorls that I’d known existed but never seen on a person except in crude line diagrams, Kraissl’s lines, Langer’s lines, Blaschko’s lines, hidden variations that came from the migrations of embryonic cells as I’d grown up. I could see my organs, and the structure of my bones, the flow of my blood, the food working its way through my digestive system, the saliva coating my teeth inside my mouth, the ridges of my brain. I could see the magic that infused much of my body, and the color of my soul. I could even see into my soul itself, through Invreizen’s eyes, and I thought to warn him about looking at the meme there, but if a god could be brought low by a meme … well I had to imagine that if it were possible, it would have already happened.

There was something else he saw though, beyond the totality of my earthly existence, and into the metaphysical. There was something on me, almost too bright to look at with whatever biological or magical instrumentation he was staring at it with, bright enough that he seemed to go blind in whatever eye was staring at the metaphysical nexus.

And then, unexpectedly, he was finished, back to a different form, this one a humanoid creature of water with a mouth and vocal tract visible inside the water, the only solid, organic parts of him. He no longer had eyes for me to see through.

At almost the same moment, at first through the Crown of Eyes, I realized that I was seeing things through a new but familiar perspective, the world as an abstract, metaphorical piece of art.

The locus was standing beside me.

As seen through her eyes, Invreizen was distinctly lacking in grandeur. He was large, true, but rather than any of the awe-inspiring or larger-than-life forms he’d taken so far, he was a fish, one that lay on the ground, breathing heavily with dull eyes. There was no respect in how she saw him, nothing like acknowledgement of his status as a deity.

He gave her a bow, and she dipped her head in response.

“One should not be surprised by the impossibility of a locus,” said Invreizen.

I watched the two of them watching each other. Neither had a body language that I spoke, and through the doe’s eyes, all I could get was a sense of her disdain toward him. From him, in this water form that had only the mechanisms necessary to make mouth noises, it was anyone’s guess. Maybe it was her interpretation that made me think of him as a dull and uninspiring fish.

“When did your blindness to me start?” I asked Invreizen. “When did the gods first notice it?”

“Not long ago,” he replied. “No more than a moon, though it wasn’t obvious, at first.”

“I see,” I replied. “Then it was probably the locus, protecting me.”

“That is now the inescapable conclusion,” replied Invreizen. “It is mollifying, as a locus can be killed.”

“I don’t think that it would ever need to come to that,” I said, though I had no idea whether anything the locus had done would rise to the level of heresy in the eyes of the god. Certainly the locus was capable of manipulating lots of natural materials, but surely — well, I couldn’t be sure, not without consulting a gaggle of clerics, or Raven’s supply of books from the past and future. I had looked into the nature of the locus, but there had been very little written on their interactions with the gods, only some notes about the perceived similarities between the two entities. There was, apparently, a metaphysical link between us, one visible through some kind of eye that Invreizen had been able to make.

“There is nothing more to discuss,” he said, turning away from me. “The source of the confusion is now clear, though no less confusing for it, and if there is a threat, it is in some capacity known.”

I wanted to ask whether he wasn’t curious about the locus being here, outside her domain, or, if he could see the way I extended the domain, whether he wanted to ask questions about why her domain surrounded me. I kept my mouth shut though, because there was still a dead man not far from us.

Ask for gold from him, said the call of the gold.

What the actual fuck, I thought back. I am not going to risk my life to beg for gold that he wouldn’t even give me.

Do it now, replied the call of the gold. Trade on your relationship with the locus.

Fuck you, man, first off, no way that works, second, that’s a betrayal of the locus. I was getting more upset the more I ‘talked’ to the call. Of all the fucking things that it could have asked for, this was one of the most irritating.

Invreizen began striding across the ring, past his clerics and supplicants, whose pleas and questions he wasn’t even pretending he was going to answer.

You need me, said the call of the gold.

I grit my teeth, trying my best to keep my face perfectly expressionless. Most of the attention was on Invreizen, but some fraction of the crowd we’d attracted had decided that I was the one to watch. The mood was decidedly muted, given the corpse that was now being put onto a stretcher, but almost everyone who would make this kind of trip was well-apprised of the temperaments of gods.

“Invreizen,” I called, striding toward the god, raising my voice to be heard but trying to keep my tone professional. “There’s another matter.”

“Oh?” he asked, turning toward me. He altered his form again, this time to become a tall, well-muscled woman with gills at her neck, some kind of hybrid of species, I was guessing. He — she, rather — was completely nude.

“We’re going against Fel Seed,” I said. “We need resources.”

I made sure to tamp down with vibration magic, but there were limits on how much could be done, and if there were another vibration mage, they’d have all sorts of ways to boost the signal back up so they could listen in. I wasn’t good enough to stop every avenue of attack. It was much harder to constrain his side of things so that only I could hear it, and though I was trying, I didn’t think I was doing a good enough job.

“If you know anything at all about the gods, then you know that our hands do not move lightly, especially not for elements outside our domains.” He seemed on more sure footing now than he had at the start, still with a bit of deference, but aimed at the locus, rather than at me. I wasn’t sure whether he was viewing me as merely a cleric or what, but he seemed to think that he’d solved whatever puzzle I had posed. It was clear that his mind changing wasn’t to my benefit.

“In Fel Seed’s zone, there’s a dimensional tunnel, one that leads to another world, which threatens to overrun our own,” I said. “Fel Seed is guarding against invasion, after a sort, but he doesn’t have our mutual interests at heart. The tunnel is a pathway to a world filled with heresies, and likewise, an avenue for those heresies to spill out into Aerb. Not long ago, we found the remains of a soldier who had made it through.”

He watched me for a moment. “You’re telling the truth,” he said.

“Yes,” I nodded. Technically. I wasn’t willing to lie to him, but I was willing to stretch the truth a bit. Earth was a place of heresy, so far as I understood it, if only for the complete lack of magic. “Please,” I said. “We need something, whatever you can offer.”

Gold, said the call of the gold. Or something that can be sold for gold.

I didn’t respond to that. I would have been happier with a boon, personally, or maybe one of us being made into a cleric, which was pure upside and had some nice overlap with my existing magics.

“You are far from the first to suggest that there is some heresy that must be met by action,” he said.

“You said yourself that I’m telling the truth,” I replied. I didn’t know how he thought he knew that. I was a mage of two of his domains, and thus fell more under his dominion than a normal human, but if I was somehow under the protection of the locus, then I didn’t know how that helped him.

“The truth can be as mercurial as water,” said Invreizen.

“You have resources at your command,” I said. “The least you could do is confirm for yourself whether or not there’s anything to what I have to say.”

“I’ve already done that,” he replied.

“You’ve looked into the zone with your godly vision?” I asked. “And?”

“There are truths that are not truths, and truths that mortal minds are not to know,” said Invreizen, giving me a sagely nod of the head, as though that were wise.

Push him on the matter of financial assistance.

“You have clerics,” I said. “At your word, we could have their assistance. You have money that we could use in order to finally defeat Fel Seed and secure the tunnel.” I had no idea how to outright ask for gold, and I was worried that Invreizen would decide, on a whim, to simply kill me, which I had no defense against except (apparently) the locus, who was still standing beside me, and whose domain followed me around.

“Matters of the church are left to the church,” replied Invreizen.

Threaten to go into p-space and alter the fundamental definitions of his domains, said the call of the gold.

I stood there, trying to think about how to speak what the call of the gold was asking me to speak. I could see the connection between p-space, the Platonic Realm of Thoughts and Ideas, and the definitional reality of the gods, but it wasn’t something that I had any concrete knowledge of, it was just a hunch. Threatening Invreizen would have been bad enough, but to do it with what might have been a paper sword … that would be insanity. The payoff could have been huge, even if I’d be making a very powerful enemy, but to actually do it —

Now, or lose the power forever. The locus will protect you. He has no recourse.

I needed gold magic. I needed it, it was the only way I could see that we could get through Fel Seed without it being grossly reckless. But this, if this wasn’t the line, then I didn’t know where the line would ever be. It wasn’t just the threat, it was the dependence on the locus to ensure that I couldn’t be eliminated, and the locus and I were — almost, kind of, friends, I guessed. Even if we weren’t, she didn’t deserve being used like that.

“Nevermind,” I said. “Forget that I asked.”

I was hoping that it was an idle threat, that I would get a second chance, but no, I felt the power leave me almost at once, the extra senses fading away.

Achievement Unlocked: Gold Standards

Quest Completed: God Botherer - You have made it through a conversation with a god without getting yourself obliterated, albeit at some minor cost. This text should not be taken as an implication that you can’t still screw it up somehow.

I breathed out a bit, then when Invreizen seemed to have no response, I walked away as quickly as I could.

“Fuck,” I said as I walked away. “Fuck fuck.”

“Gold magic?” asked Amaryllis, taking up a place at my side as I moved. On the other side was the locus, who was attracting considerable attention. People probably didn’t know or understand what it was, but they knew that it was some kind of magic.

“Gold magic is gone,” I replied.

“Okay,” she said. “I’d wondered.”

“We’ll talk more later,” I said. “Somewhere safer.”

We had, at some point, lost our escort. Maybe he didn’t think it was safe to stick around, or maybe he thought that escorting us was more of a hazard than he was getting paid for, but he was nowhere to be seen, and we were left to descend down the elevator on our own. The locus looked as though she was debating getting into the elevator car with us, but after a moment, she elected to evaporate instead, with us in spirit only.

“What happened?” Amaryllis asked, once we were seated on the train. We had a cabin for just the four of us, small enough that we could all sit within range of Grak’s built-in wards.

“Raven,” I said. “Do the definitions used by the gods live, in some sense, in p-space?”

“Uh,” she replied. “I don’t think it ever came up, or if it did, then I wasn’t privy to it. Is that … true?”

“I don’t know,” I said. “I had a hunch that it was. The call of the gold wanted me to threaten Invreizen with something like that, I don’t know if it had some special understanding, or if it was just using my guess, but — I probably would have done it, but the only protection I had was the locus.”

“You understand that we weren’t privy to most of what was said?” asked Amaryllis. “You muted it.”

“Sorry,” I said. “Way, way too hard to do it any other way. I’m not yet a comprehensive audio system.”

I had to explain what had passed between Invreizen and myself for them, which took some time.

“Not a tragedy then,” said Grak, the first to give his input after a moment of silence.

“Were you not listening?” I asked. “Gold magic is gone. It’s a huge setback.”

“Of all the ways that it might have failed us, to fail in defense of a friend was good,” said Grak.

I blinked at him. “I guess,” I said.

“Far better than to have the issue pressed when we were in Fel Seed’s zone,” said Amaryllis.

“Or while you were in the middle of a long flight,” said Raven.

“It does throw a wrench in the works though,” I said. I was feeling a little bit warm. I hadn’t expected anyone to congratulate me for doing what seemed like the right thing.

“It does,” nodded Amaryllis. “But it’s nothing that cripples us, not as far as our near-term plans go. I’ll put a halt to liquidation, and we’ll have to be cautious about the threats that have been waiting in the wings. Best to not reveal that you’ve lost the power, because I worry that we’ll have dragons on us if they know.”

“I doubt it,” said Raven. “The dragons left Uther alone, once he proved their equal.”

“If he kills a dragon, shame on Uther, if he kills a second dragon, shame on the dragon?” I asked.

“Something like that,” she said, giving me a little smile. “At least, so far as I understand dragons.”

“Am I right that we got essentially nothing from that meeting?” I asked. “Maybe a little insight into the ways in which the locus is similar to a god, but that’s nothing that I haven’t read about in textbooks. That the locus has been offering me protection … good to know, I guess, but it means that the locus is a lot more powerful than I’d thought, or at least godlike in unknown ways.”

“No hints on what you might need in order to further resolve the locus’ situation?” asked Amaryllis.

“There’s one thing I haven’t tried,” I said. “But that’s going to have to wait until after we get back.”

“Our plans haven’t changed?” asked Amaryllis.

“So far as I’m concerned, the god was a distraction,” I replied. “The real work lies ahead of us.”

A Lost Friend

There were a lot of salient facts about Aerb, but the one that I kept coming back to was that it was really heckin’ big. What was more, it was big in a lot of ways that Earth wasn’t.

I had never really been a huge fan of open world games like Skyrim and Assassin’s Creed, but I’d played one or two of them, mostly because I’d been a believer in making sure that I had a good sampling of every genre. One of the things that I’d noticed was that they all had way too much stuff in them, all of it packed too closely together. Some of that was surely because of resource constraints, the fact that even if you were cloning things over and reusing assets, you would eventually run into space limits, or if you tried to spread things out, you’d be wasting the labor of your artists and programmers on the stuff that wasn’t fun. But most of why they clumped so much together was ‘fun’; it probably wouldn’t be that hard to generate vast expanses of featureless land, bereft of anything interesting, but what would that really add? Verisimilitude and a sense of size, mostly. People who played those games didn’t want that though, they wanted a jaw-dropping vista at every turn, they wanted to be able to randomly stumble across cool things rather than trudging through thirty farms in a row that were broken up by small towns that were virtual clones of each other.

Aerb was like that, in a way. It had its fair share of sameness, but there were what seemed to be too many points of interest to me, too many things that were new and interesting. On Earth, you could dress up Vancouver so that it was almost any city in the world, but on Aerb … well, entad architecture was a part of it, and the athenaeums were definitely exceptional, but there seemed to me to be more history, more variability, so many different species, so much that was exceptional, because the base rules just weren’t the same.

The Athenaeum of Claw & Clocks seemed like one of those places that probably had a couple of hundred different quest lines running through it, and that was the impression just from looking at it, before you heard its long and impressive history (though it was much diminished in the modern age thanks to exclusions). Each of the buildings seemed like the kind of grand place that you would find an NPC waiting with a little exclamation mark above his head. The melange of cultures and peoples meant that there were a thousand points of conflict, hidden tensions and ways of mixing things up that made it all seem so expansive and never-ending.

I had wanted somewhere casual for the meetup, like a coffee shop or a teahouse, or whatever kind of place they had, but Grak had pointed out that this was a rather stupid idea that just wasn’t possible for someone of my stature, nor wise given the sensitive nature of the things that we would likely be discussing.

We had instead procured a room at Claw & Clocks that was normally used for therapy sessions, though Grak spent enough time and concordance on the wards that I was pretty sure it would have been about as efficient to use any other room anywhere else in the city. The room was one of those bland kinds of places with inoffensive artwork, which I guess suited its intended use. Compared to the city around us, it was a little bit grating. We could have been having a light lunch while watching a parade of strange peoples going by, but instead, we would be somewhere generic.

Tiff was a little bit late, so I spent a lot of my time just sitting there, wringing my hands and thinking about how I would approach things, gaming out the conversation to come. None of it mattered, not in the grand scheme of things. Nothing hinged on what we might say to each other, there were no revelations waiting in the wings, fuck it, she wasn’t even really the Tiff I had known back on Earth.

She came into the room with her head slightly down, closing the door behind her. When she saw me, she stopped, as though she was surprised to see me, but maybe she was just surprised by what I looked like, or what I was wearing. I’d thought about dressing like I had in high school, either in Earth clothes or as close to what I wore on Aerb, but there had been too much of a physical change to pretend, and my guess was that it might have a bit of an uncanny effect.

She sat down on the couch opposite me and smoothed down her skirt. She was simply dressed, just a t-shirt, skirt, and a bag that was just a bit too unigendered for me to call it a purse. She didn’t look much different from how I’d remembered, nor too different from how Bethel had displayed her, which was a little sickening to think about, because it meant that Arthur had spent time getting the illusion right.

“So,” she said. “Mr. Smith, I presume.”

“Yeah,” I said.

“Only, not,” said Tiff. “Or not really.”

“Kind of,” I said. “I — I didn’t know the Juniper that you knew, but from what everyone has told me, we were … I don’t know, kind of close to one another. Proxies.”

“You never had trouble telling fantasy from reality,” said Tiff.

“No,” I said. I watched her for a moment. “Otherwise you might think that this was all a delusion of mine.”

She nodded. “Tell me what you remember of how things were between you and me.”

I hesitated, trying to think about what she was really asking about. “You gave me a ride home after a session,” I said. “My parents were being just … the worst, I guess, so we went to your place instead. Your parents had left you home alone, so it was kind of — there was an implicit invitation, and you said in very explicit terms that it wasn’t like that, so I told you that I had a huge crush on you. And then you said you felt the same way.” I watched her for a moment. “Did that night — did it happen for you the same way?”

“Do they have cars, on Earth?” she asked. “We did a group project on the dream skewered. Arthur thought it would be right up your alley, because you liked thinking up new worlds. It was a little frustrating how incomplete all the books were.”

“We have cars, yeah,” I said. “But they don’t run on souls, they run on something called gasoline, which is derived from a type of oil, which is created by the action of heat and pressure on the corpses of microscopic plants and animals over the course of millions of years.”

She crossed her legs. “That sounds made up.”

“It does, a bit,” I replied. “Sorry, I wasn’t trying to say it in the most ridiculous way that I could, that’s just how it came out. You probably didn’t need the long explanation. I could have just said that we have cars the same as you do, even if that’s only partially true. I’ve been nervous about seeing you.”

“Do you remember what we were talking about, that night?” asked Tiff.

“No,” I replied. “Or, I do, but saying what we were talking about — it wouldn’t make sense to you.”

“Tell me anyway?” she asked.

“Unicorns,” I said. “It was — Earth doesn’t have unicorns, except in fiction, so I’d put my own version of them into a game, which are, more or less, exactly how they are on Aerb. Why, what was it for you?”

“Penqans,” she said. “They’re a legendary and supposedly apocryphal creature. You made up your own version to put into the game.”

I frowned. “I’m not familiar, either with the old version or the new one.”

She shrugged. “It’s really not important.” She must have seen disappointment on my face, because she continued on. “Penqans are a legend from the Zorish Isles,” she said. “They’re a kind of forest sprite. As the legend goes, a girl who gets lost in the woods will be guided by the penqans, not to her home, but to a good match for a marriage bond. If they come across an adulteress though, they’ll bewitch her and lead her through the forest until she dies of thirst or starvation.”

“Huh,” I said. “I can see how you wouldn’t like that.”

“Can you?” she asked, raising an eyebrow.

“And I suppose my version of them would have been more about leading people to destinies that they didn’t want,” I said. “Something about sacrifice for the greater good? Or rewarding people for falling into social roles?”

Tiff nodded. “It was a fun fight, as those things went. The less we acted like stereotypes, the better we did. As I recall, it took us a few hints to actually get it.” She smiled a little, a soft, sad smile. “I do miss it.”

“I’m sorry,” I said.

“Yeah?” she asked. “Me too.”

“For what?” I asked.

“For abandoning you,” she replied, looking down. “At the time, it felt like I didn’t have a choice, like I was going to watch you self-destruct and get caught in the blast no matter what I did. It felt like I was going to suffer wounds. Scars, even. I cut and ran. I was a coward about it. I should have at least formally broken up with you, even if it was just in a letter.”

“Huh,” I said. “I guess I never thought you’d have regrets.”

“Not regrets, per se,” she replied. “If I could do it over again, I would probably do the same thing. But there were prices to be paid, harm inflicted on you, and it was shitty for you. This is that kind of apology. Not one where I say that I was wrong, one where I say that I was right.”

“Ah,” I replied.

“Now would be a good time for you to apologize too,” she said. “I wouldn’t put it that bluntly, but it’s painfully obvious that you’re wanting to spit something out.”

“Yeah,” I said. “No, you’re right, I was just … putting it off. Because I feel like if I have to put everything that I’m sorry for out there at once, it’s going to rightfully make me look like a shit.” I stopped for a moment to think. “Sorry, just trying to see if I can do this in chronological order so I’m not forgetting anything.”

“Take your time,” she said.

“Well,” I said, after having gotten everything in order. “Sorry for my part in keeping things secret, which made everything all the more difficult for everyone. Sorry for bogarting — for hogging all of the grief for myself, for not coming to the funeral, for not being a better boyfriend and lending you whatever support and comfort I could, for taking from you and everyone else in my life, for feeding these cycles of anger and depression, for not breaking up with you, for not talking about it with the others after the fact, for just letting things fester and poisoning even the mere memory of something good.” I hesitated. “Sorry for —” I had trouble getting it out. “Sorry for sleeping with Maddie.”

“Not really something that you need to apologize to me for,” she replied. “And personally, I don’t really think that it’s something that you should apologize to her for either.”

“No?” I asked.

“We talk, me and Maddie,” she replied. “I don’t think it left as big an impact on her as you might think. She’s resilient. You coming in — you as you are now, this giant of a man who people are saying might be a few years away from being king, heir to Uther, to have that guy come in and frame it as though it was — I mean, better for her to think that it was a fling, that you were trying to find comfort and it just didn’t work. Better for her to think that Juniper was wholesale replaced.”

“As opposed to,” I said, almost wanting to let her fill in the blank, just because it would hurt worse coming from her lips. “Victimization.”

“I guess I wouldn’t go that far,” said Tiff. “It definitely got a ‘yikes’ from me, but not much more than that. Compared to you getting sent to jail, then apparently killing someone, then being presumed dead in a trial by adversity … and Maddie feels about the same. She feels bad, like some of it was her fault.”

“Well, she shouldn’t,” I said.

“Duh,” replied Tiff.

I stopped for a moment and frowned. “Can I tell you about the true nature of the universe?” I asked.

“Sure,” she replied. “Unless it’s going to melt my brain or something.”

“Nah,” I said. “Nothing like that. It’s just not good opsec to do it, so it’s a bit of a burden on you in that way.”

“Well, then maybe don’t,” she replied. “But I am curious.”

“There’s an alternate Tiff on Earth,” I said. “She looks just like you, you know that. But I didn’t just come from a place with alternate versions of everyone in your Juniper’s life, which would be weird enough, the group that I came from, they created about half of Aerb with me. On Earth, there are no elves, they’re mythological, but the elves that I made up for our games are how they are on Aerb. Same goes for the dwarves, those are dwarves that I made up. And the stuff on Aerb that I didn’t make up, it either came from stuff you guys created as players, or it’s stuff that seems like I would have come up with.”

“If you hadn’t punched a dragon’s eye out, I would probably find that harder to believe,” said Tiff.

“You’re taking this well,” I said.

“I’m a wreck,” she replied. “But I’ve been a wreck ever since getting in touch with Reimer, and eventually the brain just can’t do it anymore. It’s like reading a book that has twenty different twists in it, eventually you’re just broken. You’re not surprised, you just want it to end. You accept the twists as they come.”

“Sorry,” I said.

“It’s not your fault, if that’s the way the world is,” she said. “I’m helpless in the face of all this. Just tell me what you need from me, or what I should believe.”

“My Arthur,” I said. “Same as yours, or near enough that we can talk about them as though they’re the same … how much do you know about Uther Penndraig?”

She stared at me. “You apparently don’t remember helping me with a very long paper about him?”

I frowned. “What did I know about Uther Penndraig?” I hoped that I hadn’t been a fanboy.

“Damned near everything,” she said. “You went on a bender reading biographies when you were twelve. Not the same on Earth?”

“No,” I said. “Sorry, Reimer didn’t mention this, it might be important.”

“Really?” she asked. “This is actually, seriously important?”

“I don’t know,” I said. “Maybe, probably not.”

“Okay,” she said, looking slightly worried. “Reimer said that he’d been answering a lot of questions.”

“You know what, just back it up to the previous point, we’ll give you a full debrief later,” I said.

“You were asking me what I knew about Uther, and I was saying that I knew enough to write a fairly comprehensive overview of his life,” said Tiff. “And I was going to ask why that was important.”

“Uther was dream-skewered,” I said. “Dream-skewered by my Arthur.”

Tiff stared at me. “Nope,” she finally said.

“I mean, it’s true,” I replied.

“Arthur,” she said. “I mean … you know that I loved him like a brother, right? But how does someone like Arthur become someone like Uther?”

“It’s a long story,” I said.

“And do we have time?” she asked.

“You know … we do,” I replied.

It took the better part of an hour to hit everything I thought was particularly important. I started with what I assumed had been the start for Arthur, coming across his whole ‘family’ dead at the hands of the Dark King. There was a three year gap when he was probably with a theater troupe, no hero to anyone, his rise to power as king … and then the story continuing on anyway, despite having reached its first logical stopping point, and then its second. I explained the narrative force, as Uther had understood it, and the ways he had presumably tried to work around it. I gave a brief digression into Vervain, the companion thought by Uther to be a DMPC, and that was where Tiff objected.

“He wouldn’t do that,” she said.

“It’s not the same Arthur we knew,” I said. “I mean, assuming that your Arthur and my Arthur were close enough proxies to one another. He came to this world at sixteen, and from there — he killed a lot of people, Tiff. Hundreds, by that point, maybe thousands if you include the impersonal ones. He led armies. He was definitely capable of killing someone in cold blood, especially if he thought they were the architect of his misfortune.”

“The stories of Uther aren’t like that,” said Tiff. “You’re painting me this picture of a grim and depressed man, someone who’s been worn out by two centuries of adventures packed into a forty year span, and —”

“I’ve been traveling with Raven,” I said. “Who, uh, incidentally looks exactly like Earth Maddie did.”

“Huh,” said Tiff. “But not like Aerb Maddie? Why?”

“No clue,” I said. “My best guess is that there was only a need for a single proxy, and Raven was it.”

“Because you believe in a higher power, like Arthur apparently did?” she asked.

“Yes,” I said. “I’ve spoken to him, actually. Once he appeared in my soul, the other time he stopped the world around us. Though he’s also probably been stopping time or talking to splinter versions of myself or erasing my memories of other encounters, or who knows what else.”

She stared at me. “But to what end?” she asked. “Is this meeting … part of it?”

“I don’t know,” I said. “This is more me, trying to make peace with you. To settle up before — well, we have reason to think that Uther is still alive, and I’m going after him.”

“Joon,” she said slowly. “I mean, I don’t know everything you know, you’ve been handed the keys to the kingdom, literally, you’re a prince now for fuck’s sake, but — do you think that’s something you should be doing?”

I blinked at her. “Wouldn’t you?” I asked. “I mean … it’s Arthur.”

“You know that he was one of my best friends,” she said. “But when people die, we — we try to work past it. We remember them, we mourn, it’s — I know you always hated that kind of story, but there’s a reason we tell them. Obsessing, getting wrapped up in those feelings of loss, I think that’s where you went wrong. You had all this anger and hatred toward everyone because it hurt, and I get that, but — I’m just worried.”

“I know it won’t be him,” I said. “I mean, at a minimum, he’s in his fifties, but there’s a good chance he’s even older. But come on, it’s still Arthur. And the stories about people obsessed with defeating death, or not being able to bring back loved ones, those only exist as a coping mechanism, they’re not real, there’s no fundamental imperative of the universe that you can’t bring back someone you lost.”

“Okay,” she said. “You’re living in a different world from me, and I’ll just have to trust that you know best. It’s just that when you talk about bringing Arthur back from the dead, even in this convoluted way, alarm bells start going off in my head. It feels like repeating history.”

“But I never tried to bring him back, did I?” I asked.

“No, but you were raging against the universe,” said Tiff. “You would have tried it, if there had been any viable path. You looked up every method you could think of, looking for long shots, or lost secrets, but of course, there were none.”

I knew that well enough. I’d done the same thing my counterpart had done when Fenn had died. Maybe me and him had ended up reading the same books, following the same hundred dead ends. That seemed like the kind of thing the Dungeon Master might chuckle about, that bastard. Maybe there was a universal imperative.

“I don’t think it’s like that,” I said. “But I’ll keep what you’ve said in mind.”

“Thank you,” she said. She smoothed out her skirt. “If we’re squaring things up, can I ask about Amaryllis?”

“Uh,” I said. “Sure.”

“Who was she, on Earth?”

“No one,” I said. “I mean, I think she’s an Aerb original. I didn’t invent her, if that’s what you’re thinking.

“So you didn’t have a poster of her in your room?” asked Tiff.

“Nope,” I replied. “To be honest, posters of women — I mean, it seems kind of creepy to me, outdated by Earth’s standards. Especially one like Reimer said that one was, not even intended for titillation.”

“Well,” said Tiff. “Not intended for titillation, but I don’t think titillation was lost on whoever was making those posters. Sex sells.”

I nodded. “Sorry if it’s awkward for you, me being married to her. It would probably have been awkward for the Earth verison of you, if for different reasons.”

“I guess I just want to know if you’re over me,” said Tiff. “And how that worked for you.”

“Ah,” I said. “Yeah. I don’t know. There were times, when we were dating, when I felt like you were the love of my life, like I should be moving mountains to make sure that we could stay together. I was imagining that we would go to the same athenaeum together, or if I couldn’t get into whichever one you ended up going, I could just live in the city, but then I would have to worry that our lives were going on different paths, and I would be committing myself to a relationship that was destined for a fork in the road, with no possibility that we were going to end up at the same destination. There was a part of me that hated it, because it felt like if we’d met at any other point in our lives, it would have been so much easier, and we could have just, I don’t know, gotten married and made it work better than my parents did, like we could have had kids and done a better job raising them than my parents did raising me — hey, don’t cry, it’s okay.”

“Sorry,” she said, wiping away a tear. “Fuck, Juniper.”

“Anything I can do?” I asked. “Did you — is it okay if I hold you?”

She shook her head. “We probably won’t see each other after today.”

“Probably not,” I replied.

“And it would just make me more heartsick,” she continued, shaking her head slightly.

“I probably would have fucked things up between us, if it’s any consolation,” I said. “I mean, I did fuck things up, so it’s likely that if I hadn’t fucked things up in the way that I did, I would have done it some other way.”

“It was recoverable,” she said, looking into my eyes with tears obscuring her vision. “Right?”

“Probably,” I said. I felt my heart sinking. Seeing her had brought a lot of feelings back up, and here she was, asking me point blank whether we could have gotten back together. Back on Earth, that had been, if not my plan, then at least a consideration. I’d thought that I could get the group back together, make my apologies, smooth things out, admit fault, and then maybe … well, maybe find Tiff in my arms once more.

“Tiff,” I said. “It’s so far away in time for me now, it’s — I was in a time chamber, sand magic, I’m a few months older than I should be, and —”

“I’m not asking you to, I don’t know,” said Tiff. “It’s just painful, thinking about what might have been, hearing all these things you never said out loud.”

“It is,” I said, but as I said it, I realized how much of a gulf there was between what we were experiencing. There was a part of me that wanted to start things up with this alternate Tiff, to reconnect, to patch things up more thoroughly than we could possibly do in an afternoon, all those old feelings for her were still there, somewhere, buried deep … but they were deep, and I felt no desire to dig. That was, on its own, a bit of a revelation for me.

“Do you know what happened to the real Juniper?” asked Tiff.

“No,” I replied. “Though I would probably know if he ended up in the hells. My best guess is that he’s gone forever, but I wouldn’t put it past this world to have one last twist in store, and my guess is that I’ll be able to make, uh, a reconstruction of him, bring him back to life.”

“If that’s possible, then — I would appreciate that,” said Tiff. “Do you think he really killed someone, in prison? Or was that you?”

“It was him,” I said. “And yeah, I think he probably did. Maybe not on purpose, but Tiff, I’ve killed people, a lot of people, so many that — I don’t know. It weighs on me. Some were more excusable than others, easier to justify.”

“Like in our games,” said Tiff. “Dozens dead and barely a thought given to it.”

“Yeah,” I said.

“You always did seem to think that some fuckers just needed killing,” said Tiff. “Or like a lot of problems could be solved with a solid punch in the face.”

“I felt it, I didn’t think it,” I said, feeling slightly defensive. “I’m a believer in rehabilitation, in structural solutions to structural problems, in the banality of evil and the ways that incentives drive actions. It’s just that our brains aren’t hooked up like that. We feel like punching problems works. There’s a satisfaction in it that’s not there in, for example, organizing the evacuation for millions of people from a dystopia and trying to get them proper education, healthcare, and therapy.”

“And you really did that?” she asked. “I’ve been reading the news, and your exploits — they’re unbelievable.”

“Eh,” I said. “I’d like to imagine that the whole situation in Necrolaborem was solved with grace and deftness, tied up with a pretty little bow. In truth, it’s ongoing, and Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle died before it was best for him to die. The most I managed to do was extract myself from the situation after putting in long hours to get things set for everyone else to do the work.”

“If even half of what they say is true, you’re being too hard on yourself,” she said. “You can’t expect to fix everything forever.”

“Yeah, I guess,” I said. But I did, of course, think that was my destiny, unless the Dungeon Master was just yanking my chain. “Speaking of … I should probably get going. There are some things that I need to get done before I go after Arthur.”

“Thank you for coming,” said Tiff. “I was worried that all I was going to get was that letter. It helped me, and I hope that it helped you too, in some way. And … I hope you’re happy with Amaryllis, for what it’s worth.”

“I am,” I said. “And thank you for having me.” I hesitated. “You don’t think that I should visit Maddie?”

Tiff shook her head. “I’ve talked to her. So far as she’s said, she’s got what closure she wanted. Once she heard that it wasn’t really you going around doing all those things, she made peace. I think if she knew how close you are to him, or how tangled up things really are, it would hurt her ability to move on. That’s just my opinion though. You had much less of an impact on her than you had on me. She’s already been through two boyfriends since dating you.”

“Okay,” I said, feeling slightly relieved.

“And Juniper, before you go … where is he? Arthur, or Uther?” She looked curious, but also a little anxious. The disappearance of Uther was one of the biggest mysteries of all time, so it was no surprise that she wanted to know.

“He tried to go back,” I said. “Back to Earth. Something must have happened to him along the way.” I hesitated, biting back the words for a moment, because I didn’t want to worry her. “Fel Seed is sitting on top of the tunnel.”

“You’re going against Fel Seed?” asked Tiff, eyes wide.

“Past him, ideally,” I said. “But yes.”

“Oh,” she replied. “Well … Juniper, if it’s all for Arthur, because you’re still hurting, because you can’t accept that he’s gone, then —”

“It’s complicated,” I said. “More complicated than I have the time to explain, probably more complicated than I should explain. But it’s not just because my friend died.”

“Okay,” she said. “I just don’t want you to have invented a new and exciting way to destroy yourself.” She gave me a somewhat strained smile.

“I’ll do my best to live a full and happy life,” I said. “And to do what’s best for Aerb and the realms beyond.”

“I guess that’s all anyone can ask,” she said. “Hopefully this isn’t goodbye forever?”

“Hopefully,” I nodded.

We had an awkward hug, and the smell of her brought back strong memories, but after she was out the door, they faded rapidly away.

Runination

Rune magic wasn’t hard to unlock: all it really took was gobs of money. We had been in the midst of liquidating assets in order to convert to gold and fuel gold magic, which meant that there were funds to slide the way of the rune mages.

We went to one of the ‘satellite’ runeforges, which was away from Stars and Sigils, but still within a city. Grunnings was almost entirely centered around the enormous, labyrinthine green ziggurat. There really weren’t that many runemakers in the world, compared to some other magics, and that was owing to the hard limits that the runeforges presented, which put a hard cap on how many man-hours could be spent forging runes. The city formed concentric rings, with the runeforge at the center, supporting businesses around it, and then support for the support around that, with residential and basic commercial zoning beyond. It was one of the most boring fantasy cities I could have imagined, centered around a mystical source of power, but with almost nothing in the way of artistry or interest beyond that. It really made me reconsider my view that the world was a series of interesting locations, but maybe you’d still count Grunnings, because it had the runeforge.

Getting a jump on the process wasn’t quite like at Sound and Silence, where money was a well-accepted part of the process, with codified shortcuts that could be bought for the right price (or with the right contacts). The Rune Council put as much effort as possible into ensuring that everyone who was a member got equal time, on the theory that this would give strong incentives to do as much pre-planning as possible, minimizing downtime of the runeforge as a whole. With that said, master runemakers did still require more time, and that was the loophole that we’d eventually used, circumventing the Rune Council: I was coming in as an apprentice.

“Apprenticeship is a grey area,” said Xo, whose robes, pointy hat, and long grey beard make him look like a very wizardly wizard. He was human, but possibly human with a touch of something else, or maybe just from a far-flung part of the world where humans had different facial features. “There’s a need for apprentices, that much is true, but if you start bringing extra people into the runeforge, you get some extra logistical challenges and start running into the dread shenanigans. Of which this is an example, of course.”

I nodded. We were waiting our turn, and while I didn’t really care about Xo or feel like talking to him, I was trying my best to humor him. “What’s grey about them?” I asked. “In terms of how the rules are structured.”

“Do you like rules?” he asked.

“Eh,” I replied. “You’d have to define what you mean by the word.” I waited for a moment, but he let me continue. “I like systems of rules if they’re entirely self-contained, strict and rigid. It’s where they interact with the real world that I start to get exasperated. There are always matters of interpretation, corner cases, things like that, which sucks the fun out of the rules. If that makes sense?”

He nodded. “Very astute. You’ll make a good rune worker, if you like hard rules. There’s no grey area, no interpretation here. The runes do what they do, with no ambiguity. Unfortunately, the Rune Council is filled with people who are used to the first kind of rule, but are tasked with dealing with the second kind.”

“So where does the grey area come from?” I asked, more to be polite than anything else.

“There’s something in rune magic that tracks who did what within the runeforge,” Xo replied. “As a general rule with one very noticeable exception, you can only use your own runeworks, but if someone else touches your runeworks, that doesn’t instantly disqualify them as yours. In fact, it takes quite a bit of actual physical work for the tagging to fail. Therefore, a runeworker can have an apprentice whose job is to run parts from station to station, setting everything up for him, and sometimes taking minimal steps. Now, most don’t have their apprentices do too much, because then tagging fails and a whole day at the forge could be wasted, but the Rune Council ran into this problem of intent, because what’s stopping someone from bringing on an ‘apprentice’ who just does all the work and circumvents the restrictions on time in the forge?”

“They could patch it though,” I said.

“Patch it, and apply penalties, which they’ve done,” replied Xo, nodding happily that I seemed to have followed along. “But their patches aren’t very strong, and if we get caught, you’re paying the penalties for me.”

“And the intent is that I’m doing everything here?” I asked.

Xo nodded. “In practice, I’ll be your teacher and you my apprentice, with rather more in the way of hands-on experience than normal, and nothing actually produced by me. Ideally, you’d have gone to Stars and Sigils to get some of the basics. They have non-functional replica stations that you can practice on. Obviously there’s a lot of theory you’re going to be completely missing. No offense, but it seems like you have more money than sense.”

“I would take offense, but I have so much money that it’s hard to take it as an insult,” I said.

“Well damn, then I should have charged more,” he replied.

“Do you do this often?” I asked. “Get people to be your apprentice?”

“No, first time,” he replied. “So I’m going to hope that it’s not a huge mistake.”

“We’ll be fine,” I said. “I’m not sure it was in whatever brief you got, but I’m already a mage.”

“No shit?” he asked, sounding much less like a wizard than he looked. “Which one?”

I took a breath. “Blood, bone, water, air, passion, still, vibration, star, and ink. Plus I had skin and soul, before they got excluded.”

“Neat,” he said, nodding along, like this was something he heard every day.

“I mean, you could at least pretend to be impressed,” I said, frowning at him.

“Eh,” he replied. He gave me a smile. “I charge extra for pretending to be impressed.”

“You really have no idea who I am?” I asked.

“Nope,” he replied. “Better that we keep it that way, unless you’re willing to let me reciprocate. I don’t like hearing life stories, not unless I get to share mine too. We all go on long and winding roads, right? None more special than any other, in the end.”

That was a very faux-enlightened way of looking at things, and I had several very obvious objections. Xo was weirding me out a bit. Maybe he thought that I was lying, and it really shouldn’t have mattered to me whether this particular guy thought that I was hot shit, but to blithely brush me off … well, it was putting me off-balance. I was the most important person in the world, aside from maybe Uther, or the Dungeon Master, if you counted him as a person. I swallowed my objections though.

We didn’t have to wait all that long for our turn, and the waiting we did was mostly because of an insistence that no one ever be late for the runeforge. It all still seemed a little bit quaint to me, since I had been picturing something like air traffic control, with detailed flight plans submitted well in advance and coordination between paths so that the whole of the runeforge could be maximized by every individual involved. That didn’t really seem to be the case though, and my best guess was that without computers, they were down to trying to track everything using pen and paper, with maybe a little bit of entad assistance or custom-built scheduling schemes, which simply weren’t up to the task.

Skill Unlocked: Rune Magic!

Achievement Unlocked: Wrack and Runes

I got the unlock the moment I stepped into the runeforge, which was a bit of a relief. If the unlock were the only thing we needed, we would probably have tried to slip in through one of the unused entrances to the runeforge. They were warded, but we had Grak, who could slip someone through a ward without even dismantling it (which he could also have done pretty easily). The problem was, we didn’t just need the unlock, because unlocking rune magic on its own did nothing for me. Instead, what we needed was for me to boost the skill as much as possible while making as many useful low-level runeworks as I could.

“Impressive,” said Xo as he watched me work one of the machines. “Usually there’s a bit more hesitance, if someone is coming in completely fresh.”

“I thought you didn’t really do this?” I asked.

“Not this,” he replied. “But I’ve broken in apprentices before, usually young men and women who are looking to work for me for a year or two before signing on to Stars and Sigils. There are limited slots. The Rune Council worries about having too many rune workers, and being an apprentice for a year or two looks good on an application. That’s assuming you don’t just buy your way in.”

From the outside, the runeforge looked like a giant jade ziggurat, but on the inside, there was a distinct lack of order. I was fairly sure that the design was one that I’d used for a campaign that featured a brief jaunt into a parallel universe, inspired by the idea of hostile architecture, or at least what I’d read of the concept on a Wikipedia page. Hostile architecture was most famously associated with spikes put in place to prevent homeless people from sleeping places, but if you thought about it for a bit, you could make the hostility a little bit more subtle, if no less effective. During the time of segregation, it had been common practice to segregate toilets and drinking fountains, and then make places where black people effectively couldn’t go because there were no colored fountains or bathrooms there. There were lots of reasons to design a place that was hostile to certain people or activities, but here, as in the campaign the design had been lifted from, it was just for flavor, and maybe a bit of spite.

The acoustics were terrible, for a start. It was hard to hear people right next to you, but very easy to hear the sounds of rune work from down the halls, echoing and bouncing off surfaces so that it was difficult to tell where any of it was coming from. The noise wasn’t very loud, but it was loud enough to get on your nerves pretty quickly. The floors were uneven, making it hard to keep your balance, and the stairs had been made so that you were likely to trip, or miss a step, always unable to find a stride, and requiring full attention. There were also a lot of stairs, random changes in levels that seemed to have no point, so it was a problem that came up a lot. Almost nothing was at a right angle, and the floors sloped, sometimes severely. Worse, it was hard to keep your bearings, not just because everything was all done in a single style, but because there was no adherence to conventions. The temperatures swung wildly, sometimes hot enough that you’d risk heatstroke, other times cold enough for frostbite. Surfaces ranged from rough enough to rip off flesh, to slick enough that you’d slip and fall no matter how sure your footing.

There had been a time when rune workers had taken pride in surviving the hostility of the runeforge. Knowledge of the internals was closely guarded, seen as the mark that someone was worthy. That time was long past. The interior of every runeforge had been mapped, and pains had been taken to soften the harsh edges, where that was possible. There were stations set up at regular intervals to provide for biological needs like food, water, and waste management, and the most flagrant of the unfriendliness had been corrected, usually by building on top of the existing floors or stairs. Rune workers brought in earplugs to help with the sound, along with tools to help them, which was no surprise given that the whole profession was about making tools. One of the first things that most rune workers created for themselves was thermoregulators so that they wouldn’t have to worry about the temperature swings.

Through the ages, scholars had asked themselves about the nature and origin of the runeforges. They seemed like a gift, a way that a useful magic had been added to the world, but why then were they so hostile? And why did they discourage but not outright stop their use? If you could make something like the runeforge, and make it so that it was deliberately hostile to use, then why not make it worse? Why not make the inviolable walls so tight that no one could fit through? Why not place the workstations on the ceiling? Or flood the place with poison, or radiation? Most people settled on it being a test of some kind, a way of weeding out the unworthy, but that was because most people who considered the question were rune workers. The truth was, rune magic was almost exactly Reimer’s kind of thing, and the inherent hostility of the runeforges were a reflection of my personal feelings towards those types of magic.

“What is it you’re making?” asked Xo, finally taking some interest in what I was applying runes to.

I had a blueprint next to me, with notes about where each rune was supposed to go. There were a wide variety of stations, so I was doing the work in an unintuitive way, all of one symbol, then all of the next symbol at a different station, and so on.  It was like writing a novel by putting in all of the letter T, then all the letter B, and so on.

“I’m a multimage,” I said. “It’s mostly multimage stuff, leveraging what I can in a relatively short amount of time. You can look at the blueprint if you’d like.”

Xo frowned, and looked at the runes on the blueprint, then at what I was doing. “You’re already working like a practiced hand.”

“I learn fast,” I said. I was already up to seven points in the skill, after not much more than lining up the level and pulling it down at the right spot a few times. I was starting with a practice piece, so the stakes were quite low, but I was still trying to do a good job, on the theory that skill acquisition worked better that way (for which there was some limited evidence).

“Look at the scale on this thing,” said Xo, pointing at the blueprint rather than the piece I had in hand. “You know that you’re going to have to carry this around, right?”

“I’m a star mage,” I said. “All this is going to be placed into a kind of subspace assembly that I’ll wear on my back. That’s a work in progress, but it’s mostly done.”

“Intriguing,” he replied, returning his attention to the blueprints. “Some of this is wrong.”

“Nope,” I said. “Just unconventional.”

Xo nodded, tracing out lines as I stamped in more runes to the sheets of metal I’d brought with me. “This is all … some advanced overload mitigation technique then?”

“You’re pretty fast,” I said, not slowing down. “From what I’ve heard from talking to other rune dudes, it takes a lot of time to grapple with an unfamiliar design.”

“So someone else designed this?” he asked.

“Nope,” I replied. “It was all me. I did run it by some skilled rune dudes though, just to make sure that I wasn’t wasting my time.”

“‘Rune dudes’,” he said, laughing a bit. “You’ve got some cheek, I’ll give you that. It’s rare in this profession. Or at least, the humor is different.”

“You don’t have people thinking up ridiculous creations that are technically within the bounds of rune magic?” I asked. “Like, as a joke?”

“We do,” he said, giving me a look as I continued my work. “But you understand how that’s a bit different?”

“Of course,” I said. “And a lot of the creations wouldn’t be practical in any real situation, or there would be enormous hurdles that you’d just have someone wave away, or exploit some specific entad, but that’s part of what makes it funny, and fun to think about.”

“You have a good understanding of the culture,” he said. “But not such a good understanding of the actual craft.” He came over to me and pointed at a section of the fin I had been working on.

“Fuuuuuck,” I said. “Welp, I guess that’s ruined then.”

“Smart,” he replied. “Most people just getting into rune magic try to figure out some kind of modification, some way to salvage it with a workaround.”

“I know I’m out of my depth here,” I said. “And if I’m going to get killed, I’m going to try my best to not be hoisted by my own petard.” I zooped the metal fin off into extradimensional space, then pulled out one of several spares and continued on with the work, starting from the beginning. I wasn’t sure what had caused the fuckup, and was hopeful that it was a low roll somewhere inside the internal systems of the game that governed my skill.

“So,” said Xo once we were on our way to the next station. He’d been silent while I did the replacement work, perhaps because he felt guilty about distracting me, though that obviously wasn’t a concern given that I had the Multithreading virtue. “I think I have a bit of a handle on what you’re building, but what’s the application?”

“Protection,” I said. “It’s as simple as that.”

“Oh, I figured that much out,” he replied, stepping beneath a low beam that seemed to be there for no more reason than to smack people in the head. “But I’m looking at what you’re making, and thinking about what it will do, then going backward to reconstruct the requirements. It would all be a lot faster if you would just tell me what you’re planning to do with this thing.”

“Sure,” I said. “But I imagine that it would be less fun for you. And if you work through things, maybe you’ll help me understand more about this noble profession, in which I’m only a tourist.”

“I’m mostly worried that you’re engaging in the kind of forbidden project that will end with both of us dead at the hands of bureaucratic assassins,” he said. “I don’t suppose you’ve read through the rule books?”

“Books?” I asked. “There are multiple? And in case that didn’t answer the question by itself, no, I didn’t read anything.”

“Even admitting to that would be asking for a lifetime ban, if not worse,” said Xo, shaking his head. “Of course, you’re not even a proper member of an organization, just an apprentice, so I suppose it matters less to you.”

“Let me guess,” I said. “A rules lawyer is one of the most powerful tiers of rune workers?”

“How is it that you don’t know that?” he asked.

“I dunno, rune magic isn’t really my thing,” I said. “No offense. It’s going to be a single tool in the arsenal, one magic of many, used to shore up some of my other defenses.”

“Against what?” he asked. “That’s what I’m having trouble figuring out. It seems as though you’re avoiding proper conduits because you want to protect against overloading, but the only use case that comes to mind for that is if you were worried about some massive energy source, and if that’s the case, all you seem to be doing is converting it into raw, focused light output, which is incredibly dangerous.”

“Dangerous why?” I asked.

“Do you actually not know, or are you testing me?” he asked, looking a bit perturbed at either option.

“Making sure that I didn’t miss anything,” I said. “I’m trying not to poison the well by saying what I was thinking.”

We arrived at another station, where a totally different type of machine was used for stamping in a different rune, this one primarily with applications in focusing the light.

“I’ll leave you to it,” he said, as I began putting my petals into place.

“It’s fine,” I replied.

“I have a book,” he said, “It’s no problem.”

“No, go on,” I said. “Tell me how the output is dangerous.”

“Normally if energy absorption is a runic defense, the energy goes into a rune assembly that keeps it contained until it needs to be used,” said Xo as he watched me continue on with my work. “Alternately, if you can spare the weight, it gets bled off into material generation, which can soak practically as much energy as you can throw at it. But if you’re just blasting that energy back out, then there’s a good chance you’re going to get, at minimum, some backwash. More likely, you’re going to destroy a bunch of stuff you don’t want destroyed.”

“Wait,” I said, stopping what I was doing to look at him. “Material generation?”

“As in, you want an explanation?” he asked.

“Yes,” I said.

He sighed. “Rune magic contains a concept of mass-energy equivalence. You put in some small amount of mass, you get an enormous amount of energy out. Now, the runes that can do that are limited, meaning that the limitless power available comes out to be more of a trickle, and to have even that functionality is usually more trouble than it’s worth. People would rather use solar, or combustion, or anything else.”

“But you can flip it around somehow,” I said. “And you don’t get killed by the same rate limit? Meaning you put unlimited energy in and get mass out pretty much as fast?”

“In theory, if you built it right, you would be able to skip past the rate limitations,” he said. “But that’s only in theory, because as far as I know, no one has actually tried to build such a thing. The mass-energy equivalence is what kills you, even if you’re generating something with a high value.”

“Huh,” I said. “And the runes for mass generation —”

“Mass-energy conversion,” he corrected.

“Sure,” I replied. “But given how many elements there are, surely there’s not a rune for each of them, right?”

He held up a hand. “You have to distinguish between true elements and chemical elements,” he said. “True elements have their own individual runes, but we don’t have the full suite. Chemical elements have their own numbers, which corresponds with … something, it’s been a while. The number you want gets selected through a supplemental rune assembly, increments and decrements.”

“I see,” I replied. “And if you select a negative number, it …?”

“Fails,” he replied. “Breaks stuff, I think. Not really my field.”

I was pretty sure that this was the answer to a lingering question of mine, which was how Amaryllis had gotten her hands on a huge quantity of antimatter in the Cypress timeline. She had mentioned only that it was a neglected area of rune magic, and as it turned out, that was almost enough. The only remaining issue was where to get the energy, but I was pretty sure that Amaryllis would figure something out —

— except that it would only take her a handful of minutes, because the answer was inherent to the question. Antimatter didn’t violently annihilate itself, it annihilated itself and the matter that it came in contact with, releasing the energy of both. If you had a way to directly and losslessly convert energy into antimatter, you would just need some additional matter, something as simple as dirt, in order to double your antimatter with every cycle. You wouldn’t need a massive power source to get your antimatter, you would just need mechanisms to run as many cycles as you wanted, doubling up until you had enough.

It wasn’t exactly something that I could do in an afternoon, given the enormous number of engineering challenges that would have to be solved, and it was possible that it was simply beyond my abilities, but it seemed like it would work, at least in theory. Maybe it would need to be hammered at by experts for a few months, then actually constructed, but it was a path toward enormous destructive power.

You’d have to stand next to it, unless you were a blood mage and used extensors, or used some other method of tricking rune magic into thinking that you were right next to this extremely dangerous, extremely fail-deadly contraption.

But to actually do it would almost certainly bring an exclusion down on rune magic, and rune magic was, unfortunately, linked in to soul extraction. If rune magic got excluded, then soul capture as a whole would evaporate overnight, and virtually everyone who died would end up in the hells. This was one of the primary reasons that a lot of potential applications of rune magic never got serious research and development. From what I knew, the regulatory apparatus for rune magic was huge and overgrown, but it hadn’t been trimmed back, because too much was riding on making sure that rune magic never got excluded. I had come to the runeforge in order to get some basics and cover some bases, and I was under strict instructions (that I didn’t really need) not to make improvisations or add on extra things beyond the base design. It wasn’t really my fault, but I had precipitated a fair number of exclusions, and rune magic getting excluded would have made things a lot worse for Aerb.

“Are you okay?” asked Xo.

“Yeah,” I said, continuing my work. “Anyway, the plan is full-on reflection, directed at the sky if there’s no enemy around, or at the enemy if one is there.”

“Oh, so you go into actual combat?” he asked. “Not necessarily rune magic’s forte.”

“Well, as I said, I know a pretty wide variety of magic. The fins will be tucked into hand-crafted extradimensional space, and hopefully save me from the worst of a major attack.” I kept going about my work. “Have you seriously never heard of me? I’ve been in the news. I killed two dragons?”

“Impressive, if true,” he said. “But no, I stay away from the news. Too much sensationalism these days, and if not that, then too much talk about dire circumstances on the horizon. I’m happier not listening, I think, especially since there’s not a whit I can do about any of it.”

“Fair enough,” I said.

“You’ll be able to react in time?” he asked.

“In time for a sudden attack?” I asked. “Well, once I’m done here, I was planning to become a velocity mage.”

“Of course you were,” he said.

The short version of how you became a velocity mage was that you had to exceed a set speed limit that went up with every person to become a velocity mage.

The long version was quite a bit longer, because there were all kinds of caveats. They were kind of funny, in a way, because I could see a dungeon master’s mind at work behind them, trying desperately to close loopholes. After all, if velocity was just distance over time, then your calculated velocity when you used a teleportation stone or stepped through an entad portal would be either infinite or close to the speed of light. You couldn’t have that, because it would break the induction right out the gate, so the velocity had to be sustained. Of course, people would come in with all kinds of magical solutions, so to fix that problem, you weren’t allowed to use magic. The restrictions on magic were, in my opinion, a little bit much: you weren’t allowed to use magic to go faster, to sustain your speed, or to survive the high speeds, which really cut down on how many different options there were. With every velocity mage inducted, the limit ticked higher, and where it once might have been enough to ride a very fast horse, the limit was now so high that actual engineering efforts had to be put toward the problem.

At the start of the Second Empire, they had been using rocket sleds, accelerating along a track by burning fuel, then slowing down as quickly as possible once they’d gone through the sustain phase and hoping that the candidate didn’t die in the process. It was scary and dangerous, but it worked, and in typical myopic Second Empire fashion, they had created a whole host of velocity mages, bumping the numbers up and forcing the rocket sled path to become more and more dangerous. (It was common to blame this kind of thing on the Second Empire, rather than the athenaeum, but that was mostly because the Second Empire didn’t exist anymore, and the athenaeums liked to disavow any work they’d done in concert with that most hated of empires. The Second Empire was a very convenient scapegoat.)

In the modern era, a large amount of money had been spent on a secret facility whose details were shrouded in confidentiality agreements and redactions, even (perhaps especially) from those who would use it. Fortunately, we had Raven, who had been around during the construction of the thing, and because of the Library, knew a lot of secrets that she shouldn’t have. The solution they’d come up with was dead simple: it was a huge tube going down into the earth, allowing a long drop. Gravity was the best source of free acceleration, it had just been a matter of harnessing it and then making sure that you didn’t kill candidates in the process. Because terminal velocity would have slowed candidates down too much, the incredibly long tube was kept in vacuum through the use of pumps. Because the vacuum would have killed candidates, they wore suits to keep them in pressure.

All the remaining problems to solve had been solved, with magic carefully kept away or worked around so that it wouldn’t taint the raw speed.

From my perspective, it was a matter of stepping into a tube, feeling weightlessness, then some time later, getting a little notification from the game layer before stepping out a few minutes later. Overall, it was underwhelming. I had wanted to do it on my own, but in the end, money solved almost every problem.

“Feel okay?” asked Amaryllis, once I was back on the surface.

“Fine,” I said.

“Perception effects?” she asked.

“None so far,” I replied. The perception effects were the major reason to skip velocity magic entirely, but it was already on the character sheet, and the balance of pros and cons had been made long ago. That didn’t stop Amaryllis from fretting.

“We can technically undo it,” she said. “Grak could attach a mobile ward anchored to you.”

“It would be difficult,” said Grak. “Better not to have to.”

“Time for a test drive then,” said Amaryllis. She looked out at the city around us, a place with a large number of granite buildings, and gestured for me to have at it.

I took a breath and then ran, leaping off a three-storey building and into the open air, feeling the magic surge through me as I gathered speed.

Velocity magic didn’t slow down perception of time, though I really wished that it did. Instead, it amplified reflexes, and at the higher levels, ran you on a sort of autopilot, with your actions being more a product of your will than anything you were consciously thinking. When I hit the ground, I twisted and rolled, applying just a smidge of still magic to keep myself from breaking an ankle. Then I was off and running, building up speed, feeling myself lose a part of executive function to a nebulous other as I picked up the pace.

The skill levels flowed quickly and freely, fast, for lack of a better word, and my speed built as I pushed through, running as fast as I could. Drag from the air became a problem, but it was a problem that I was used to from flying with gold magic, and I’d become relatively proficient in making tunnels for myself using air magic. To my mild surprise, the use of other magics was under the same effect, sped up and beyond my conscious control, the mental processes being piloted the same as physical ones. I was out of the city before I knew it, racing down a poorly maintained road as the scenery whipped past me.

I came to a stop when I got to a crossroads, stopping on a dime with still magic. I didn’t know how fast I had actually gone, but it was well in excess of what any normal car could do. Once I was stopped, I felt a bit of the perceptual changes, a sense that everything was moving quickly around me and my own body was lagging behind the commands that I was giving it. It only lasted for a few minutes though, and after that my perception was back to normal. I was thankful for that, and didn’t plan on abusing velocity magic enough that I’d suffer much for it.

To my surprise, Amaryllis appeared beside me with a gust of wind not long after.

“Huh,” I said. “You were following me?”

“I need testing and training with it, just like you do,” she replied. “Of course, I’ll always be worse, but it’s part of the toolkit. Have you hit the virtue yet?”

“Level 10 has come and gone,” I said. “So I’ll probably see it by the end of the day. It’s going up fast though.”

“Good,” she said. “Let me know what the virtue is. I’m a little surprised that Reimer wasn’t able to provide us with any information on it.”

“Velocity magic is based on a ruleset that I worked on with Tiff for a superhero campaign,” I said. “From what history Reimer and Tiff have provided for us, nothing of the sort ever happened on Aerb, and if no one ever decided to go with being a velocity mage, then Reimer would never have learned the virtue. And if it were me, I would never have written the virtue for something that no one was using. Could be that the virtue won’t exist until I actually get to it.”

“Maybe,” she said. She stretched out. “I’d challenge you to a race, but we both know you’d win. Any new synergies that you hadn’t thought of before?”

“The actual experience hasn’t been revelatory,” I said. “The virtue might be busted though, given that anything that upsets the symmetry of it would be great for rune magic. I kind of wish we’d done it in the other order, but —”

“If we need to, we can put you through the runeforge again,” said Amaryllis. “Gold magic is gone, which means that our only time pressure at the moment is the Void Beast, and perhaps an eventual attack from Celestar, both of which are years away.”

“True,” I said. “Well, I guess you’ll have to give me until the end of the day to find out.” I looked down at my hand and wiggled my fingers, trying to get them moving fast, but not really seeing much. “Care to spar?”

“If you want to beat me up, you can just say so,” she said. “I haven’t been able to keep up with you for a long time now, and velocity magic isn’t going to help matters.”

“You don’t think you’d be good enough that it would at least be interesting?” I asked. “I think you would. I wouldn’t just demolish you.”

“Oh, you would,” she said. “But that was an honest offer. If you want someone to beat the shit out of, I’m here for you.”

“Gross,” I said. “Not my cup of tea.”

She shrugged. “No judgment.”

“Is this about me and the locus?” I asked.

“A bit,” she said. “It just made me question how much I actually know you, and what you want.”

“Don’t overthink it,” I said. “That’s what I’m trying to do.”

“What will it take for you to have sex with me?” she asked.

I stared at her for a moment. “I don’t know,” I said. “It’s not … does it bother you, that we haven’t?”

“A bit,” she said. “It feels like a missing piece.”

“Eh,” I said. “I mean, in the sense that a conventional relationship would have that element to it, but of all the reasons for us to have sex, the fact that it’s ‘what people do’ shouldn’t even be crossing your mind.”

“Our lives are ruled by social expectation,” she said. “Our identities are crafted from them. But I’m not sure it’s that. I think it feels like a missing piece because you’re being timid with me, not expressing your actual self. I don’t want our relationship to be one where we both hold back because we worry about inconveniencing or upsetting the other. If we could just try it once, perhaps it would be awful and we could put it behind us, but at least then we would know.”

“You’re usually better at making arguments,” I said.

“With you, I try to restrict myself to honest expressions of what I’m feeling,” she said. “No sleight of hand, no manipulation with careful wording, no carefully calculated appeals. Definitely no lies. I think that’s the only way that you and I can work.”

“I appreciate it,” I said. “I really do, even if it makes things more difficult for you.”

She nodded. “I think there’s some part of you that thinks you would have to be a monster to have sex with someone who isn’t particularly interested in it.”

“Well,” I said. “Yeah.”

“I’m perfectly capable of making my own decisions, Juniper,” she said. “You understand that, right? And you understand that making my decisions for me is the kind of paternalistic crap that I don’t want from anyone, but least of all you?”

“Why least of all me?” I asked.

“Because I love you,” she said. “And because you’re the one person that I can’t bludgeon into submission in one way or another. When some senator from a neighboring republic treats me like I’m a stupid little girl, that’s just fine, because I know that with only a little bit of time and effort, I could crush him politically, or strip his life of meaning, or murder his wife and children — I wouldn’t, obviously, but the point is that I could, and whatever I might be feeling about that particular brand of rudeness, it’s easy to take comfort in my absolute power. I can’t really do that with you.”

“There’s a power disparity,” I said. “So the paternalism — what you see as the paternalism — has no real solution.”

“So long as we clarify that the power disparity only exists within our relationship,” she said.

“Er,” I said. “I don’t accept that we’re on the same power level, no.”

“In terms of combat ability, no,” she replied. “But within our own spheres? Grak is the best warder on the hex. You’re an extremely good fighter and an unsurpassed multimage. And I’m the most skilled political animal that Aerb has ever seen, and that includes Uther.”

“Things are going that well in Anglecynn?” I asked.

“They are,” she replied. “Sorry, it’s a sidebar, but — I would be helped if I knew that my own contributions to the team weren’t glossed over in your mind.”

“For sure,” I said. “I would be utterly lost without you. Probably dead. The work you do in the background so that I don’t have to think particularly hard about minutiae puts you at the top of a hypothetical companion tier list.”

“Thank you,” she said. “So the problem between us, from my perspective, is that you’re trying to shield me from something that I don’t need to be shielded from. You’re holding back, and I don’t think that you should be, not unless you really think that this is about your own complicated feelings. I don’t want you to feel bad, but if —”

“Okay,” I said. “Sure. We can give it a shot.”

“Really?” she asked.

“Yeah,” I said. “Why not. A week from now I might be dead, so either it’s great, and I’m glad I didn’t miss out, or it’s terrible, and then I’ll be dead.”

“Did you want to do it now?” she asked.

I looked around us, at what appeared to be a plain dirt road through the middle of some nondescript woods. “Er, no. That’s — later.”

She gave me one of her quiet, judging looks, the kind she gave when she was trying to figure me out. “Alright,” she said. “Later then. I’ll do my best to make it special.”

I lay on my back and felt my heartbeat slow back down. The scent of flowers was just about adequate to mask the scent of sex. The room around us was almost a parody of romance, with flower petals on the floor and a number of candles burning away. In my moment of clarity, I wondered whether this was something that Amaryllis had done for me, or for herself.

Amaryllis was staring at the ceiling, and when she saw me looking over, she turned to me and kissed me on the lips. She looked at my face for a moment, then resumed looking at the ceiling.

“So,” she said. “Something’s on your mind, and I can’t read minds. Yet.”

“Did you … did you come?” I asked.

“Yes,” she said, then looked over at me again, watching my face.

“Huh,” I said.

“I wouldn’t fake it, if that’s what you’re thinking,” she said.

“No,” I said. “I’m just … surprised that you were able to.”

“Why?” she asked.

“I don’t know,” I said. “I just … assumed.”

“You could have asked,” she said. “There can be a bit of awkwardness from having direct conversations, but if that was what was holding you back, then that’s a bit silly of you.”

“I’d been modeling you as asexual,” I said.

“Well, sorry I’m not a gold star asexual,” she said. “Except not at all sorry, of course.”

“Gold star?” I asked.

“By analogy to a gold star lesbian?” she asked.

“A what?” I asked back.

“It’s an Earth thing,” she said with a sigh. “Nevermind. All I’m saying is that there’s a lot of wonderful variation among people, and smacking them with labels is often counterproductive unless those labels hew really close to reality. One of the worst things that a person can do with their life is try to match a label. Especially us.”

“Because we’re different?” I asked.

“We’re exemplars,” she nodded. “I’m not even really Amaryllis anymore, I’m the Ultimates version of Amaryllis. It wouldn’t just be wrong to think of myself as being a collection of regular labels because that’s a normally unhelpful thing to do, it would be wrong because I’m so far outside of normal that it doesn’t apply.” She turned to me. “Sorry if this isn’t proper post-coital talk.”

“No,” I said. “It’s fine. Good. I like listening to you think.”

She reached over and threaded her fingers through mine. “You’re feeling okay?”

“Great,” I said.

“Sleeping with me wasn’t a mistake?” she asked.

“Nope,” I replied. “Whatever I was worried about, it was mostly in my head. I’m not sure I really understand it from your perspective, but … this worked out.”

“Good,” she said. She kissed me on the cheek, then settled back in beside me. “I know tomorrow is going to be rough for you.”

But as it turned out, we didn’t know the half of it.

Fires of my Heart

I could turn pain off and on, though it was a bit of a complicated process, and pain had a lot of useful functions that I wasn’t capable of doing a wholesale replacement of. Pain itself was a bit of an odd thing, when you thought about it, because if you were designing a body from scratch, you wouldn’t make it so the mechanism for alerting the brain to a problem to also be incapacitating or a problem in its own right. If you were one of our ancestors on the savannah and got gored by a warthog or something, what did it help for you to have a massive, distracting warning blaring at you? Now, the body did have mechanisms like adrenaline to temporarily dull the pain enough that you could deal with the current crisis, and maybe it was a way of forcing rest or temporary non-use of something that was healing, but overall, what I dubbed the ‘pain system’ seemed really half-baked in some ways and complete overkill in others. Controversially, I had never been a fan of being in pain.

Pain was controlled through the soul, at least in part. I had physical nerves, but those nerves went to the brain, and the brain seemed to work in parallel with the soul and spirit, so pain could be stopped there. I had refined the technique that I’d devised when I was in the Anglecynn blacksite, narrowing down the effects over a rather painful two days of testing with Amaryllis, which amounted to something that was very close to torture. The pain cluster was now readily identifiable, and I kept it at something like 40%, though it was hard to pin a number on.

For acquiring fire magic, I ratcheted it down to more like 1%, and even that seemed a bit high sometimes.

The process of becoming a fire mage was common enough that the field couldn’t really be controlled. All you needed to do was get set on fire and then get lucky. Because people caught on fire often enough just from random accidents, there were a lot of fire mages throughout the world just from happenstance, and though athenaeums had attempted to become centers of learning for fire magic, there was no possibility of control, not like with other magics. It also meant that allowing me to become a fire mage was something that we could do at home, on our own time.

“Anyone want to bet how many times this is going to take?” I asked.

“What would we bet?” asked Grak.

“You’re not betting with my money,” said Amaryllis.

“Well I don’t take a salary,” I said. “And almost everything that was my own personal money got made into gold, which is now stuck on the moon. So we can bet some random humiliation, I guess. A shaved head or something.”

“I can grow the hair back,” said Grak, gesturing to the axe that rarely left his hip.

“Okay,” I said. “Closest without going over, everyone else shaves their head for three days, who’s in?”

“I am,” said Grak. “I will take one hundred.”

“It’s a one in a hundred chance,” I said, frowning at him. “You really think it’s going to take a hundred times?”

“Yes,” he replied.

“We have enough bones to heal you from burning three hundred times,” said Amaryllis. “If need be, we can get more while we’re in the process, without having to stop. I have more on standby.”

“God damn,” I said. “I was thinking more like fifty.”

“It will be more like a hundred,” said Raven. She had taken up position in a chair, and there was a stack of books beside her, as she was evidently in it for the long haul. “I’ll take one hundred and twenty-seven.”

“Well, I’ll take one hundred and one,” I said.

“No,” said Grak. “Then I would only win at a specific number.”

“That’s the point,” I said.

“Then we need to reorganize our betting so that voluntarily going last doesn’t provide a significant advantage,” said Amaryllis. “Thanks for being un-fun, Juniper.”

“Sorry,” I said.

It took some time to come up with a better system for making our wagers, which I was happy for, since it meant that I would be able to put off being on fire for a little bit longer. Obviously we had the resources to do this safely and repeatedly, and it wouldn’t hurt very much at all, but there was still something psychological going on that made me extremely uneasy. I wondered whether stuntmen who set themselves on fire for a living ever lost their fear of it.

The steps were pretty simple: get a coating of accelerant, light myself up, wait a predefined amount of time while on fire, then extinguish and heal. Bodily damage was, unfortunately, a necessity, so I got to watch hair and skin burning away off my arms, sometimes going as deep as the bone. I was mildly worried that I would have some permanent scars, but the last time I’d gotten scars from a burn (dragonfire) they had been healed through a level up. After the first time through, I was less concerned, because it didn’t seem that the controlled burn of my flesh was going down to the level of my soul.

“I’m not sure that I want the goggles,” I said after the twentieth time. “There’s not really a need to watch my body burning up.”

“Just close your eyes then,” said Amaryllis. “You need to protect your eyes in case something goes wrong, and if it does go wrong, you’ll want to be able to see. Or just don’t look at your body, that would work too.”

“Are you just saying that because you went through all the trouble of getting fireproof goggles?” I asked.

“No,” she said. “Juniper, if you need a break, just let me know, but we’re potentially going to be doing this for the whole rest of the day.”

“I think you’re being pessimistic,” I said. “But okay.” Amaryllis had taken the unusual bet of ‘higher than the highest amount anyone else will guess’. The next highest had been Raven, with a thousand, and I honestly didn’t think that if we had to do it that many times we would actually keep going.

Not long in, Amaryllis put on a radio play for us to listen to, which helped a bit, because it gave my mind something to do. The radio station at Poran was quite small, run by the tuung, but it had nothing in the way of advertisements, which I appreciated. The radio plays themselves were from a huge selection that had been bought by Amaryllis, all recordings from Anglecynn. It was something, at least, even if I had heard one or two of them before.

The problem with the procedure was that it took too much time. Even relatively streamlined as it was, each attempt took five minutes or so, which included every step of the process. That meant only about twelve attempts in an hour. Once we got into the swing of things, it got a bit faster, but there were hard limits on how fast we could actually go, so long as we were attempting to do things safely, which we were.

“Unicorn bones would speed it up,” said Amaryllis. “Each bone would be worth somewhere between five or ten attempts. Some of the bones are too large to be useful in combat … but you’d said that you were working on portable extradimensional space with a stable boundary?”

“I was,” I said. “But there’s a lot of competition for my time, and I’ve been spending it on star magic as well. It’s not a problem, I can suck it up.”

“You say that,” said Amaryllis. “I don’t want to have to stretch this out another day, or worse, have you bail on it entirely. You need to make sure that you’re balancing your own psychological state.”

“I’ll be fine,” I said.

Fifty attempts came and went, with no progress to speak of. People came and went, since there wasn’t all that much for anyone to do, and watching me get repeatedly set on fire wasn’t super interesting. Amaryllis stayed the whole time, which I thought was at least partly so that she could provide moral support. Grak came by to check the wards he’d put in place every once in a while, but he seemed put off by the gruesomeness of the burnings.

“I really thought we could do it in under fifty,” I said. “Do you think there are really some dice being rolled behind the scenes, or nah?”

“It is hard to say,” said Grak, who had returned for just a bit. “Why would you think it would be under fifty?”

“Uh, I haven’t done any math,” I said. “And it’s not the kind of math that I can do instantly. But if there’s a one in one hundred chance, I’d expect that most people get it before they’ve gone through a hundred times. Like, if you were trying to roll a 20 on a d20, you’d be mildly surprised to not get a nat 20 in your first nineteen rolls.”

“That should just be nineteen twentieths to the power of nineteen,” said Grak.

“Oh, right,” I said. “Which is thirty-seven point seven percent, repeating, of course.”

“What?” asked Amaryllis. “It’s not repeating.”

“Sorry,” I said. “It’s a meme.”

“I’m sure it was very droll for you,” she replied, rolling her eyes.

“Point being, seems like most people would get the unlock before they have to actually go through the full hundred,” I said. “So it’s not totally outrageous to think that if the thing is fair and unbiased, it’s more probable than not that I won’t have to go through a full hundred times.” I cracked my neck and stretched out a bit, relishing the freedom that I didn’t have while we were repeatedly going through this procedure. “Anyway, I’m good to go, I think.”

“You still have time left,” said Amaryllis. “Better to take your break now. Anything I can get for you?”

“Nope,” I said. “And I’d like to start now, if it’s all the same to you. If you give me another five minutes, I might lose my will. Besides, I have a good feeling about the next ten. I have a point in LUK, that should help me, right?”

“Maybe,” said Amaryllis. “Assume that we’re in it for the long haul.”

We didn’t get it in the next ten, or the ten after that, or the ten after that. People still came and went, with Amaryllis being the only constant. In part, it was boring, and in part, it was terrifying, since there was something about my flesh burning that I couldn’t get used to no matter how many times it happened. Eventually, I requested a movie be put on, and we spent a bit of time talking about what there was available before I settled on Star Wars: A New Hope, which I had seen twice before and wouldn’t mind missing bits and pieces of. I didn’t even particularly like Star Wars, but it was a staple, and I had seen all of the staples, most of them with Arthur, the better to understand what more modern creators were building off of (in his words).

Eventually I stopped Amaryllis from saying which iteration we were on, so that it was simply a string of burning, extinguishing, healing, application of accelerant, and then more burning. The movie didn’t really help.

Once A New Hope was finished, I asked for another break.

“How many is that?” I asked.

“Do you want to know?” asked Amaryllis.

“Maybe,” I said. “Probably. I mean, at a certain point, we have to just say that the Dungeon Master doesn’t want to let me have this, right?”

“I suppose,” said Amaryllis. “A point beyond which it’s so improbable that we have to rule out what we know?”

I nodded. “So?”

“One hundred thirty-two,” she said.

“Fuck,” I said.

“Is it possible you missed it?” she asked.

I closed my eyes for three seconds and looked at the character sheet behind my eyelids. Everything was exactly as I had left it, and the spot where ‘Fire Magic’ would go was still blank.

“Nothing,” I said, sighing a bit. “So what’s the limit?”

“The highest record is for two thousand, four hundred and twenty-eight times,” said Raven. “It was set by a now-legendary fire mage during the time of the Second Empire.”

“Well, fuck,” I said. “I’m not doing that. Five minutes per, that’s more than eight solid days, not including breaks for sleep, food, or anything else.” I paused. “Now-legendary, you say? Is there some kind of correlation between how many attempts it takes and how much power you get?”

“No,” said Raven. “But the kind of person who has the perseverance, or more to the point, bloody-mindedness, necessary to carry on for so long will probably be well-served in other areas of their life.”

“Is that a challenge?” I asked. “Because it sounds like hell, but I think I probably could endure two weeks or so of this.”

“No one is asking you to do that,” said Amaryllis.

“I win if you’re under two hundred,” said Valencia, who had appeared in the room at some point, perhaps while I was on fire. “And keep in mind that this kind of bet is completely unfair, because Grak’s axe won’t work on me.”

“Don’t try to sway him,” said Amaryllis, casting a frown in Valencia’s direction. “Fire magic was supposed to be a key element of the final approach. It’s got a lot of beneficial interactions.”

“I haven’t been talking about bailing,” I said. “But I’ve been sick of going through with this for at least a hundred attempts now.”

“Let me know if you can think of anything that would make it more pleasant,” said Amaryllis.

“I will,” I said. “But, I guess, let’s get back to it.”

“It’s been eleven hours,” said Grak. “Perhaps tomorrow would be better.”

“Why?” I asked. “The tuung have generously offered to take up the work of sleep on our behalf. There’s no actual need to stop. Besides, eleven hours is nothing in the scheme of things, and that’s including various breaks.”

“You don’t need to push yourself,” said Amaryllis. “Grak is right. Better to rest and reset, get some maintenance in, make sure that the team is sharp.”

“Fine,” I said. “But as Captain America says, I could do this all day.”

By the fourth day, I was getting pretty fucking irritable.

“Fuck the Dungeon Master,” I said.

“Don’t say that Juniper,” said Amaryllis, who was apparently as cool as a cucumber, not letting frustration show through, if she was feeling it at all. Then again, she had thirty clones floating around out there, and was taking brief breaks to sync up with them, which meant that her lived experience was much different than mine. Also, she wasn’t the one getting set on fire, which wasn’t painful, but was a bit distressing.

“We’re in the eight hundreds, right?” I asked.

“Yes,” said Amaryllis.

“Then I’m being fucked with,” I said. “So fuck him.”

“There’s a chance that it’s legitimate,” said Amaryllis. “A low chance, but it’s there.”

“It would be approximately zero point zero one percent,” said Grak. He was folding his arms. “I would be inclined to agree with Juniper.”

“Things that are one in ten thousand happen all the time,” said Amaryllis. “That’s approximately the odds of rolling a twenty-sided dice and getting a natural 20 three times in a row.”

“The shitty thing is that I’m not even ‘due for it’,” I said.

“That is how probability works, yes,” said Grak.

“Well it’s not how the human brain works,” I said. “You go through eight hundred times of failure and your brain starts to prime itself, thinking that success is coming up. But it’s not, it’s just as likely the next time. I’m saying it’s shitty because it’s very hard to correct the magical thinking that goes on in my brain. Each failure hits harder because of that priming.”

“Then take a break,” said Amaryllis. “A long one, a few hours, go for a walk, get something to eat, take your mind off it, and if you want to call it quits, no one will blame you. You’re already well-past what most potential fire mages prepare themselves for, and it’s not crucial.”

“It is,” I said. “We need every advantage, if not for Fel Seed, which is going to be rough either way, then for the Long Stairs.”

“You’re just saying that to be hard on yourself,” said Grak. “You feel like a failure.”

“I don’t — I mean, I do, in this instance, because I don’t want to crack, but holy shit I’m tired of this, and I want to give up,” I said. “It’s a slog, it’s a grind, it’s unpleasant and nauseating, and everything that I hate about life. And it’s taking a long fucking time.” I turned to Amaryllis. “Look at it this way, what are the odds that the Dungeon Master would fuck with me? A lot higher than one in ten thousand, right?”

“I understand that,” said Amaryllis. “But the Dungeon Master has incredible power, and to do something petty like this … I don’t think that’s him, not from what we’ve seen so far. Seeing you suffer, or at least grind this out, doesn’t seem like his typical style of operation. Think about the most bullshit thing he’s pulled so far. Is this like that?”

“I guess not,” I said. “But if you’re asking me to just have faith … this really reminds me of the story of Job, where the Dungeon Master is putting me through some shit to see whether or not I’ll stick to it. Not being a dick just to be a dick, but as a test of faith? Maybe.”

“That would be more in line with what we think we know about him,” said Amaryllis. “But either way, I think you need a longer break than you’ve been taking. Rest, relax, take your mind off things, try to drain the built up stress.”

I did as she said, and wandered out into Poran, trying not to have any particular destination in mind.

When I ended up at the door to Raven’s room, I wondered whether that was just through random chance in my wandering, or whether some part of me had intended to come there. I gave a tentative knock on the door, not really knowing what I was going to say.

“Enter,” she said, so I did.

“Oh, Juniper,” she said, looking me over.

“You thought it would be someone else?” I asked.

“Some of the tuung approached me, offering to be my research assistants,” she said. “I’ve taken them up on their offer. I was surprised to find out that Amaryllis hadn’t put them up to it, actually. She seemed offended that I didn’t think of them as being able to take the initiative.” She shrugged. “I assume you’re a fire mage now?”

“No,” I said. “Just taking a break. I thought I would come here and, I don’t know, see how you were doing. Or what you were doing. You haven’t been by to visit.”

“I found it distressing,” she said. “Also boring.”

“Yeah, me too,” I replied, smiling a bit. “So what are you doing?”

“Reading, mostly,” she said. “Bethel’s been lending me Earth books.”

“Anything good?” I asked.

“Not really, no,” she said. “I had started out looking for evidence that Earth was under the dominion of the Dungeon Master, but that was a fool’s errand. From your perspective, it’s obvious that Aerb is under that dominion, not just because he rips off a lot of your old designs, but because he makes jokes that you’d have to be from Earth to get, or that you’d have to be you to get. You would know even without direct intercessions. There’s nothing like that on Earth, but that might just be because there’s an extra layer above, so all the jokes, references, and cribbings are undiscoverable by us.”

“Sounds maddening,” I said.

“It was, and I don’t want to pretend that I suffered through trying for all that long,” she said. “After that, I descended into the field of comparative media studies. In practice, that meant comparing things that Uther had written against their inspirations. Amaryllis had already done a lot of it, and not found it particularly fruitful, but for me …” she turned away from me. “For me it was a way of trying to reconcile who the man was.”

“You didn’t like what you found?” I asked.

“I was there when he wrote most of it,” said Raven. “He spent a lot of his time lost in thought, and would always answer that some new story was on his mind, or some new poem, or song, or — something. It might have been suspicious, if he hadn’t produced enough great works to banish the question from anyone’s mind.”

“And in retrospect, that question is still there,” I said. “All those times he said he was working on something now seem like deflections.”

“I’m sure it was occasionally true,” said Raven. “Even being who he was, reproducing a novel from memory is no simple task, and he did take liberties in the reconstructions, altering details and sometimes conceits in order to make the stories or characters translate across cultures.”

“Still,” I said.

“Still,” she nodded. “Still, it’s a lot of deception.”

“Has anything come from the analysis?” I asked. “Any insights?”

“He has a tendency to cast things in black and white,” said Raven. “He makes the heroes into better people, and the villains worse. There’s more of a structure to his stories. I think more telling might be in what he chose to adapt and what he left behind. There’s almost nothing of what we would call postmodernism in his own works. Maybe those aren’t the kinds of works that he enjoyed, or maybe he didn’t think the intended audience would enjoy them, or … it’s hard to know, because it’s nothing he ever spoke about. It was all internal to him.”

“Unless he told Vervain,” I said.

“Or his wife,” nodded Raven. “Or other people who weren’t me. He viewed me as being very young.”

“You were,” I said.

“In some ways,” she replied. “And in other ways, I was ancient.”

“I’m guessing you’ll have a chance to ask him,”  I said. “We’ll get our answers.”

“Or we’ll die trying to get to him,” said Raven. “Or Bethel will murder him within three seconds of us finding him. Amaryllis has been talking doom and gloom lately, specifically with me, I think, because she knows that I’m in on this plan come hells or high water.”

“I hope Uther’s decent to you,” I said.

“Decent?” she asked.

“Hrm,” I replied. “I hope that when he sees you, and understands how long it’s been, that he greets you like an old friend. I hope that he asks how you’ve been and respects that it’s been hard for you to try to fill his shoes.”

“I hope that too,” she said, nodding. “But I don’t expect that. I’ve been trying to change my perceptions of him so that they account for him being from Earth, him hiding things, him having gone a little insane, or if not insane, then maybe just working within the framework of an insane world. I’m not sure that I know what kind of man we’ll find, if we find any at all.”

“Let me know if there’s anything I can do for you,” I said. “I’m not the best equipped for much but killing, if I’m being frank, but when I say anything, I really do mean anything.”

“When you say that, it’s hard for me to not think about the mission,” said Raven. “But of course I know that’s not really what you’re offering. If it were about the mission, I would only have to ask, but if it’s about my own mental health, my own understanding of myself … it’s hard to make my mind go in that direction.”

“I know,” I said. “If I were a better friend, maybe I would understand what you need, and just do it without putting the onus on you.”

A tuung woman walked into the room carrying a stack of papers, then walked right back out once she noticed I was in there.

“How about this,” said Raven. “Tell me what it’s like to create a world.”

“For D&D?” I asked. “Or just in general?”

“Did you do much of it outside of the games?” she asked.

“A bit,” I said. “Sometimes for other systems, other times just for fun. And you’re asking this because … ?”

“It’s something you care about,” she said. “It’s something that you have honest enthusiasm for. It’s not really related to any of our missions, except insofar as it gives insight into the world we live in, which means that it will be easier to focus on you.” Left unspoken was the fact that we repeatedly failed to connect with one another, which I was fairly sure neither of us were all that happy about.

“Alright,” I said. “Usually it starts with some idea, or image, or, sometimes, me watching a movie or reading a book. Building a world is usually about that seed, and what naturally grows from it. Like, I had this idea of a world that was completely overgrown, plants everywhere, growing so fast that you have to worry about being smothered in your sleep. That’s the seed, plants growing so fast that you could realistically get smothered in your sleep. And then from there, I have questions I ask myself, which is where everything else takes place. Questions like, how do these plants grow so fast? And sometimes the answer is just ‘it’s magic’, or a longer version of ‘it’s magic’ that maybe feels a bit less lazy but contributes about as much. Otherwise, I try to think about some unifying force or phenomenon that I could put in, something that would make the plants grow so fast, something like … I don’t know, the plants are harvesting some far-off energy source due to a celestial gate that someone opened up a thousand years ago, or the elemental plane of plants collided with the elemental plane of sunlight, or a spell was ultra-maximized by a legendary artifact, or … you know, it’s the kind of thing you could do all day, thinking up things like that and trying them on, but eventually I would settle on one that was the most promising.” I looked at her. “Is this about what you wanted?”

“I think this is what makes you special,” she said.

“Not the godly powers?” I asked. “Or the fact that I came here from another world?”

“You’re special in those senses too,” she replied. “But no, this is what makes you special as a person. It’s nice to see. I’m sorry that you don’t get a chance to shine in that way.”

“Ink magic is the closest,” I said. “But that has a little bit too many restrictions on it, a little too narrow of a focus, and it wears me down.”

“And after you’ve figured out the gimmick for a world?” she asked.

I briefly considered that I was probably going over my allotted break time, but decided to say nothing about it, because I was enjoying myself. As unfortunate as it was to admit, that was a rarity with Raven.

“After the gimmick is squared away, then come the people,” I said. “You have to worry about being smothered in your sleep by plants, so then you take to the trees, or you hack things down, or you lay down a ring of salt, or you go on the seas if they’re not choked with seaweed, or you dig down below where the roots can reach, and because it’s a good way of developing a world, probably all of those things are true in different places. From that seed, that core idea of not having to find a safe place to sleep so the plants don’t grow too much around you, you can get other things that hook the imagination, like people who live in symbiosis with certain kinds of plants. I imagine a little old auntie living up in a hollowed out tree, descending on vines to a world that’s always a bit different from how it was the day before, but that’s fine, because she knows all the tricks, all the native plants and the way they ebb and flow with the weather and the seasons. I usually try to think of as many compelling things as I can, then work backward to make sure that they make enough sense.”

“Why?” she asked, cocking her head to the side.

“Why what?” I asked back.

“Why do they have to make sense?” she asked. “Uther always said that some of the best stories had some element of the nonsensical. He thought that if you had to decide between adding a few lines to make something make sense and skipping that in favor of brevity, you should choose brevity every time.”

“Eh,” I said. “It’s a conversation we had a few times. For myself, if it doesn’t hold together, it’s not actually interesting. If I poke things and they fall apart, then there’s no way that they can entertain me late at night when I should be sleeping, or in class when I’m bored by the lesson, or while I’m waiting in line, or walking somewhere, or otherwise want to detach myself from the world. And if they don’t survive at least some scrutiny, then they’ll never make good worlds for playing games in.”

“What was it that made him light up?” asked Raven. “With you, it’s easy, you just … gush about things. For him, I thought that it was his writing, his plays, even his songs, but knowing that almost all of it came from Earth, knowing that so often it must have been a deflection from his true thoughts — what was real about him?”

“Sorry,” I said. “You’re in a better position to answer that than I am. When I knew him, he had a love of dissection, of argument. He liked to tear things apart to construct the hottest take he could.” I saw the confusion on her face. “He liked to put forward inflammatory arguments just for the sake of how difficult they were to defend, or to make conversation.”

“Ah,” she said. “That he did. But looking back on it, with the context that I have from Earth, it seems like many of his ‘hot takes’ are just what a teenager from the Midwestern United States of America might have taken for granted. Did you know that he advocated for democracy?”

“Dangerous thing for a king to do,” I said. “But yes, I’m something of an Uther scholar myself. I’ve read a lot of his arguments. It’s weird, because there’s nothing perverse about them. I don’t mean perverse like — just nothing that makes it seem like he’s taking the piss, I guess. There’s no satire, no ‘modest proposals’, it’s just straightforward rote argumentation. Some of it is gripping, but it’s just … played straight, I guess. Maybe that’s him having grown up, or maybe it’s him playing a role, but it’s hard for me to not read it as kind of sad.”

“I worry,” said Raven. “That used to be my job, when I was Head Librarian, so maybe I just got in the habit, but knowing what I do about Uther, I worry about the reunion.”

“Yeah,” I said. “Me too.”

“I’m not sure you could beat him, if it came to that,” she said.

“No?” I asked. “I mean, even with the full team?”

She bit her lip for a moment. “If we all made it through Fel Seed, and whatever is waiting in the Long Stairs … I don’t know.”

“Okay,” I said. “We’re not natural enemies though. Arthur and I were friends.”

“I know,” she said. “But I worry.”

I nodded. “Sorry,” I said. “I should have stuck with talking about something that I love.”

“It’s okay,” said Raven, giving me a forced smile. “We can go back to that.”

I hesitated, thinking that it was time to go back to the fires, then pressed on anyway, working through the development of an idea into something that someone might some day want to play, or that would at least get me through a boring class.

She seemed to take some enjoyment from it, at least, which I suppose shouldn’t have been as surprising as it was. She shared that in common with Maddie, and maybe gave me a bit of insight into what Maddie had actually been like. Maybe Maddie hadn’t asked me so many questions because she wanted attention, or because she was annoying. Maybe it was because it was a chance to see me when I was happiest. It was hard to tell though: Maddie and Raven were wildly different people, for all the points of similarity.

I left just in time to meet Amaryllis, who had apparently decided that it was time to see whether I was going to be coming back to set myself on fire again.

“Odd of you to seek her out,” said Amaryllis. “Not that I’m complaining.”

“Yeah,” I said. “It was surprisingly good though. I think she’s a little bit stressed, and obviously the trial by fire isn’t going well, but I think we helped each other, at least a little.”

“Good,” said Amaryllis.

“You need to stop unloading your fears and concerns on her,” I said. “It’s getting to her.”

“Noted,” sighed Amaryllis. “I’d thought we were of a like mind.”

“You are,” I said. “But she’s not made of iron like you are.” I shrugged. “Just a thought.”

“No, you’re probably right,” she said. “Are you ready to return to the fires?”

“I guess,” I said. “But I wish that life could be more about conversations, and less about repeatedly setting yourself on fire in order to get a somewhat marginal benefit for a fight against a being of such immense power that there’s almost no way we could possibly win a direct battle.”

And, of course, I got it first try back.

Skill Unlocked: Fire Magic!

Achievement Unlocked: Actually, We Did Start the Fire

I breathed a long sigh of relief and satisfaction as stress drained from me and an unpleasant task was finally completed, then steeled myself for a day of racing through the skill levels as quickly as I could.

The Road

The plan had been to fly in as quickly as we possibly could, moving in a straight line toward the City of a Thousand Brides while in Bethel. We would go at multiples of the speed of sound, completely warded by Grak. We were going to make a crash landing, with Bethel killing almost everything she could see, then either high-tail it down to the basement of the palace with velocity magic, or have Bethel drill us down there, depending on what we saw. Our big problem was that remote viewing on Aerb was virtually non-existent, and the remote viewing that we could use hadn’t been helpful enough. Once we were on site, my wildly heightened remote senses would help us figure out what conditions on the ground were, and let us bee-line to the Long Stairs, or failing that, rip a hole there.

Amaryllis had created an FSP document, the Fel Seed Plan, and she’d fretted over the thing using dozens of clones, breaking it apart, testing whatever parts of it were testable, putting us through training … it was all fairly uninteresting, frankly, but our plan was to go in with every advantage we could muster, and ideally, take all those advantages into the Long Stairs with us.

We were inside Bethel, who had so many entads at her disposal that a more foolish person might have thought that there would be no way to defeat her. The only way that we knew to defeat her was a full-entad ward, or one that had been set up specifically for her. She could move at three times the speed of sound, teleport, portal, warp space and time, shift into the ethereal realm, become invisible to almost every sense, control almost every one of Aerb’s twenty-eight elements, and make frighteningly accurate predictions of the near future, so long as they didn’t involve anything with a soul.

Bethel was the size of a needle, moving invisibly. Inside, we were time dilated, a day to every minute that passed outside, and hooked into her sensorium through some combination of entads, given an augmented reality display of everything that was happening out to a mile around her. If not for the time dilation, it would all have been happening too fast for any of us to actually follow. In theory, Bethel could pilot us straight to the exact place we were looking for, using portals or short-range teleportation once we were close enough for those to function.

The pace was glacial. We were going more than two thousand three hundred miles an hour, but with the dilation we were under, the one hundred and thirty-eight miles we had to travel was going to take a subjective three and a half days, and that was if it was just us moving in a straight line. If Bethel was able to get into the palace in the City of a Thousand Brides, it would take even longer, because her full speed wasn’t possible if she had to do any actual navigation.

We didn’t talk much. Well, most of us. Little Pallida was just the fucking worst, I mean really terrible, and I didn’t understand why we were bringing her along. Even when young, Pallida had a pseudo-magically powerful ability to get through locks, and she could be stealthy as hell if she wanted to be, but those weren’t actually relevant abilities. I suspected Amaryllis of ulterior motives, but it wasn’t like her to not come clean about ulterior motives when directly asked.

The landscape crawled by, and we were there for every riveting minute of it. I had been worried that three solid days of going over Fel Seed’s domain would be bad for morale, but it was much more tame than I had been expecting. It wasn’t pretty or lush, but there was little of what I had dreamt up. Instead, it was mostly dead and barren.

In the Manxome Foe campaign, Fel Seed had been rather new within the timeline of the world, a fresh monstrosity. The world had been dying, but it hadn’t been dying for as long as anyone could remember. I had never put a date on it, because I loathed making timelines, but he had been around for maybe twenty years, and not all of that had been when he was at the height of his power, or at least, he had hidden his true power for some of it.

On Aerb? On Aerb, he had been living in the same zone for five hundred years, long enough that generations of people had come and gone, long enough that he was a subject in history books, even if they were history books of the gruesome and macabre. Fel Seed was pure, monotonous evil, but that didn’t mean that he wouldn’t change over time, it was just a question of how. Like Blue-in-the-Bottle, there was little question that he was engaging in his own breeding programs, but rather than just making slaves, he was making … well, it was hard to say. Monsters, certainly, but I had to guess that he was also making the next generation of brides. It seemed like a Fel Seed thing to do. There always had to be another level of disgusting with him, that was kind of the point.

I wondered if he would ever get bored though. This was his domain, likely forever, but if I put myself in his position, I imagined that depression would eventually follow. His gimmick was shocking torture and imagery, but how long could he go until that well ran dry? Forever was the obvious answer, but it didn’t feel true to me. It wasn’t interesting. Fel Seed, locked up in this place, with only the targets he’d made for himself … my idea of him, and what I’d expressed of him, was that he liked the grandeur, liked the pain, liked the shock and horror, the feeling of hope washing right off a person in the face of what he had prepared for them. Five hundred years though? That seemed like a long time. It seemed like he would have relished something like the Fifth Empire coming in to destroy him, a chance to flex on people who had only the vaguest idea what he was really capable of. And after that climactic parallel timeline battle, he’d come back, as though it had never happened. I could imagine the rush that would come from that, the sheer artwork of despair, so much cost, so many lives lost, and then everything put back the way it was before. If I’d been Fel Seed, locked up for hundreds of years, with only my imagination, and no new people, or at least no people I hadn’t created, I would want to play with the outside world.

It seemed like us paying him a visit would have been exactly the kind of thing that would re-energize him.

I watched another few miles crawl by. There was no flesh, nothing out of the ordinary, just a plain, mostly dead landscape. We passed what might have once been a town, but there were no monsters there, no people. I was grateful for that, but also a little bit worried.

By the far the worst place we’d been on Aerb was the Doris Finch Exclusion Zone. There, bodies had been piled in the streets, a stench had hung in the air, more than half the people were slaves, or effectively slaves, there was cannibalism, abuse — it was hard to stomach. I’d thought that Fel Seed’s zone would be worse, that every mile would be some new monstrosity or horror presented explicitly for us to see. I’d thought that we would go through three days of it.

“Juniper, what’s under the ground?” Amaryllis asked me.

I frowned at her, and tried to tune in with my senses. The way things were set up, in our little virtual environment, I could see what Bethel saw, but her ability to penetrate ground was limited to maybe five feet. My own ability was better, but only in terms of water magic, and while I had gotten much more fine-grained sensory input and control, it was still hard to pick out exactly what things were by the shape of the water. Still —

“It’s consistent with flesh,” I said. “I’d thought that it was the water table, but you’re right, it’s not quite right for that. Probably miles and miles of flesh beneath us. He’s put in roots that probably go as far down as they’re able. Further down than I can actually sense. Hard to tell if it’s biofactories or weapons or defenses or what. There’s a ton of it though.”

The scale was hard to imagine. If those were factories of some kind, my guess was that he had more factory space than the whole rest of Aerb combined. What he was making was impossible to say, as was where he was storing it. If those were weapons hidden beneath the surface, then he had the equivalent of a Death Star.

It was worrying that all of it was hidden. I didn’t know who it was hidden from, or why.

We were fifty miles out when Bethel’s voice came into our heads.

{{Problem.}}

I’d been watching the ground crawl by for two days, doing my best to stay alert. Bethel was going insanely fast, but we were watching it all insanely slow.

In contrast, the massive pieces of rock coming out of the ground seemed to be going the speed of, say, a kid riding on a bicycle, which meant that in reality, they were moving at many multiples the speed of sound. Earth was slipping off of them like water. I could see the shockwaves around them as they moved through the air, and it was hard not to miss that they were going considerably faster than we were. Bethel had become inviolable thanks to the entads she had, but that didn’t mean that we couldn’t get knocked around, slowed down, stopped, trapped … all the usual concerns, even if she had a few ways around all of them. Every trick had a counter-trick.

Bethel began evasive maneuvers, but she was slower than the pieces of rock that were rising out of the ground, and slower by a fairly significant margin. It was wrong to say that they were rising out of the ground, actually, because something had propelled them, or was propelling them, all with the energy of an atom bomb, coming from both our left and right. Just before the leading shockwaves reached us, she transitioned into the ethereal realm, attempting to avoid them entirely.

In D&D, the ethereal plane mostly coexisted with the Prime Material Plane, existing as a place of ghosts and spirits, allowing anyone who went into it to move straight through solid objects, flying without gravity. My ring of partial incorporeality had used the ethereal plane, and I missed it dearly, but it had been eaten by the Cannibal, or at least lost somewhere in Anglecynn and had never recovered. On Aerb, the ethereal realm worked a little bit differently, in that it had gravity, no air, and a geography of its own. Sometimes the ethereal was inaccessible thanks to a giant mountain in the way, or other times, the ground was lower in the ethereal, causing you to drop down.

I don’t know why I was at all surprised, given that it figured, and given that Amaryllis’ FSP explicitly stated it, but the ethereal realm inside Fel Seed’s exclusion zone was entirely taken over by him. There were no rocks moving toward us at extreme velocities though. Instead, there were white orbs, each the size of a car, floating around at irregular spacing. Almost as soon as we were into the ethereal they began to glow, not just around us, but over a mile away as well. The first lightning bolt shot out not that long after, slowed down, in my view, slow enough that I could see the stepped leaders coming in, trying to find us. Bethel dipped and twirled, but the maneuvering she’d already done had slowed her considerably, and compared to the speed we’d been going before, she was dawdling along. We missed the first bolt, but the second hit us, and while Bethel was inviolable, and had some faculty with lightning, it slammed into us hard enough that we were knocked off course.

Bethel wasn’t as slowed down as we were. She had enough entad intelligence that we’d hit some serious diminishing returns, the point where the only remaining gains were from parallelization. All of that allowed her to process information more quickly than before, which had already been quite quick. She was still, unfortunately, slower than a lightning strike. The more we were hit, the more she slowed down, and while she had impeccable defenses, the force and energy had to go somewhere, a process that she couldn’t fully control. There was a risk that we would cook alive inside her. It was something that had come up in our threat modeling, and which we hadn’t found a good solution for.

She went weapons free as she spun around with us inside her, lancing out at the ethereal white blobs, popping a few of them where she focused her fire. There were too many of them though, and up from the ground there were other things rising, ghostly green creatures. It was possible to see into the material plane from the ethereal, and the walls of rock that had been approaching us at incredible speeds were smashing into each other, right where we had been. They wouldn’t have been able to harm Bethel, but perhaps they could have held her in place for long enough that other weapons could be deployed. Void was a vulnerability, even with ultra thick plating.

Bethel teleported us forward a mile, then shifted us back into the prime material. Almost at once, the same attack we’d just escaped was renewed once more. Vast quantities of rock were launched into the air at us, faster than even the ludicrous rates that Bethel was capable of. This time she chose to go up, trying to escape the two walls of moving rock by positioning herself higher than the point where they would slam into each other. For a while, it seemed like it might work, but as the mountains of rock crashed against each other, something dark, black, and very very fast shot up from the expanding cloud of debris. It was quickly followed by a second, and a third, and by the time the first reached us, there were several dozen of them, all moving out of the dust and ejecta of the ongoing collision at mind-boggling speeds.

The one nearest to us opened up, casting its outer casing off with an explosive blast. Inside was a purple crystal, which was already charging. There were hundreds of them following after, all rising up from below. Bethel could teleport and use portals, but the entads that allowed that were limited, not enough to cross fifty miles, and not when we might need them to beat a retreat, or get into the Long Stairs.

“Void,” said Amaryllis. “Bethel, portal down, we’re coming out.”

Bethel obliged, using another portal to bring us to the ground another few miles forward, and as soon as that was done, we were unceremoniously spat out. Behind us, the slabs of rock were still falling to the ground, enormous chunks broken off in the collision raining down from the sky. Some of them landed above us, bouncing off Grak’s shield before smashing into the ground, and we all waited for a moment, seeing if there was going to be some other attack. Personally, I wasn’t a huge fan of this section of the FSP.

“Everyone around Grak,” said Amaryllis, though we already were.

“No imminent threats,” I said. Threat detection was one of my roles in all this. The ground was still settling. “There are fucking miles of flesh beneath the ground still. Nothing moving toward us though.”

“He was throwing the ground. How can he even do that?” asked Bethel. “Throwing it at hypersonic speeds! I shifted into the ethereal and there were balls of something that shot electricity! And green things! And those missiles!” She must have come into this with a higher opinion of our capabilities than I did, or maybe a lower opinion of Fel Seed’s.

“At no point should anyone worry about how anything he’s done is possible,” said Amaryllis. “It isn’t. He cheats. We know this.”

“He wants us to walk in,” I said. “He wants us to not skip anything. We’re going to have to face him.”

“Anticipated,” said Amaryllis.

“We all read the FSP,” said Grak. “Chance of bad outcomes has spiked.”

“We can’t abort,” said Amaryllis. “Likely we literally can’t abort.”

“We shouldn’t have stopped,” said Raven, turning to Amaryllis. “We should have pushed forward, or fled. We’re at least forty miles out.”

“Thirty-two,” said Bethel. “I was able to get us closer.”

“Second-guessing isn’t part of the plan,” said Amaryllis, her lips thin. “We’re a team. We should get moving.”

“Is that seriously what your stupid plan says?” asked Pallida. She was still roughly twelve, despite my objections. “Just get moving, on foot, toward a place literally worse than being in the hells? Walking on rocks that just moments ago were launched into the air at us by someone who knows we’re here, knows that we’re going against him?” The dust was still settling, and rocks were still raining from the air, some of them as large as cars, though nothing that big had hit us yet.

“That is the plan, yes,” said Amaryllis. “We’re at the part of the FSP where we face him on his own terms.” She turned to Bethel. “There was nothing you could have done.”

“Nothing?” she asked.

“Nothing,” I said. “If he wanted you brought down, he was always going to do it. He’s not beholden to the rules, and even if he was, he’s had five hundred years to practice magic of his own, or create creatures that can harness magic for him. He’s captured plenty of people.”

“Going fast is unlikely to help,” said Amaryllis. “We’re miles from the city because that’s where he wants us to be. We’re talking right now because he’s allowing us to talk.”

“What happens if we try to escape?” asked Grak. “There are no wards to stop us from teleporting. None of us have been infected with his magic.”

“Not yet,” said Raven, her face grim.

If even the smallest spore landed on you, Fel Seed could work his way into your system, and alter you enough that you, too, would be excluded, never able to leave his zone, not by any means. We were warded against everything, with additional defenses beyond that, but it was still terrifying to think about, and had been one of the main points of discussion. Grak had gone through the trouble of giving each of us a ward against Fel Seed’s magic, individually anchored, which had meant he had to spend time in the time chamber recovering concordance.

“We might still be able to escape,” said Amaryllis, looking toward the city, so far away it couldn’t yet be seen. “He might try to kill us before we could, but right now he’s inviting us in.”

“You’re reading too much into it,” said Valencia.

“We should get moving,” said Amaryllis. “Before we’re made to get moving.”

“Inside Bethel or outside?” I asked.

“Outside, per the FSP,” said Amaryllis. She gave me a look that suggested she thought I hadn’t read the FSP, and I gave her a look that was meant to suggest that of course I had read the FSP, I just wanted to know whether or not we were deviating from it. Let the record show that I had read the FSP, twice. After slogging my way through most of the Bible (I skipped Numbers), it was practically a breeze.

We were centered around Grak, keeping within his wards, which allowed nothing through and killed everything in their wake. Valencia carried Bethel, who was a much thinner staff than the last time she’d taken that form. I took the lead, with Grak not far behind me. I had gotten Water Magic high enough now that I could more or less tell where people were, so long as they were large enough and in range, and with the runeworks on top of my armor, I could in theory tank some pretty ridiculous amounts of direct damage. None of that mattered in the face of Fel Seed, but at least it was something.

We’d gone a hundred feet when the locus appeared alongside us. That wasn’t entirely unexpected, but she was outside Grak’s bubble of protection, and I was worried that she had, in an instant, been infected by spores. It was possible Fel Seed would make rapid changes to her body to make her a permanent fixture of his realm. I wasn’t even sure how that would work, given that the locus was only allowed here through virtues that I had. Maybe it just didn’t apply.

“Is she going to be okay?” asked Raven, looking nervously at the six-eyed doe.

“Hope so,” I said.

We kept walking.

Fel Seed’s domain was still less obviously evil than I had envisioned it, keeping its fleshy nature cloaked. There were dead trees, but they weren’t made of gross things, no leaves crafted from skin, no bark made of scabs, or whatever else I had worked up in my mind in those terrible months when I was running the campaign. The grass didn’t seem to be made of hair or nerve endings or anything else, it was just dead grass. Of course, below the surface, there was flesh, I could tell by how the masses of water felt, and there were constructions there, vast somethings of biological nature. At least some of it was the machinery necessary to shoot hypersonic rocks at people, and some more of it was probably those void missiles, but there was enough matter that it probably wasn’t just that. The possibilities were literally endless, because while Fel Seed was biology-themed, I didn’t for a second believe that everything he could do fell under fine-tuned biomanipulation. Hells, the supposedly biological organisms on Aerb didn’t always seem to follow normal biological rules, even if they registered as non-magical.

Beyond that, Fel Seed had enough resources to work with that he didn’t need to keep within his theme, though I did wonder when and how he had gotten enough void crystals to carpet his zone with them out to fifty miles away from the city. My guess was that they’d been brought in by a conspirator, but it could have happened ages ago.

The fact that all of it was hidden, out of direct view, was frightening in its own right.

Tween Pallida started singing a Fel Seed song that she had apparently prepared for the occasion, titled ‘Fel Seed is Bad’. I stopped her before she could finish a verse that seemed like it was going to rhyme something with ‘He’ll grab you by your nape’.

“Are we just going to walk in silence then?” she asked, after being shushed. “What in the fuck is the point of marching to your death if you’re not going to have fun doing it?”

“We can literally age you up at any time,” I said. “It’d be better for you and better for us.”

“Nah,” said lil’ Pallida. “I’m a better thief at this age. There’s going to be a lock somewhere, and my dumbfuck older self wouldn’t be able to get past it. Besides, she wouldn’t want to come, said so herself in her journal, though that just goes to show how fucking dumb she is, because of course I’m not going to listen to her.”

We walked on, mostly in silence. It was clear to me that we were recreating the original session, and not by our own intent. I wished that we had something like phantom steeds, but we needed to stay within range of Grak, at least in order to have full protection. That would potentially make things awkward in combat, but if the locus had some way of purging even the slightest biological touch, then things would be quite a bit safer. We also had our personal wards, but Grak didn’t trust them, and didn’t think that we should either. I kept blinking on my magic vision, not just to check for threats, but to make sure the ward was still there, like a forgetful person patting their pocket for the fifth time to make sure they still had their keys. I had velocity magic, and could have tried to run in, but it was pretty clear the big guns would be brought out.

“Not much around,” said Amaryllis, looking out over the plains. I couldn’t help but compare the geography to Kansas, which was notoriously flat and boring. “I was thinking there would be … more.”

“Yeah,” I said.

“Luring us into a false sense of security?” asked Valencia. “Or something else?” She turned to look at me. I was the resident expert on Fel Seed psychology, unfortunate as that was.

“I don’t know,” I said. “It’s not … like him.”

I didn’t want to say it out loud, but maybe the Dungeon Master was going to go easy on me. Maybe he was going to show me what the session should have been like, how a villain could be brought low in a moment of triumph. The DM wasn’t supposed to set himself against the players, he was supposed to set things up for them to knock down, sometimes with enough risk involved that there was a chance of a bad ending, but only so that the win felt better.

I was hoping the reason we weren’t being shown the bad stuff was because I didn’t want to see it. I was hoping that my comeuppance for the Fel Seed Incident was having my nose rubbed in how poorly I’d done, by way of seeing it done better.

We were thirty-two miles from the City of a Thousand Brides when any hope of that being true evaporated.

The road we were on was packed earth, with no indication that anyone actually used it. We hadn’t aligned ourselves with the road, but rather, had stumbled across it, laid out for us in exactly the direction we wanted to go. It was hard to say whether Fel Seed had built it specifically for us the moment we decided to get out and walk in, or whether it had always been there, preemptively prepared in some way by the Dungeon Master.

The horrors started off simply, with women impaled on stakes, one every five feet or so. In a traditional impalement, someone was stuck through with a long stake and then left to be further penetrated by gravity until they’d bled out enough to die, or had something vital poked. These bodies were fresh, no more than an hour old by Bethel’s analysis, and their deaths had been swift and sudden, the stake slammed right through them, sometimes exiting the tops of their heads. It went on for a mile, this corridor of death, more than a thousand bodies lined up for us. We tried bottling souls, early on, just in case any of them were within the window of viability, but none of them were, and eventually we stopped trying.

Then there was a second mile, this one with women who were still, to various degrees, alive.

We took them down and healed them, one by one, then stored them inside Bethel, which she accepted without comment or complaint. It took quite a lot of time. They had all been infected by Fel Seed’s magic, unable to leave the zone without dying, but there was a chance that something could be done. Per the FSP, if there was nothing we could do, Bethel would kill and bottle them all, then dump the bodies and escape. In the meantime, they would be sedated.

It was entirely possible that they were monsters rather than people. There was no real way to check, though Bethel’s senses were fine enough to rule out a lot of possibilities. It was clearly within Fel Seed’s skillset to make a meat puppet shaped like a person, or to implant within someone a great and terrible weapon, one disguised so finely that Bethel would only be able to see it as it unfolded.

The third mile —

Look, this went on for thirty-two miles. There’s no way for me to give you a sense of the monotony of it, the sick feeling that sat in my stomach for the days that it took us to get through it all. After those first two miles, there started to be fighting, and it picked up in fervor as we moved forward. The horrors we saw — the point was to be gross, to be crude, to shock and disgust, all to the point of apathy and boredom. To recount them here would inflict them on you, and I don’t want to do that. I don’t think I could do that, because if we had to go through it all, you and I together, you would probably just stop reading.

I was fourteen when I read The 120 Days of Sodom, the Marquis de Sade’s magnum opus, penned while he was in prison. The whole thing made me ill, but I kept at it, in the same way that I imagine a lot of teenagers do, when they realize that the perversions and horrors of the world are right at their fingertips. It was like watching videos of beheadings in the Middle East, or that one video where some Ukranian teenagers murder a homeless guy with a hammer, or … lots of stuff really, the kind that made me a little bit sick, that I never wanted to see a second time.

It was thirty-two miles of that, and not a single punch pulled. It was pointless, uninteresting in its cruelty, very occasionally imaginative, but usually just crude and base. It made me feel like if I breathed wrong, I would start throwing up, but that was just nausea. Everything we saw affected me, especially because there was so much of it.

We tried getting back in Bethel, to push on ahead fast, to cover these horrifying miles in an instant, but the moment we boarded, the other weapons came out, the serious ones, and we disembarked almost as quickly, having not moved an inch. Our skipping past this ever-increasing string of horror wasn’t a part of the script, so we stuck to the script. So it was written in the FSP, long may we follow it, amen.

“Why is he doing this?” Amaryllis asked when we were halfway through. I had hoped to see some weakness in her. I’d have found it comforting, but she sheathed her sword with practiced ease and a steadiness that I envied.

“He hates us,” I said. “Hates us with a burning passion. This is all foreplay for when he kills us down to the last. Which will take a while, because he’s not going to make it fast.”

“No,” said Amaryllis. “Not Fel Seed, I understand him, why is the Dungeon Master doing this?”

“Same answer,” I replied.

“If you believe that, then why are we doing this?” asked Amaryllis.

“Because there’s a chance,” I said.

It was torture, plain and simple, though almost purely psychological. There were things for us to fight, at first under the safety of Grak’s aegis, and later outside of it, under our own lesser defenses. We used up resources and tricks as we went. Some of them were possible to shoot down from long range, but that stopped working fairly early on as the next iteration of creatures would either pop up from the ground, be fired through the air at us, or had defenses that could resist the raw might of Bethel. All of it we could kill though, one way or another. They had been designed for us to kill, and designed to show off different abilities. If you’d put all the tricks together into one super monster, it would be unbeatable, and that was rather the point.

It was all part of the FSP, down a line of contingencies that Amaryllis had prepared for but hoped we would never use. The plan was to trudge along, kill everything in our path, and get to the palace, then fight our way through to the Long Stairs. When we were at the palace we would hopefully have eyes on the portal, or corridor, or whatever it actually was, and then we could use Bethel and one of her remaining portals to get right to it, if it looked like we could without being completely obliterated.

And if we had to, we would fight Fel Seed, and somehow, we would win.

The last two miles were the worst. The horror had been gradually escalating, both in the monsters that were presented for us to fight, and in the psychological aspects. There were bystanders of all kinds, most of them in great pain, and damage was freely inflicted upon them, and sometimes had to be in the course of trying to make progress. Once, for a few brief minutes, it rained babies. In those last two miles though, with the walls of the City of a Thousand Brides visible to us in the distance, the tenor of it changed. It became personal.

After so many miles of monsters, it was almost refreshing to just get a woman’s corpse. There were other corpses ahead, dotted along the field, and I could guess where it was going just from what I could already see.

When we flipped the corpse over, it was Amaryllis.

We called them effigies, because we didn’t want to call them clones. Fel Seed didn’t have our essence, or shouldn’t have, no scrap of our DNA or anything like it, but that hadn’t stopped him from making perfect likenesses of us, down to our scars and the freckles on our skin. All he’d really needed to have done was to look at us with special-purpose eyes, and after Invreizen had looked at me with all those different eyes, I was pretty sure that biology alone would allow the kinds of detailed long-range analysis for something that was close enough to a clone. We spent some time at the first one, an effigy of Amaryllis laying dead in the middle of the road, looking it over.

“It’s a shoddy fake,” said Bethel. “So many details are wrong.”

No one else agreed.

“Face protocol,” said Raven. “If he can make convincing duplicates of us, then he can potentially fool us. Juniper is muting us, but we should assume he can hear everything we say.”

I nodded. “Face protocol.”

There were more corpses along the way, effigies of all of us. I was waiting for one that Fel Seed shouldn’t have known about, one directed specifically at me, but no, it was just members of the group, everyone except for Bethel, who hadn’t shown a human form in all that time. I kept looking at the bodies, expecting to see Tiff, or Reimer, or my mom. I thought we would see someone who Fel Seed had, somehow, in violation of the exclusion zone, actually killed, a real person hiding in among all those effigies he must have made from scratch. There was nothing like it though, just a field of dead bodies that looked just like us, including one of the locus.

In the last mile before the walls, past the corpses that looked just like us, the effigies had been set in motion.

It was a bit of a ‘more is less thing’. We’d gone through mile after mile of horrible monsters and terrible scenes, tortures of innocents presented to us over and over again in nauseating quantity and variety. It had taken days. By the time we actually got to seeing tortures played out on copies of ourselves, my brain was pretty much mush. It didn’t seem to matter to me anymore that these things were happening to someone who looked and sounded like Amaryllis, or Raven, or Grak, or even myself. We freed them all the same, where possible, and killed the monsters that were savaging them. Sometimes we would put the effigies out of their misery, bottling their souls afterward.

It was another grueling mile at the end of a long list of grueling miles, all prepared for us by Fel Seed, all part of his power trip, or for the pleasure of seeing us miserable. We were going to have to confront him, I was absolutely sure of that, and if we left, if we even could leave, then at some point we’d have to come back and do it again. In the long term, Fel Seed couldn’t be left unresolved.

I watched people who looked just like my friends get torn apart. There was sexual violence, of course. There were posed scenes, dioramas, horrible things done to exact copies of people I knew and loved. I hated it, and eventually Valencia called for a break. We listened to Valencia: it was in the FSP. We shot at what we could see, delivering death at a distance, with no resistance to speak of.

“Why’d we stop?” asked Amaryllis. She was still as stoic as ever. I wondered whether she would display some vulnerability once this was over, show some impact that the horrors had on her, but there was nothing, just a glacial coldness.

It was wearing on everyone else, except perhaps Bethel, who was a staff, and had no face for me to read. Raven was sagging slightly, Grak looked morose, and even the locus moved with a bowed head. Little Pallida, in contrast, seemed to be burning with an anger she’d been keeping up for nearly the whole time we’d been walking down this forsaken road. Valencia was doing the best of us, but I didn’t know whether that was because she was projecting calm, or because she’d seen more horrors than the rest of us.

“We stopped because tensions are high,” said Valencia. “We need to air them. Better to do it now.”

“Go ahead,” said Amaryllis.

“Juniper was going to ask Bethel whether she could sense anything,” said Valencia. “Bethel was going to reply with biting sarcasm, something to the effect of ‘yes, I just thought I would keep it secret’, which would run the risk of escalating a conflict.” She said this all dispassionately, as though reading a receipt. “Raven is wondering why it’s always women, which Juniper feels defensive about, and would deflect on, which would risk escalation of conflict. In fact, Juniper knows why it’s always women, which is that he personally finds it more shocking and horrible when bad things happen to women, especially if there’s some element of sexuality involved. He recognizes this as being inherently unfair to both women and men, but his efforts to reframe his view of the world have so far failed, and in his opinion, so long as his actions don’t reflect that bias too badly, he’s not going to worry about it. There’s some unresolved guilt there though.”

“Wow,” I said.

Valencia looked between us. “I think that’s all that needs to be said right now. It would be easier if I could see all your faces.” We all wore helmets and were as close to hermetically sealed as we could be, sometimes with entad support. I had a small entad marble in my mouth that made it so I didn’t have to breathe, while Grak had an entad ring whose microportal could deliver air, water, or even food to him.

“Are we good to go?” asked Amaryllis.

“Wait,” said Valencia. “Grak?”

“I’m fine,” he said.

“He’s not fine,” said Valencia. “Grak, Juniper’s view of you as essentially male doesn’t mean that he inherently devalues you as a person, nor that he’s incapable of viewing you as equally vulnerable or emotionally real.”

“I’m more upset by the gratuitous violence,” said Grak.

“Well, yes,” replied Valencia. “But I’m trying to help with the sinking feelings you have that I can actually help with. Your particular mindset leads you to look for excuses to be unworthy in the eyes of others. Juniper’s misogyny —”

“Hang on a minute,” I said.

“Let me finish,” snapped Valencia. “Juniper’s misogyny cuts both ways. He views you as being stronger and more self-reliant than he would if he viewed you as being strictly female. He trusts you more to be on your own, to protect the group, to serve your function.”

“Can I have a moment to defend myself?” I asked.

“Of course,” nodded Valencia. “Or I could defend you, if you prefer?”

“Sure,” I said. She was going quickly through everything, and there was something a little amusing about it, like she was speedrunning conversations that she was hoping would help. I wondered whether that humor was intentional, and decided that it probably was. I needed something, anything, that was remotely light. Little Pallida had turned into a ball of rage.

“Generally speaking, it doesn’t cause problems,” said Valencia. “It’s all a product of your Midwestern upbringing, you understand and acknowledge that. You’ve killed your share of women, not letting their gender stop you. At the same time, you’ve never balked at a woman being in charge, never shunned the protection offered by a woman, never shown discomfort at a woman being better than you in manly ways — your wife being the primary example here — and to the extent you have a worldview which is tainted by these lessons you’ve learned early in life, you generally haven’t let it infect your thinking about the people close to you, nor your thinking about society at large. What we’re seeing here, horrors partially built by you, were built because they are visceral and base.”

I still felt uncomfortable at what she’d said, but it was as good a defense as I would have given, and I wasn’t actually in the mood for an argument about the purity of my mind or heart. She was right, after all. Dead women made me uncomfortable in a way dead men didn’t, and that was at a sub-intellectual level. I didn’t really agree that it was misogyny, but Tiff and I had discussed it before, and in her view, there was probably some other, less loaded word to use.

“We should get moving,” said Amaryllis. “Ever onward, against the dark.”

“That was a joke in ill-taste,” said Valencia, holding up a hand in Raven’s direction. “We’re all ready for this to be over. Let’s keep the bitter humor to a minimum.”

We pressed on, killing our body doubles, destroying the dioramas that had been set up for us, and trying to keep our minds off it. Little Pallida had stopped cracking jokes a long while back, not because it was inappropriate, not because no one was laughing, but because it seemed like it was all getting to her. She’d shared some of her own traumas with us, usually in a crude, mocking way. She would imply that we were soft, weak creatures since we had never been dumped, still living, into a mass grave, or been sold into slavery, or — on and on. She wasn’t totally over the cumulative trauma she’d suffered her various times being twelve-years-old, that was clear.

The City of a Thousand Brides was circled by an enormous wall, and a particularly useless one given that Fel Seed was entirely capable of killing anything within a hundred miles. Anything that he couldn’t kill wouldn’t have been stopped by a fucking wall, that was for sure.

The front gate was open a crack, and I imagined that the whole thing had been built while we were on our way over, the gate, at least, if not the wall itself. The whole purpose of that front gate seemed to be the enormous doors, upon which were nailed effigies, one of each of us. They were all nude, as nearly everything had been so far, and there was writing below each of them. Bethel read it first, to examine it for suspected memetic content, and then I took a read of my own. It was name-calling, nothing more, and none of it was particularly true to each of us, nothing that cut straight to our hearts at our smallest insecurities.

We walked through the city, and though we saw various traces of inhabitation, there were no more monsters, no women, nothing but a straight path to the palace.

Interval

Back on Aerb, I was pulled from a large machine, one surrounded on all sides by death. It was a huge auditorium, one that looked similar to the portal I’d just left, but laid on its side. Instead of a wide variety of different mortal species, there were Dorises, each of them with their brains hooked together with long wires, though with a sophistication and rigidity that hadn’t been there in the version that was in the hells. There were also ten bubbles, each of them painted black to disguise what was inside, and from the small glass bottles attached to each, I thought it likely that the original intent had been to harvest the souls shortly after whatever mechanism inside killed them. It was horrifying, but in a much more industrial way than things had been horrifying up to this particular point. I hadn’t seen the worst of the hells though, never got near one of the large-scale farms where people were stapled to trees or had their skin endlessly stripped from their bodies. The infernals had died without me seeing all that many of them, so I was spared the worst of it. And before that had been Fel Seed …

“Debrief or decompress?” Amaryllis asked me.

I looked at the women next to her, who were checking me over and putting a robe on me. I hadn’t recognized it right away, but they were both Dorises. They didn’t look how I thought of Dorises as looking. They didn’t have weariness lining their faces or the same signs of embedded despair. They were clean, put together, and well-fed.

“Are you debriefing me, or am I debriefing you?” I asked after a bit.

“I’d be giving you a debrief,” said Amaryllis. “I have to warn you, it would be dilated and inside Bethel.”

“Fenn,” I said. “I need to talk to Fenn, we did in the hells, but it wasn’t enough time with her. Amaryllis, you brought her back, it’s — I didn’t think it was possible.”

Amaryllis nodded. “It wasn’t. I’ll give the two of you time together, in Bethel, maximum dilation, like we did with Fel Seed. A few days in a few minutes.”

“Fel Seed wasn’t that long ago for me,” I said.

“Sixty-three hours,” said Amaryllis. “That’s approximately how long it’s been since we lost rune magic.”

“Understood,” I said. “Send me in whenever you’re ready then.”

“Close your eyes for three seconds?” she asked.

I did. No game menu appeared. “Nothing. Magic is back though.”

“I know,” said Amaryllis. “I feel it too, which means that Symbiosis is back.” She nodded to the Dorises. “We’re checking you over,” said Amaryllis. She had her arms folded and was watching me.

“Alright,” I said.

“Your body in the Omega Hell was altered,” she said. “The hells, by their nature, alter people. This isn’t the same body you used to have. Let me know right away if anything feels wrong to you, either mentally or physically.”

“Pain modifications got undone,” I said.

“Anything else?” asked Amaryllis.

“I’ll take a look,” I said. “I would guess you’re ready to put me down?”

Amaryllis nodded.

I did the check, as requested. Everything was where I left it, minus the pain modifications. The hack that I’d imported to get the Outer Reaches to stick was still there, as was the other hack to make sure I didn’t go crazy with the rush of leveling up, and I had my meme protections as well. I reported that back to Amaryllis, which caused her to let out a bit of tension.

“Good,” she said.

“I don’t suppose I get super regeneration powers, given this is an Omega Hell body?” I asked. “Or resistance to going insane or catatonic from pain?”

“No to the regeneration,” said Amaryllis. “It’s a property of the hell, not your body. The other stuff we haven’t had a chance to test.”

“And won’t, right?” I asked. “Like, we won’t be torturing someone to the point of insanity to see if that still works?”

“No,” said Amaryllis. “It might come up in the wild though, given what we’re about to do.” She hesitated. “Decompress,” she said, nodding to me. “We’re leaving for Fel Seed tomorrow at the latest.”

“I just got done with Fel Seed,” I said.

“We lost the first round, and we’ll win the second,” said Amaryllis. “We have the teleportation key, the place we’re going is a part of our worldlines, we can wardproof past wards if necessary, it’s — something that can be saved for when we’re under dilation.” Maybe she saw the look on my face.

“I’m ready,” I said, nodding.

“It’ll be inside Bethel,” said Amaryllis. “Is that okay?”

“Yeah,” I said, swallowing the part of myself that felt uncomfortable with it. It was the second time she’d mentioned it. A few days ago, I might have objected, because it was different, using Bethel as a source of comfort and relaxation. Time was tight though, I could tell that.

Without so much as a goodbye, I was standing in a nicely furnished room. The legs of the two couches were black maple, with a brown studded leather on top. Between them was a coffee table of a similar design, one that was nearly overflowing with different kinds of food and drink. Beyond this prepared area, there were other features that I didn’t quite understand, because it seemed like they couldn’t be real. There was a balcony with open doors, its curtains billowing in a faint wind. It was an ocean scene, with birds in the distance, their calls faint. Doors led to the left and right, into unknown places. Fenn was already sitting on one of the couches, dressed in some of her old clothes, khaki short shorts and a tank top. She was smiling at me.

“It’s a real trip, huh?” she asked.

“You’ve already spent some time dilated,” I said, looking her over.

“A’yup,” said Fenn. “Re-integration, Mary called it. Lots of creature comforts, a few movies, some snuggling, it was … you know. It didn’t make up for being killed, nor for having to kill myself a half dozen times, or all the bullshit in the hells, but it was nice.”

“Are you,” I paused. “Are you coming with us to Fel Seed?”

“Jesus,” she said. “You get done with all of that, the fucking Doom Sun, and you want to throw yourself right at the guy who literally killed you?”

“Want to, no,” I said. “Have to, yes. It’s the fate of the world. There’s a chance that we’ll be allowed to win. Or if not strictly allowed to win, then maybe he won’t cheat this time. Or won’t cheat as much.”

She shook her head. “Mary was talking to me about it. Grak too.” She looked at me. “But you know, that’s not really what we’re here for. You and me, we’re here to chill out, relax, maybe watch a movie or two, get in some reading time, just … decompress. And hey, I’m back, right? Which you’re still happy about?”

“Right,” I said. “I didn’t mean to — it means the world to me that you’re back, but the mission is just … all-consuming. I don’t know if Amaryllis told you about what it was like to go into Fel Seed’s domain, what it was like to fight him, but —”

“But maybe if she didn’t, then you shouldn’t either,” said Fenn. Her voice was gentle. “Maybe I don’t need to hear about all that.” She looked me over, searching my face. “You’re different.”

“Hope so,” I said. “The me of a few months ago was a total asshole, and I didn’t like him. In fact, I disavow anything that I said up until, uh, the start of this conversation. So it should be a clean slate.”

Fenn smiled at me. “Fine,” she said. “Amaryllis explained things, by the way. About you and her. How you’re so in love. It does sting, I have to say.”

“Sorry,” I said.

“Don’t be sorry,” she said. “I was dead, I get it. You and Amaryllis … I can’t say that I really get that, but it seems like it was always there, even from the start. You’re too similar, if you ask me. You’ve got that same analytical way of looking at the world. And a kind of … detachment.”

“I guess,” I said. “I’ve never really thought about it like that. There’s a lot to like about her. A lot to admire.”

“Agreed,” shrugged Fenn. “She was always my favorite, no offense.”

“None taken,” I replied. “Shit, I’d be lucky to find myself in the top half of that list.”

“I also have to say,” said Fenn, dragging out the sentence longer than necessary, “I did proposition her.”

“Who?” I asked. “Mary?”

Fenn nodded.

“When you were in the time chamber together?” I asked, frowning. “In the Boundless Pit?”

“Oh, no,” she said. “Like, twelve hours ago.” She was watching me, and I’m sure I looked more bewildered than anything. “In my defense, you were dead and she was a widow, and after the death and mayhem, I felt like I needed a release.”

“Huh,” I said. “And what did she say?”

“Well, it was really more of a, ‘hey, wouldn’t it be funny if we both got naked, I’ve never been with a woman, might be nice to try before I died, just joking, ha ha,’ kind of thing,” said Fenn. “I mean, she knew I wasn’t joking. She brushed me off though, in a very gentle and understanding way.”

“Huh,” I said again. “I didn’t know you were, uh.”

Fenn shrugged. “Any port in a port.”

I stared at her. “Okay, I know you know that’s not the expression, but I don’t —” I paused, trying to collect my thoughts. “In your mind, is it that the phrase ‘any port in a storm’ is so obviously a sexual metaphor, with the ship being a penis and a port being a vagina, and the storm being … horniness, I guess, that when talking about two women, you feel the need to substitute in port? Like … two ports mashing against one another?”

She smiled at me. “Sometimes I just say things without really thinking about them,” she said. “You should try it sometime.”

“You’re in a good mood,” I said, frowning at her.

“I don’t know,” she replied. “Maybe it’s coming back from the dead that’s done it, but I am in a good mood. You know, I can understand why people fake their own deaths and then go listen in on their funerals. When you die, everyone has such a rosy picture of you. It’s been three years, and they’ve forgotten all the annoying shit about me.” She reached forward to the coffee table and began moving things around, finally pulling out a pack of mochi. “You should eat.”

My digestive tract was empty, and my body, to the extent this was my body, was as hollowed out as it could be without me dying. Not wanting to risk it too much, I grabbed a glass of water and started eating some plain crackers, but I was, in fact, hungry, and that progressed to meats, cheeses, fruits, and all kinds of other things, eaten in a very undignified fashion. Fenn watched me until I started to slow down.

“Do you feel differently about me?” asked Fenn.

“Meaning, differently from the way I felt before you died, after I had a few months to reflect?” I asked.

Fenn nodded.

“Yeah,” I said. “Some of that was talking to people about you. I … had a very specific image of you, one that really appealed to me, but it wasn’t what you actually were. I didn’t take your attempts at growth seriously, and I ignored you when you tried to contribute to the group in any other way than being comic relief. That’s my post mortem, if you will.”

Fenn sat back and popped a mochi into her mouth, then chewed on it as she watched me. It wasn’t a small mochi, so this took some time.

“And now, what?” asked Fenn. “You’ve got a better understanding of who I am? You’re a changed man?”

“Eh,” I said. “I’ve been through some stuff, I guess. I don’t want to make promises. I will try though.”

Fenn nodded. “Alright, good enough for me. Let’s go kill Fel Seed then, shall we?”

“I don’t know if you’re joking right now,” I said slowly.

“It’s a joke, because it’s funny,” said Fenn. “But it’s also serious, because yeah, sure, I’ll do it.”

“You don’t have to,” I said. “I mean, everyone that was on the initial team — and I don’t yet know what the redux plan is — we were all there for a reason, either against Fel Seed himself, or for when we got into the Long Stairs.”

“I’m a pretty fucking good archer,” said Fenn. “Surely you haven’t forgotten that?”

“A lot of that was Twinned Soul, no offense,” I said.

“Well, whichever,” said Fenn. “You don’t want the world’s best archer on your team?”

“I do,” I said. “But it’s more because I selfishly wouldn’t want to do it without you than because I think you’ll — and again, no offense — shoot Fel Seed through the heart with an arrow.”

“Hmm,” said Fenn, narrowing her eyes at me.

I sighed. “I mean, I get it, if Twinned Souls is even still there, which it maybe shouldn’t be —”

“It is,” said Fenn. “Mary could feel it. She wants to do some testing, but she thinks that everything except the user interface is still there. She lost Symbiosis while you were gone, but not Twinned Souls, because of some rules lawyer stuff, or maybe the grace of the Dungeon Master.”

“Okay,” I said. “I’m just … what I was saying was, let’s say that you’re William Tell, Legolas, and Hawkeye all rolled into one. Even with your bow in hand, these aren’t the kinds of problems that can be solved with an arrow.”

“William Tell used a crossbow,” said Fenn, folding her arms.

“Uh,” I said. “Okay, sorry?”

“If you’re going to use Earth references, you should at least get them right,” said Fenn. “Last time you mentioned William Tell, I looked him up, and he was a crossbow guy, not a bow and arrow guy. Completely different.”

“I don’t remember ever mentioning him,” I said.

“You told the whole story,” said Fenn. “Someone said William Tell had to shoot an apple off his son’s head, so he pulled out two arrows, except they weren’t arrows, they were bolts, and then he did the shot, perfectly, and the other arrow, except actually a bolt, was revealed to be meant for the guy who told him to take the shot, in case he missed.”

“Well I sure hope I did a better job of telling that story than you just did,” I said, smiling.

Fenn beamed at me. “It was interesting enough for me to go look it up,” she said. “And yeah, crossbow guy, not bow guy.”

“I also kind of misunderstood the Earth stuff,” I said. “I mean, your interest in it. That’s another thing I think I was going to apologize about.”

“Oh, keep them coming,” said Fenn. “I love apologies.”

“You were trying to connect to me,” I said. “And trying to figure out where the elements of elven culture came from. It’s a way of understanding the world. You had your own interests, which were different from mine. I was too self-absorbed to see it, I guess. Worse, I was too self-absorbed when it came to you, specifically. It might have been more forgivable if it was the same level of self-absorption for everyone else.”

“Oh yeah,” said Fenn, laying back with her head resting against the couch. “That’s the stuff. Keep it coming.” She let out a small moan.

“Wow,” I said. “You know, I’m trying to be emotionally mature here, to make amends, and you’re just — making me feel like it’s not actually appreciated.” There was a temptation to laugh with her and blow off all the serious talk. There always had been, with Fenn.

“Sorry,” she said, sitting up. “You know that I’m not good with this kind of stuff, right? Or did you forget?”

“No, I didn’t forget, it’s just hard to remember that it was all only a few days ago for you,” I said. I looked around in the piles of food and finally found something appealing, a small bar of chocolate. For whatever reason, the table had been stacked with a lot of candy.

“I could pretend to be ‘emotionally mature’, if that would help,” said Fenn. She gave me a grin. “‘Sorry, Juniper, that I’m bad with my feelings’,” she was using a silly, mocking voice, “‘I use humor as a coping mechanism, I annoy people so that they’ll push me away which lets me blame them for not taking a joke and protects my fragile ego, I try to defuse things that are serious so that I don’t get hurt, myeh.’”

I gave her a skeptical look.

“See, it’s funny because it’s true,” said Fenn. “But you’re not laughing, which is the sign of a really funny joke.”

“Yeah,” I said, letting out a breath. “Well.”

“Also, that’s as close to an apology as you’re going to get from me, at least for the moment,” she said.

“Ah,” I said. “Because you didn’t want to see me doing the same expression of orgasmic bliss that you were doing to me?”

Fenn snorted and leaned forward, looking for something to eat. “Oh come on, you know what my expression of orgasmic bliss is like.” She looked up. “That’s probably inappropriate, now that you’re married.”

“It is,” I said. Amaryllis wouldn’t mind, but I would mind. Fenn probably would too.

“Damn,” said Fenn, snapping her fingers. “Tell me, is it inappropriate in a good way or a bad way? Be warned that no matter what you say, I’m going to take it the wrong way.”

“Our breakup was … a few days ago for you,” I said. “Something like four, five? Sorry, it was a while ago for me.”

“Longer,” said Fenn. “I’ve been in here, or a place like it, for almost a week. So, call it two weeks total, for me, since the break up. That’s rounding up though.”

“Then I don’t really,” I paused. “I don’t really see what you get out of flirting with me.”

“I like flirting,” Fenn shrugged. “It’s fun. Knowing that you’re married, that you can’t flirt back, that it’s inappropriate — you know, it’s immature, but that does it for me.”

“And if I politely asked you not to?” I asked.

Fenn rolled her eyes. “Valencia talked to me,” she said. “She explained that I would probably feel some lingering attraction to you, and I would need to ‘not fuck you’.”

“Her words?” I asked.

“Approximately,” said Fenn. “She understands me. I mean, even without the devil whispering in her ear, she gets it. I see a bad decision and my brain goes ‘oh my, don’t mind if I do’. There’s this allure to the forbidden. It would all be a lot easier if there were someone to rebound with, but there are not a lot of available men in our group. You should have worked on that while I was gone.”

“Grak?” I asked.

Fenn laughed. “I’d need to be very drunk to fuck Grak.” She leaned forward and lowered her voice. “Did you know he doesn’t even have a penis?”

I didn’t find that particularly funny, but maybe it was because the dwarves were one of the Aerbian species that I was most intimately familiar with. Grak not having a dick was, yes, true, but her saying it out loud felt like it undercut who he was as a person, and the trials that his people had gone through. It was nothing against her, it just didn’t land right for me.

“Tough crowd,” said Fenn. She was watching me and seeing how poorly it had landed with me.

“It was dumb of me to suggest it,” I said. “And I know he doesn’t have the right kind of energy for you.”

“I suppose,” Fenn replied. “I guess it doesn’t matter, if the end is coming. Soon we’ll beat Fel Seed, capture Uther, then you’ll become some kind of god, and you can just whip me up a new boyfriend to help me soothe my woes.” She squinted at me, then waved a hand in my direction. “Someone like you, big and strong, but,” she waved her hand some more, then flicked her fingers at me, like she was casting a spell. “Better.”

“Like me, but better,” I nodded. “Can do. I mean, you could also go for someone who was completely unlike me. I don’t think I’m that great.”

“True,” said Fenn. “But you were a good friend. Are still, I guess, given that you helped pull me out of the hells, though I’m giving Mary most of the credit.” She was looking at me. “You know, I like the muscles, but a part of me misses the horribly plain Juniper, the one I met back in Silmar City. Simpler times.”

“Yeah,” I said. “Not actually that much simpler, but yeah.” My mind went to the horrible pile of undead, as large as a skyscraper, and the fireteam we’d had to kill together.

“So listen,” she said. “This has been … great, I guess, but part of my mission statement here was to make sure that you weren’t suffering from any problems following the whole killing yourself a dozen times thing, or some of the shit in Fel Seed’s zone. So what do you say we clear the table and play some games, or pull out the television, or do something to take our minds off whatever the hell is going on in this great big world that seems to have left both of us a little bit behind.”

“Sure,” I said. “I’d like that.”

I went for the television, the better not to think for a bit. I’d been expecting something like the old setup, the one we’d used back in the time chamber, either the prototype made from Earth scraps or the simpler film projector. Instead, it was something that had clearly been made on Aerb. It was shit, frankly, by the standards of Earth, but by the standards of having been invented three years prior with a bunch of workarounds to make sure that it wouldn’t allow an eldritch entity to mind control people, it was incredibly impressive. It was bulky, a piece of furniture in its own right, but it had a little attachable module that could play cassettes with spooled magnetic tape inside them.

“Mary thought you would get a kick out of this,” said Fenn. “They started pumping out the televisions, but they needed television stations, and shows, so,” she slid in one of the cassettes. “This is the most popular show on Aerb, watched by about twelve percent of the population.”

“The fuck?” I asked. “There are televisions in twelve percent of homes?” Or more than that, because surely not everyone was watching this show. That seemed really high, for only three years having passed.

“You’ll have to ask her about it,” said Fenn. “Shhh, it’s starting.”

The image quality wasn’t great, but again, that was by Earth standards. For Aerb, it was probably impressive as heck. Part of what was probably really impressive was how complete of an experience the whole thing was, polished and iterated over, with all kinds of tricks that had been reworked and refined on Earth over the course of a century. There were production company logos and a fade-to-black as the music began to rise, with a wide establishing shot of some Aerbian city. I didn’t know how long those things had taken to happen on Earth, but here they were, done right away in the first few years of television on Aerb. Everything was in full color, and the audio quality was better than I’d heard on Aerb’s radios or telephones.

The establishing shot gave way to a mid-shot of an apartment building, and that in turn led to a shot of two people sharing breakfast together at a small table in the middle of an apartment. The woman was broshe, tall and elegantly dressed, while I guessed that the man was ha-lunde.

“What is this?” I asked.

Fenn didn’t answer me. She was gazing intently at the screen. It was nice to be with her, but I didn’t know what I was expecting to get out of this. There would be a punchline, I expected.

The idle conversation between the two characters was cut short when someone knocked on the door, and the camera moved and panned, showing only the woman and obscuring what was happening by the door. She looked a little bit bored, but then in the course of words being exchanged at the door, her eyes went wide. There was a sound of a gunshot, then a second as the woman was shot in the chest. The camera held on her as she groaned and bled out. In the distance, footsteps were heard beating a retreat.

“They allow this to be shown on television?” I asked.

“After the kiddos are to bed, yeah,” replied Fenn. “No Hays Code.”

“I didn’t understand that reference,” I admitted.

Fenn shushed me.

“In the criminal justice system of Anglecynn,” said the TV, “The crimes are processed by three separate yet equally important systems: The police, who investigate crime, the judges, who determine guilt, and the exclusions, where trials are held to determine whether the criminal’s life should be spared.”

“Is this fucking Law ampersand Order?” I asked.

“Yeah,” said Fenn. She was still looking at the screen, not at me. “You know, they actually kill the actors for this.”

“What?” I asked.

“Yeah,” she replied. “On Earth they use those little blood bomb things?”

“Squibs,” I said.

Fenn frowned at me. “I thought that was a wizard who couldn’t do magic.”

“It’s both,” I replied.

“You understand I’m going to look this up later?” she asked, poking me in the ribs.

“I do,” I said, squirming.

“But JK Rowling decided on squib, right?” asked Fenn. “Why would she have used that word if it was already a word for something?”

“No idea,” I said. “Maybe she didn’t know.”

“Anyway, we haven’t invented squibs on Aerb,” said Fenn. “In plays and such they use trick costumes or something like that, and make a red silk scarf coming out of someone's vest look close enough that the audience gets it. But for a show like Crime & Exclusion, they just have two revision mages on set, and the actors agree to be temporarily killed until the cameras stop rolling.”

“That’s fucking insane,” I said. “How do you even put in a performance?”

“Practice, I’d guess,” Fenn shrugged. “Though I think usually they try to make sure the deaths are pretty fast, like that one. And it’s not hard to act like you’ve just been shot when you’ve just been shot.”

“Wait,” I said, watching what was happening on screen. “That actress.”

“Yup,” said Fenn, beaming at me. “Our Mary moonlights as an actress.”

We’d been talking over a lot of the show, but apparently this was the part where the main two detectives worked on the case together. Her partner was a guy who had been on-screen for quite a lot of what we’d seen, and they both played kind of similar characters, weary and sardonic. They looked around the crime scene for a bit, talked to some witnesses, then went to track down some leads. Fenn and I talked through a lot of it.

“Nah, I’ve seen six episodes of this now, and it’s pretty critical of the whole thing,” said Fenn. “It’s got our girl’s sense of justice and complexity in it.”

“Cops always get the bad guys though, right?” I asked.

“Nope,” said Fenn. “In one of them, they get the wrong guy. I mean, it’s not stated outright, but the actor did a good job in the exclusion part selling the innocence angle.”

“Eh,” I said. “I still think ‘beautiful detective saves the day’ might be a bit of propaganda. I would maybe call it unintentional, but if Mary is behind it, then it’s got to be on purpose.”

“For sure,” replied Fenn. “It’s our Mary, she’s putting herself front and center on almost half of these shows, and she’s writing almost all of them. A lot of them are cribbed from Earth, but she controls the televisions, the stations, and the companies that are making the content, so of course she’s showing what she wants to her twelve percent. Crime & Exclusion is the best of them though.”

It turned out to be a story of revenge. The guy in the apartment at the start, the one who’d got shot, had fucked a corpse, which his species did to reproduce. It was one he’d been allowed to, as it had been donated, but the guy who’d done the shooting hadn’t understood that, or maybe just couldn’t handle it. The detectives caught him, he had a very brief trial, and then he was sent to an exclusion, which took up the last twenty minutes of runtime. It was less brutal than I’d thought it would be, especially given the violence of the opening, but it was definitely not what I’d have chosen to watch after having gotten out of the hells. With Fenn beside me though, it wasn’t so bad, especially because we were talking over it.

We spent quite a bit of time there, snacking on things, talking over taped television, and just generally taking it easy. I was, unavoidably, getting some details on what had happened on Aerb, but there was nothing that surprised me all that much, not given what I already knew.

“You know, maybe I should have gotten pregnant,” said Fenn.

“You … did?” I asked.

“No, right, I know that,” she gave me a light punch, “But back when we were trying to bring Solace back to life,” she said. “I’d have gotten nine kooshy months in a time chamber, waited on hand and foot.”

“I think you’re looking at those days with glasses that have been not just tinted, but painted over,” I said. “The first few days in the chamber were fine, but it grated on you.”

“True,” she said. “And with Mary, she could at least get along, smooth things over, but you and me, we probably would have had some fights. It’s not the kind of place you’d want to fight, given how you still need to share all your meals together and can’t even go to another room. Lots of sex, especially boredom sex, but also lots of fights. So you’re right, bad idea.”

“But rilirin, right?” I asked. “Nostalgia for a thing that never was and never will be.”

“Yeah,” said Fenn. She sighed. “But hey, once the Fel Seed thing goes flawlessly, and we find Uther, and then dot dot dot, and you become god, you can create an alternate reality where that happened, and make it not suck!”

“I wouldn’t do that,” I said. “I mean, the point of using the time chamber was to bring Solace back, and if I were god, I would just … do that. Just bring her back.”

“Seriously?” asked Fenn. “So you would never create some contrived circumstance that would put us together?”

“No,” I said. “Or … maybe. Between things with Fel Seed, the Dungeon Master, the hells, and before that, Invriezen, and the locus, I’ve been thinking about gods a lot. About how I would do things in an ethical way. I’m thinking of opt-in danger, like there is in video games, some amount of risk and pain for people who want it that way. So maybe, if we both opted into that, then I, as a benevolent god, would have contrived circumstances so that both of us would have been stuck together in such a way that we both had a chance to learn and grow.”

Fenn gave me a poke. “You’re less fun than you used to be.”

“I was never fun,” I replied.

“Yeah, but you were less serious,” said Fenn. “Even now, after a few hours of rest and relaxation, I can feel you vibrating to get back out there. You used to treat actually doing stuff as an unfortunate obligation.”

“It is,” I said. “All this stuff, it still is an unfortunate obligation, one that I would rather not have, one that I would rather someone else do. But it’s my obligation, and if I don’t do it, it’s not going to be done.”

“You’re not worried that it’s all a trick?” asked Fenn. “That you won’t open that door, or find Uther, and there will just be a little note on yellow legal paper saying that your Lost King is in another castle?”

“Sorry, but I don’t really want a lot of reasons not to go back there,” I said. “I don’t want to be convinced. To the extent I have that same driving purpose, I want to keep it, because I’m going to need every ounce of willpower to get through Fel Seed a second time, not to mention traveling up the Long Stairs, however far we have to go.”

“No, you’re right,” said Fenn. “I shouldn’t have said anything.” She turned away a little bit. “I just wish I had my fuck-off buddy back.”

“Have you tried Pallida?” I asked. “She might be available for that. I mean, she’s a thief by trade.”

“Meh,” said Fenn. “New people.” She leaned over and rested her head on my shoulder. We were ostensibly watching a talk show, one hosted by Amaryllis. It was okay, though I understood about zero percent of the monologue. It was weird and unsettling seeing her mug for the camera, but the studio audience seemed to be laughing.

It was nice, being with Fenn, but the more time we spent together, the more I could see all the old cracks in our relationship. Nothing much had changed for her, and even the trip through the hells, tough as it had been for all of us, didn’t seem like it had particularly caused her to reflect and grow. I hadn’t grown, not all that much, but for all that I could see the things that had attracted me to her, it wasn’t as appealing anymore.

When we were in the time chamber together, or the massive dilation that technically didn’t count as a time chamber, Grak gave me a long hug, and I hugged him back, closing my eyes and letting it go on for as long as he needed it, which turned out to be a long time.

“I missed you,” said Grak, pulling away.

“If I can be blunt, it wasn’t enough time for me to miss anyone,” I said.

“I know,” he nodded.

“So,” I said. “What’s new, I guess?”

“Well,” he replied. “The biggest thing to happen in my life is that I died and returned from the hells.”

“Yeah,” I said. “Sorry about that.”

“I volunteered,” he said. “We were not short on volunteers. I could have let someone else go.”

“I know you have a thing about shirking duty,” I said. “You know, you don’t need to go fight Fel Seed with us. I’m giving you an out there. Same goes for the Long Stairs, if we beat Fel Seed and have a chance to go get you.”

“I have a thing about shirking duty,” he replied, smiling at me slightly. “Now, while I have you, there are some Ranks configurations I think you’ll find interesting …”

That was mostly what we did together, maybe because he was following the mandate of getting me mentally and emotionally ready for Fel Seed, or maybe because he felt it was the best way for us to connect. I asked him about his personal life a few times, but was mostly rebuffed. Like the rest of them, he’d been living in the DFEZ, though he often traveled the world for work, which seemed to suit him. He wanted to tell me more about the places he’d been than about himself, it seemed, but traveling the world and seeing more of its enormous variety was important to him.

With his unique abilities, he’d gone into a number of entad exclusion zones and shut them all down, at least as much as possible, finding the entads themselves and then putting wards around them to stop their effects. He didn’t really seem to care that much about it though, nor see it as any great accomplishment, and my guess was that the fact that his abilities were unearned and unfair still weighed down any joy he might have found in his competence and power.

He had friends in Dorisopolis, which had a fairly small contingent of dignitaries, engineers, specialists, and there were regular social events that were largely dominated by Dorises. Hearing about it made me think of a Where’s Waldo book I’d had with a land filled with Waldos and like a dozen random non-Waldos thrown in. He’d also grown close with Raven, though I had trouble imagining what that was like.

It was clear that he’d missed me, and toward the end of our time together, he broached the topic of depression and suicide, which seemed to him like a spectre that would forever haunt him. I had no easy answers there, only empathy and understanding. I hoped that was enough. I broached the topic of pharmaceutical answers, which were beyond the reach of Aerb’s technology but not the backpack Bethel had eaten, and he’d told me that he’d tried one which made him violently ill. I stopped trying to fix things after that, and did my best to make him feel loved, since that was what I had to offer.

“I’m not coming with you,” said Valencia. After a brief hug, it was the first thing she’d said to me. She definitely seemed older, in a way that Amaryllis and Grak mostly hadn’t. Maybe it was that she’d had more maturing to do.

“I understand,” I said.

“Jorge and I got married,” she said. “We have three children.”

“Three?” I asked. “Damn, you must have been busy.”

“It’s been almost five years for me,” said Valencia. “I sleep using the time chamber.” She shrugged. “It’s necessary in order to ensure the infernals don’t know that the attacks are tied to a real person who needs to sleep. It’s been a part of the protocol.”

“Still,” I said. “Children. That’s … unexpected. They, uh, have souls?”

She nodded. “Captain Blue-in-the-Bottle left behind some research data. We discovered that it was possible. Safe, or as safe as having children when magical healing doesn’t work.”

“And I suppose you read them the Harry Potter books every night?” I asked, giving her a smile.

“Only the oldest,” she said. “I hope you don’t mind that I used the name Juniper. It felt more fitting when I thought you were dead.”

“Oh,” I said. “No problem, I guess. For your sake, I hope he’s not like me. I have a feeling I was a bit of a tough kid to raise.”

“She’s a girl, actually,” said Valencia.

“Huh,” I said.

“Ah,” she said. “That you do mind.”

“I’ll get over it,” I said. I had been teased for having a girl’s name a few times, but not enough that I had a complex about it.

“I know you will,” she smiled. “I missed you. We haven’t had enough time together.”

“I feel like you became a different person while I wasn’t looking,” I said. “When we first met —”

“I was abused for almost my entire life,” said Valencia. “You were the first person to treat me like a human, and you were the reason that the tables were turned on the infernals. You allowed me to not just block them from taking control of my body and my words, but to kill them. I know you had nothing to do with it, that it was the machinations of a higher power, but in my mind then, and still a bit now, it was all you.”

“Which wasn’t healthy,” I said. I looked out over the coffee table, which had been restocked when she came in. I was having trouble meeting her eyes.

“A relationship between us might have worked,” said Valencia. “But it wasn’t a good place to be starting from. There was a power imbalance between us, a complex one that went both directions in various ways. It’s hard to fix relationships that have a bad start. Not impossible, but hard. All that applies to being friends as well, but less so.”

“And now?” I asked. “We’re friends, aren’t we?”

“We are,” she said. “Or were. It’s been a long time, for me. When I left with Bethel, it wasn’t just because I thought that’s where I was needed. It was because I knew that I had never made it up to you, what happened with Fenn.”

I frowned at her. “You did,” I said. “I don’t — I expected too much of you, and a lot of my anger was just — you said true things. I was defensive.”

“I know,” said Valencia. “But I was in the wrong, and I needed to square it away with myself before I could feel like I had actually done a good job apologizing.”

“Okay,” I said. “Consider your extended apology happily received.”

She gave me a smile. “I would come with you, to Fel Seed and beyond, if I didn’t have children. Maybe even then, if someone didn’t need to hold down the fort as far as the hells go. But as it stands, this is probably the last time we’ll see each other, until and unless you come out the other side.”

“Thank you all the same,” I said. “How is it, being a mother?”

“Good,” she replied. “Better than expected. I’m privileged in a way that nearly no one else in the world is. Bethel has been a good home to us. She watches the children, cooks us meals, makes sure that everyone is safe and happy. We’ve given each other what we both wanted.”

“Ah,” I said. “It’s still … there’s a part of me that flinches from her. Once bitten, twice shy.”

“I know,” said Valencia. “I think you’re right though, that you’re under no obligation to like her, or to be her friend. She’ll help you through what remains, to the extent she can, and then part ways forever.”

“Is she going to be a problem, when it comes to Uther?” I asked.

“I don’t know,” said Valencia. “She’s broken out of her own cycles of hatred. It’s still a reflex within her, but she’s gone years without hurting anyone. If I could come with, I would be able to make sure that she stayed the course, but the thought of leaving my children without a mother terrifies me down to my core. I never had a mother. They’d have a father, a good one, but … there are also the hells to consider, which make me feel like I’m not being selfish. I don’t even know if I would be able to act against them in the Long Stairs. I’ll stay here, with them. We’re already losing our house for an unknown period of time.” She gave me a but-what-are-you-going-to-do-about-it smile.

“I’ll try to be understanding with her,” I said. “I’ll … do my best.”

“I know,” nodded Valencia. She looked over the coffee table. “Now, did you know that I ran a candy store? There are a few creations I want you to try.”

“Okay,” said Amaryllis, once Valencia left the time dilated apartment. “Are you ready for a debrief on the last three years and a mission overview for what comes next, or do you need time with me?”

“I need time with you,” I said. “But … you can do a soft debrief.”

Amaryllis nodded. She didn’t look like she’d aged at all, despite the three years, which, with her clones, should have been something like ninety subjective years. That wasn’t counting time in the time chambers either, which I was sure she would have used.

“Wait,” I said, before she could start. “Are we still — I mean, I was dead, but are we still … married?”

“Are you asking if I still love you?” asked Amaryllis.

I gave her a sheepish nod.

“I still love you,” she said. Her voice was soft. She was sitting across from me, on a couch, with papers neatly laid out in front of her. “There have been other potential suitors, some of them appealing, and offers of strategic partnership, but I turned them all down.”

“Oh,” I said. “I’d have understood if, uh.” I paused. “If you’d had the need for affection, or intimacy, or even just needed a marriage to get things done.”

“I know,” said Amaryllis. “If it had been necessary, I might have, but I was able to do without. I always knew you were coming back.”

“You did?” I asked.

“You’d call it an article of faith,” said Amaryllis. “It took a long time to get anyone else on my side.”

“I can understand that,” I said. “In terms of debriefing me, can we start with what the world thinks happened to me? I assume my ignominious defeat at the hands of Fel Seed wasn’t made public knowledge?”

“We made the strategic decision to reveal the existence of the Other Side,” said Amaryllis. “According to public reports, you’ve been there, fighting the Union Empire. Figaro Finch has been helping us keep the truth from getting out.”

“Okay,” I said. “I’m not ready to go on your talkshow just yet. You’ll need to give me more information if you need me to lie to anyone.”

“I have a script prepared,” said Amaryllis. “But it’s moot, because we’re not going to do that unless the rest of our plans go horribly wrong. I’m a bit worried about the Other Side actually, because it does seem like there’s some amount of unrest within the Union Empire, to the extent we’re able to get any intelligence out, and that instability might mean that there are plot elements happening there, but at this point we simply don’t have time.”

“I’m sorry you had to go through this alone,” I said. “Or, not alone, but without me.”

Amaryllis had been looking down at her papers, then looked back up at me. “Thank you,” she said. She looked at the papers, then set them down and got up from her couch. With quiet footsteps, she came over to my side, wrapping her arms around me as she sat down. She buried her face in my shoulder and kissed my neck. For a moment she just sat there, holding me and breathing me in. “I missed you, Juniper.”

I rubbed her back for a bit, and then she moved us so that we were laying together, with her on top of me, her face pressed against my chest. I didn’t really know what all she’d been through in the past three years, but it had probably been hard. She’d had the rest of the team, and the clones, but it wouldn’t have been even remotely the same, just because of the personalities involved. She’d gotten along best with Raven, but their differences in values would have undoubtedly caused friction at certain points. And from what Fenn had said, Amaryllis had been diminished, losing the power of Symbiosis and all her magics along with it.

“Okay,” she said, after ten or fifteen minutes had passed. She pushed off me, then leaned down and gave me a long, slow kiss. “Fuck I’ve missed you.”

“Sorry I died,” I said.

“It was necessary,” she said. “Cold and cruel, but a necessary part of the plan.”

“The … plan?” I asked, suddenly alarmed.

“The Dungeon Master’s plan,” she said. I relaxed. “You needed to die so that we could follow the pattern, the second time he can give us a fair fight, which we should win. You always talked about the do-over, the new campaign you were making that would correct for the problems of the past. That’s what this is.”

“It is?” I asked.

She nodded.

“I actually talked with him,” I said. “After I died. When I was in hell.”

Amaryllis stared at me. “And what did he say?” she asked. There was something about the way she said that, a kind of breathlessness, that made me uncomfortable.

“He copped to being Vervain, said that he hated me, explained some of what he did with Arthur, uh, told me Fel Seed’s weakness was that Fel Seed wasn’t actually the Dungeon Master,” I paused. “I can see in your eyes that you’re going to ask me a lot of questions about the precise words, but this was three days ago, and I frankly went through a lot after that, so you’ll forgive me if I’m just giving you the gist of things.”

“It’s vitally important,” said Amaryllis. “I’m sorry Juniper, I know you hate it, but if there’s some hint, some clue, then we need to know it.”

“We’re going to Fel Seed anyway,” I said. “We’re going to try to defeat him a second time, because we really have no choice in the matter anymore. If we had some kind of clever plan against the Void Beast, or against the hells, maybe I would say that we stay and fight, but it seems like we don’t. I can see the necessity of getting eyes on every word the Dungeon Master said, but I would rather just charge into the fight again.”

“Okay,” said Amaryllis, relaxing.

“Okay?” I asked. “That’s not like you.”

“We’re following the will of the Dungeon Master,” she said. “We need to do our due diligence, but I’ll let you go over his words on your own, if that’s what you prefer. I trust you.”

“Really?” I asked. “Seriously?”

“I’ve come to accept that the Dungeon Master doesn’t speak to me,” said Amaryllis. “To the extent anything was designed for me, it was always subordinate to the things that were about you.”

“Ah,” I said. “That sounds … kind of grim.”

“It’s reality,” she replied. She got up off of me and went back to her own couch, taking a moment to compose herself. “Are you ready for the proper debrief?”

I nodded, and Amaryllis gave me the bullet points of the last three years.

With me gone, the Council of Arches had lost a seat. That wouldn’t have been a problem, because quorum was defined as four of the seven seats, but there was a challenge from some of the tuung on account of several of those members being ‘straw’ advisors, under the control of Amaryllis but not actually involved in governance. There could have been an argument, or a political fight, but Amaryllis gracefully allowed the Council to dissolve, at least as an official government body. That left the first and second generation to self-governance, which brought with it a fracturing of their society into a number of different factions, at least partly along generational lines. The tuung loyalists were still loyal to Amaryllis, the tuung nationalists were loyal to their Republic, and the tuung traditionalists were more interested in going back to the traditional ways of their people, albeit with some level of synthesis with the culture Amaryllis had created. This was not, by any means, an equal split, with the traditionalists being a small but vocal minority. I had some questions about the tuung that I’d known, either the ones I’d talked with on security detail, or those that I’d sat with in committee sessions, and Amaryllis gave me brief one line descriptions of the trajectories of their lives.

The Void Beast had altered its velocity, or had its velocity altered, and it still wasn’t known what had caused it. If you graphed it though, you could see a sharp upward inflection which started with an explosion at a void factory, but couldn’t be accounted for with just that. The common theory was that it was another death cult like the one in Li’o, though how they’d gotten their hands on enough void crystals to make an appreciable change in trajectory was a mystery. In theory, it was possible to set up banks of thousands of void rifles firing every six seconds for as long as they had power, but only a death cult would do that. It was also possible that some state actor had done it, for whatever reason, or some non-state actor following incentives, but it was very difficult to know for sure.

The Republic of Miunun had become a part of the Empire of Common Cause, though it was a bit of a contentious issue for both Miunun and the Empire. The industrial might of the small nation was undeniable, as was the educated workforce and technological prowess. The omnidevice they’d been producing hundreds of millions of seemed likely to be in every home in the near future, and the massive factory and supply lines couldn’t be beat by anyone, especially since so much of it had been done with entad assistance. It wasn’t just a television, it was a (better) radio and VCR too, which meant that anyone with disposable income would be clamoring for it. Amaryllis had no official government position within the Republic, but she commanded loyalty, and had personally founded and funded almost every major company, often acting, with her clones, as the entirety of upper management.

The Dorises had gotten their collective act together. There were, apparently, a few factors involved in that, but the biggest thing that had happened was that resource scarcity had been virtually eliminated. Grak could, apparently, set up a ward that would prevent duplication of a Doris, but not her things, and these had been set up in public places all around the zone, enough so that a Doris could duplicate her possessions once or twice a day. Entad duplicates had also been flooded into the city, supplied through BGD-sponsored clades, borrowed from the stash that Amaryllis had accumulated. Resource scarcity had been virtually eliminated over the course of a year, and cleanup efforts had been followed by new buildings. It was enough to create a slowly expanding zone of lawfulness and charity around the initial site where BGD had been found. One of the biggest changes, at least according to Amaryllis, was a change in the culture of the zone, and the understanding that all this largess ultimately came from one of their own. A combination of extraordinarily improved conditions and the idea among Dorises that they were capable of being not completely shit had led the Empire to reclassify the zone from major exclusion to minor exclusion. A second reclassification to ‘free’ exclusion was on the horizon.

The locus was healthy and expanding, and most of the tuung nationalists still lived on the Isle of Poran, which had quadrupled in size thanks to whatever the locus was doing. There was a thriving colony of druids there, mostly doing jack squat, and tight controls on who went in or out, because the place would have been mobbed in a heartbeat if anyone had let it. Amaryllis said, in a low voice, that there had been a sighting of a second locus, far away from the Six-Eyed Doe, one shaped like a wide white toad with a garden on his back. Information was, at the moment, sparse, and inspecting a locus too closely was a bad idea.

“Do you think it’s,” I said. “I mean.”

“Yes,” said Amaryllis. “I do. There’s no proof one way or another. It’s possible it’s not even connected to the doe, or not a locus. I saw it with my own eyes, then left.”

“And what, uh,” I said. “What would be my ... responsibilities?”

“Unclear,” replied Amaryllis.

“Okay then,” I said.

Amaryllis had, in fact, gone to the Outer Reaches and become a conceptual version of herself, as her great-great-great-great-great-great-great-great-grandfather had done before her.

“It was difficult,” she said. “Probably the most difficult thing I did in the entire time that you were dead. Getting there was easy, Raven found a way, but being there was like trying to drive straight while completely drunk. I could see when I was going the wrong way, but when I tried to correct, I would overcorrect and end up swerving all over the place. The Court is mercurial, not even really fitting of the name court, it’s just people as ideas, holding ideas, using them, sharing them, altering them, being them. I took on the Mantle of Princess — imagine everything in all capital letters, all the time — and the Mantle of Assassin, a combination that hadn’t been seen in thousands of years. I could barely remember what I was there for. It was so easy to get sucked into the games they played. Death and Hero were in personal union, I think because you were dead, but I never got a straight answer from anyone.”

“Sounds confusing,” I said.

“I enjoyed it, at the time,” said Amaryllis. “Enjoyed it a bit too much, to be honest. I killed the Queen and took her Mantle, and looking back there was no real reason for it. I was prideful, I think, maybe because of the Princess Mantle, or the Assassin one. I — my conceptual self — was there for an entire year. I almost missed the window for bringing you back.”

“But you did come back,” I said. “And you managed to insert a way out of the hells.”

“I did,” nodded Amaryllis. “You know, the whole time I was in p-space, I was thinking that it was the kind of thing we should have been doing together. It was the kind of thing we could have been doing together. I don’t know why it didn’t occur to us to do all this once Fenn died.”

“It didn’t seem possible, I guess,” I said.

“You would have been better at the insertion than I was,” said Amaryllis. “I kept trying to build a way out of the hells, to retroactively construct … something, anything, that would get you back. We didn’t have your soul, we didn’t know whether you were alive or dead, we didn’t even know if you were maybe in the hells and we’d just missed you, somehow.”

“And so you built this enormous thing,” I said. “Something that runs on suffering, something that the infernals could plausibly have built and then never used, with high costs on both ends.”

“It was as good as I could do,” said Amaryllis.

“I know,” I said. “I mean, I figured you didn’t just do it that way for kicks.”

Amaryllis nodded. “In a way, it was, though. There was a part of me that was trying to create something beautiful, something inspiring, poignant. But in the end, I managed it, to make something that could do the impossible. And even then, I had to betray people who were — not friends, not in p-space, but who were aligned, which maybe meant something more. If I’d just been able to keep my head straight, I would have been able to do something better, but I was in this fog of clever ideas, of roles and narratives and … it didn’t feel right to make a portal to the surface without suffering and death. I tried other things, too, but the portal left me diminished, and I was worried if I stayed too long, I would never come out.”

“You did more than anyone could have expected,” I said. “Whatever went on there.”

“The clones had to fend for themselves,” said Amaryllis. “They couldn’t sync. We did, once I was back, but there was some divergence, some sense of … differentiation.”

“And you’re okay?” I asked.

“There were three of the thirty that didn’t want to merge,” said Amaryllis.

“Ah,” I said. “And … did they, eventually?”

She nodded. “Two of them were,” she let out a breath. “Lovers. It was utter narcissism.” She blushed slightly at the memory, then paled. The muscle in her cheek went taut. “I didn’t manage to convince them. They didn’t think that I would have the same love for myself as they had for each other. They argued that they could be just as effective without merging. I just merged them anyway.”

“Ah,” I said. It sounded suspiciously like murder, or at least forcibly changing another person’s mind. I couldn’t judge though, not with three years gone. “And … you’re okay?”

She reached over and threaded her fingers through mine. “The world is coming to an end, but for the first time, I feel like we’re back on track.”

The party had stayed together, which had apparently not been a given once the disastrous attempt at Fel Seed had been made. Pallida had fucked off for most of the time I’d been gone, rejoining the crew only within the last few months, and then only because Amaryllis had put in the time and effort to retrieve Pallida’s favorite hat from the Bryllyg Sea. Raven had gone back to the Library, but only temporarily, and mostly to make amends and ensure that everyone was working on the same side. The end of the world was on the horizon, and seemed unavoidable, at least based on the information they had.

Grak had never left the group, nor threatened to, but he’d had a number of relationships in that time, most of them flings, some of them serious, and Amaryllis had been mildly worried that he would settle down, leaving her without the most powerful warder in the world. I got a lot more from Amaryllis than I’d gotten from Grak, at least about the relationships.

Bethel had been brought back into the fold. She was done with being a place for colonies of tuung, done with being a mobile defense platform, and for the most part, done being of any particular use to anyone, except as the best house she could be. The one exception to that was a promise, one made shortly after the whole Fel Seed thing had gone sideways, extracted by Amaryllis in what was apparently a heated exchange. Bethel was going to help with a second shot at Fel Seed, and the Long Stairs. She felt she owed it to us, and she had unfinished business with Uther, though to hear Amaryllis tell it, that was more about closure.

And Valencia? She had the three children, of course. She had been a friend to Amaryllis and the others, but not as much of a partner. She wasn’t coming with us to go against Fel Seed, not when she was so much more vulnerable than we were, and not when she had a family. It was, clearly, not what Amaryllis wanted, but it did mean that Valencia would be on hand to counteract whatever the infernals were doing. She would also be there remotely, watching in and able to speak through Bethel and a variety of different entads, but it wasn’t clear whether that would work in the Long Stairs. It was odd, how differently Amaryllis spoke about Valencia compared to how Valencia talked about herself.

“She’s changed the most,” said Amaryllis. “She’s stable. Happy. Not all that interested in adventuring, or statecraft, or, really, any of the mountain of work she’s most suited to help with. Bethel is mostly her house.”

“You were trying to keep everything together,” I said.

“Maybe it would have been possible, if I’d done things differently,” said Amaryllis. She let out a long, low sigh. “I think that’s everything you’d care about, and most of what you’d need to know.”

“The rune magic exclusion?” I asked.

“Very recent,” she said. “I tried other methods, and nothing worked. It’s arguably the worst exclusion in Aerb’s history, and I was almost solely responsible. And now we have very little time.”

“Because of the souls piling up in the hells?” I asked.

“It’s already weighing on me,” said Amaryllis. “And if the guilt and doubt weren’t enough, there’s some chance they find out that it was me. I could be arrested.”

“You’ve been a fugitive from the law before,” I said, frowning. “I mean, I understand what you’re saying, the gravity of spiking souls not working anymore, but … being arrested, or having to avoid it, I’m missing what’s clearly an emotional component.” I’d come to that realization as I was talking to her.

“Three years ago it would just have been about the loss of resources,” said Amaryllis. “Now? I’ve built up so much. I’m famous. Actually, so famous that it’s almost a problem sometimes. We’re at twenty percent saturation on the omni, but the reach is far larger than that. I have power, influence, and — I’m using it to do real good.” She looked me in the eye. “I thought about not going for you.”

“Yeah?” I asked.

“The three year window was closing,” she said. “I could extend the window for Fenn, there are half a dozen ways to do that, but we didn’t have you, and it was only a guess that you’d been bottled. Maybe the three year time limit was only imagined, if you were still alive, being endlessly tortured by Fel Seed. We didn’t know. We still don’t know, actually, what the fuck Fel Seed had done with you. A part of me was having a crisis of faith, wanting to call it all off, to forge a world without you, or at least put it off and hope that we could still execute the plan at a later date. It was attachment speaking, I think, a base desire for the wealth, accomplishment, accolades, and power I’d won. I loved you, I do love you, but I knew that no matter what happened, when I went ahead with the rescue attempt, everything else would irrecoverably shatter.”

“And it did,” I nodded. “Just worse than you thought.”

“No,” said Amaryllis, shaking her head. “Not worse than that worst case. I thought that one of us wouldn’t make it back from the hells. I thought maybe it would just be you back in the world, at the expense of everyone and everything else.”

“Oh,” I said. “That’s … a huge risk to take.” I did wonder why she’d chosen to go, when she could have sent someone else, but I was worried about the answer she’d give me. It smelled like narrative thinking.

“It was a risk,” said Amaryllis. “Infernal unification was a bigger risk. If things had gone perfectly, we might have been able to extract you without them noticing. Now … we tried to keep it contained, and we tried to make sure there were decoys, but they have their own investigative teams. They’ve been working on the project for three years now, adapting to this extreme asymmetric warfare, and we’ve tipped our hand, at least in part. There’s a good chance they’ll know we can read the minds of the dead. Val can kill them, but we need to know where they are first, and the hells are just too big, with too many infernals, too many teams working in cells, and too much of a risk that they’ll breach into Aerb and make a beachhead here we won’t know about until it’s too late.” She shook her head. “It doesn’t matter. None of it matters. We just need to get you to the Long Stairs.”

“I know,” I said.

Amaryllis let out a breath. “I was hoping you would say that. Come on. We have planning to do.”

More Dakka

The second time was a lot different from the first. For one thing, we weren’t flying in, we were teleporting in. For another, we had more experience after that first round, and three additional years of planning. And this time, there was a chance that the Dungeon Master would elect not to totally fuck us.

The one drawback, aside from trying to fight fucking Fel Seed, was that we’d lost a fair number of entads. Everything I’d been wearing was gone, left in the FSEZ and then presumably completely annihilated. I counted us lucky, very lucky that Amaryllis hadn’t lost all her inherited entads when she’d died, since there was no known precedent for what happened when you brought someone back from the dead. There was some kind of entad magic which tracked inheritance, and I wouldn’t have blamed it for saying ‘hey, I only recalculate when someone dies or is born, you’re shit out of luck’. Amaryllis had been confident that she’d get them back, but looking at the same data she’d had access to, I felt like at least some of that confidence was coming from her particular brand of faith.

We arrived with Bethel acting as the teleportation key, taking five of us, minus Amaryllis, who arrived a split second later: there was an entad statue, inherited from Rosemallow, that she could teleport to, and it was inside Bethel. We were at maximum dilation, only for long enough that we could get some sense of what conditions were like given the extremely large explosion three days prior. It was an enormous crater, completely devoid of life or features, with only three exceptions. The first exception was the door, which was as perfectly intact as ever, untouched by the explosion. The second was a bone-white platform that had been built up from the bottom of the crater, forming a platform some fifty feet around the door. And the third was Fel Seed, standing in front of the door with his hands folded on top of the hilt of the vorpal blade, which was stuck in the ground. There was plenty of room to fight, but unlike the previous throne room, it felt relatively barren.

“It’s extremely rare for someone to escape me,” said Fel Seed as soon as Bethel spit us out. “I allow it, at times, mostly for sport, and especially for the fanatics that come to me. I arm them, equip them, give them instructions, then send them out past the various guards and defenses at the border so that they might work my will by proxy. But even beyond those, there have been some who have escaped. Three, I believe. They come to the borders, dressed in wards, and flee like little mice at a moment’s notice. This too, I allow. It makes others braver and bolder, and them I kill.”

“You allowed us to escape,” I said. “Magnanimous of you.” I was willing to put up with the monologuing. With a stage prepared like this, it wasn’t like he was buying time, and there was a chance that he’d reveal something critical.

“No, it was that god you brought with,” said Fel Seed. “I don’t see her about.” He craned his neck around, like he could possibly have missed a giant six-eyed doe. I had talked to the locus before we’d come, as one of the only things I had done outside of extreme time dilation, but naturally, I hadn’t gotten a response to any of my questions, nor a commitment that she would be there for the fight.

Fel Seed glared at me. “I seem to recall you being here, before the unceremonious explosion of my city. You were in a sorry state.”

“I got better,” I said. He knew the answer about what had happened to me over those three years, whether I’d been tortured and had the memories erased by a merciful Dungeon Master, or been bottled in a plan to send me to oblivion, or something else, but I really didn’t give a shit.

“I’ve never seen someone die twice,” said Fel Seed. “I’m always forced to bring people to the mere brink of death, as close as I can without killing them, which as it turns out, is quite close. If I take you apart, will I find out how you returned?”

“No,” I said. I was gripping my sword. It was better to let him talk, but it was trying my patience.

“The deal still stands,” said Fel Seed. “If you give me all of them, you’re allowed through this door.” His eyes settled on Fenn. “And a new one too.”

“We were planning to just kill you instead,” said Amaryllis.

“That didn’t work out so well for you last time, did it?” asked Fel Seed. “I wonder what you think has changed.” He had the vorpal blade in front of him. Its tip was embedded in the bone surface, and his fingers danced on the hilt, threatening to pick it up at any moment. The door was behind him.

“Things have been going badly for the outside world,” said Fel Seed. “I should have thought that would take some heat from me. Am I really so important?”

“No,” I said. “You’re not. You’re just in the way.”

I gave Fenn the signal. She drew in an instant and loosed an arrow, which zipped through the air at impossible speeds, cracking the sound barrier from the sounds of it. Putting that much power into an arrow should have snapped the bow and ripped off her arm, but she was completely fine. Fel Seed’s head exploded where the arrow struck, more from the shockwave than the arrow itself, and he slumped slightly before starting to regrow. She fired more arrows, and they left her bow one after the other, just slightly slower than a machine gun. Still, he regrew, but I gave it a bit.

“Fine, it’s not working,” said Fenn in disgust. We’d let her try, because it was entirely possible that it might have worked, as the funny kind of joke that the Dungeon Master seemed fond of.

We attacked, coordinated, blasting him with everything we had. His body ripped apart and reformed, burnt and regrew, and through it all he stood there, smiling at us, even as his lips and teeth were being ripped off and broken. Eventually, when it became clear that nothing was working, nothing would be allowed to work, we stopped.

I was getting nervous. The Dungeon Master hadn’t said that he’d make the second fight fair, nor had he said that I would win, or that it would be possible for me to win. It was entirely possible that he was, true to his word, actually gone, letting all this play out as a coda. I wouldn’t put it past him.

“Oh, are we starting?” he asked. He lifted the vorpal blade from the ground and spun it around, then looked over our group, contemplating us.

He went after Raven first, leaping through the air, and I used one of our secret weapons, tapping a bone. It wasn’t just any bone though, it was one that I was touching through a star magic construct that had been specially built for exactly that purpose at great expense.

The bone belonged to Mome Rath.

It was an exhilarating rush of strength and speed, and I moved considerably faster than the wind, sending my sword screaming through the air so fast I was worried it would snap or tear apart. The blade tore through him like butter, with the shockwave destroying more of his flesh.

Raven’s attack came right after mine, and she cut through him with her blade of stopped time, down through his head, the speed and force of it vaporizing everything there.

He reformed, of course he did, but it seemed slower, and in the meantime, the doorbreak team of Bethel, Grak, and Pallida had moved to the door. It was hard not to notice that the door itself was completely intact, even after being hit with the equivalent of a nuclear blast.

Raven and I kept up the assault as the Mome Rath bone burned down, each slice bringing him down into smaller and more spread out chunks. This was just the avatar, but at the same time, the nigh-infinite power we were using was from Mome Rath. There was a chance that channeling the power of someone at his level would be enough, conceptually if not logically.

Eventually, the bone burned down, and I began burning a unicorn bone, hoping to give us more time at the door. We didn’t need to beat Fel Seed, we just needed to get through to the Long Stairs and leave him behind. I called out the loop number to the doorbreak team, amplifying my voice, so they could try different pre-arranged tactics. The password was going to be the sticking point, but it wasn’t clear that Bethel doing a dictionary attack would work, because different kinds of magic had different requirements, and not all of them would allow the words of an entad to count. There might also be a rate limit to password ‘attempts’, or any other kind of security feature, we just didn’t know, and the last time we’d been there, Grak hadn’t been able to gather enough information to say for sure what the constraints were.

When Fel Seed regrew, he grew back as multiple bodies, each of them having regenerated from a different part of him. It seemed like a cheat, as there was no way to have done that with just biomanipulation, not with how much mass seemed to have come from nowhere, but I supposed it was technically possible if pulling from the bone below us. The copies meant that it would be harder to protect against his attacks.

He avoided me and Raven, maybe because he knew there was a second Mome Rath bone for me to burn, and attacked Amaryllis and Fenn instead. Fenn shot an arrow at a whip of flesh that came her way, and her arrow sliced through, causing it to thump to the ground instead of touching her. She was firing her arrows at full speed, one after the other, seeming never to pause in her motion, and it might have been a thing of beauty if I weren’t so worried that she was going to die. Mixed in with the arrows was some of her magic, though Fenn hadn’t had as much time to train in everything new as we might have liked. Her archery was augmented by magic, and her quiver would never empty, but she was just barely keeping up on defense, and I could see a swirl of passion magic around her, fear driving up the speed of her motion to a blur I could barely follow.

Amaryllis was faring worse, perhaps because she was getting the brunt of the attacks. She had the same wide variety of magic, but in most cases it just wasn’t strong enough, or only strong enough to let her narrowly escape. The vorpal blade flung through the air and sliced her personal wards apart. She took hard hits, one of them nearly sending her off the platform before she could use still magic, but she soldiered on, even after a second hit blasted away part of her armor and took a chunk from her arm. Open flesh, exposed to the air — I was worried that Fel Seed was going to infect her, that we’d get the door open and be forced to leave her behind.

Pallida was the first casualty. She’d been frantically working at the lock, trying to figure out something, and I had been too busy trying to protect Amaryllis and Fenn to realize that she was a target. The vorpal blade casually cut her wards, then a fist from Fel Seed caught her squarely in the back of her head and continued on, crunching it directly against the door. Bethel shot at Fel Seed, hitting him with a supercharged cannonball that blasted flesh apart, then picked up Pallida, tucking her into extradimensional space, where I hoped she would live.

I was worried we would be picked off one by one. I was worried that in the end, if I really was the Chosen One, if any of that still applied, it would be just me going down the Long Stairs. I didn’t want to face it alone. It didn’t seem right or fair.

I went for Fel Seed’s sword, the vorpal blade. I had used it last time, in the first round, but I had only given it a part of myself. That had been in the FSP, a part of protocol I was following, but the revised version called for it to be used in full, with all of my life force behind a singular hit. There was a good chance that it would kill me.

He had been using it to break wards, but he’d only used it for direct attacks a few times, and we’d been able to block or dodge. Amaryllis had tried to parry it, and the vorpal blade had sliced straight through her entad sword and then would have taken her life, if not for a short range teleport at the last moment.

Fenn saw what I was doing and fired off an arrow, severing the arm Fel Seed had been holding the vorpal blade with. As I dashed forward and reached for the sword, Fel Seed snatched it away, firing one of his tentacle hands to grab it before I could pick it up. Raven went forward to cut off his hand, but he parried her slice of frozen time with the vorpal blade, broke her wards with a follow-up attack, then hit her in the stomach with a fist, hard enough that I could see the sizable dent in her banded armor. She went sailing off away, slowed by her magical cloak and otherwise limp.

“Bethel!” I shouted. “Grab the blade.”

Bethel moved away from the door in a flash of lightning, appearing next to Fel Seed before the afterglow had faded from my eyes. She tried what she’d done before, wrapping herself around the blade, not to eat it, but to send it to me. Fel Seed could move at arbitrary speeds if he wanted to, and in this case it was apparently important to him. He formed a hand of jagged bone and made a grab for her, and she flew backward, dodging away before taking another jabbing run at the vorpal blade. This time he struck her with the blade, cleaving halfway into her, trumping her inviolability with, I was assuming, bullshit.

“Copy!” I shouted, and held out my hand. Bethel flew to it, forming a sword even as she healed through the cut.

In addition to the Mome Rath bones, we had another thing we hadn’t had in the last fight: after much trial and tribulation, Amaryllis had been able to acquire Onion’s sword, the one which could copy the abilities of any other sword.

I burned the second Mome Rath bone as she assumed the power of the vorpal blade, which was stacked with as many other powers as she had, adding speed, power, sharpness, and raw momentum. Time slowed down as I wound up for a giant swing. Fel Seed’s corporeal body didn’t actually matter, save for the fact that he could kill us using it, but it was a part of him. The lore of the vorpal blade, at least as I had written it, was that it could sever anything, even things that weren’t strictly real.

He tried to move out of the way, but he wasn’t fast enough, and he seemed surprised by that.

When my sword struck him, time stopped, and I put every last ounce of myself into the hit, not just my own natural strength, but everything I could muster from the bone of Mome Rath. I didn’t know whether that would be enough, or if it mattered that this was only a copy of the vorpal blade, but it was the play we had available.

The last thing I registered on his face was shock, in that moment of frozen time. Then the hit happened, and it was meteoric. Fel Seed was blasted apart into a cone of vaporized pieces a mile long, and if anyone had been standing behind him, I was sure they would have been killed. The sound was enough to deafen and the shockwave nearly knocked me to my feet, leaving my hands stinging from the vibration. I had felt the cut go deeper than the body, feel it carve into something metaphysical, or maybe several somethings. They gave a slight resistance before they too were sliced.

And then I dropped Bethel and clutched at my heart, which was hammering arrhythmically in my chest. My armor felt too heavy, and I sunk to my knees, trying to think, trying to breathe.

“What are you doing?” asked Amaryllis. “We need to get through the door.”

“He,” I said. “I was just —” It was already slipping out of my mind. There were, for some reason, piles of meat sitting on the bone platform around us. And there was something that I had been doing, something that had been vitally important. Whatever was in my brain that had felt so important moments ago now felt like it had been sliced apart into unrecognizable pieces.

“What?” asked Fenn, still holding her bow taut. She was looking around wildly and not seeing anything to shoot at. She had been shooting at something, but I wasn’t sure what.

“Antimeme,” I said, feeling weak. I had used the vorpal blade, or at least Bethel copying it, but I couldn’t recall on whom. Presumably it was the piles of flesh sitting on the ground, each of them torn to ribbons. The bone platform was marked with a cone of red leading away from me. Next to it, there was the vorpal blade, stuck into the bone and reflecting death, but otherwise inert.

“Fuck,” said Amaryllis. “Fuck, we don’t need this, we came here with a —” She stopped. Grak was still trying to get through the door, and Bethel had resumed her dictionary attack. “The antimeme is enormous.”

“How can you tell?” asked Fenn, slowly lowering her bow. We had been in danger, maybe we were still in danger, but whatever it was, we couldn’t sense it and had no knowledge of it.

“I don’t think it’s an antimeme,” I said, coughing. “Not a proper one.” I was feeling incredibly weak, but not dead. In game terms, it felt like I’d hit zero in every single attribute, but that hadn’t killed me. If I could have seen my HUD, my guess was that I was sitting there with a single hit point left. I pointed at the piles of meat. “I think that was it. That was the — the danger.”

“Bethel, side bar,” said Amaryllis. Bethel zipped over, and Amaryllis disappeared, reappearing slightly later.

I groaned and laid down on the ground. What I wanted was to sleep. I’d used the vorpal blade against something, someone, and it had taken a lot out of me. I had a brain fog to go with it, but that might have been from whatever had happened when the vorpal blade had made contact with whoever it was. I hoped that it had been the right thing to do, but it was hard to remember. We were in an exclusion zone, one where a lot of innocent people had died. It had been a bad place, before Amaryllis had detonated a bomb there. The bad thing, it was something I had created. I could remember the session, too, just not the details.

“Okay,” said Amaryllis. “From what I can find, and the lack of active combat, I think you killed the entity. The document that we’ve been working from is called the FSP, and the exclusion zone we’re in is referenced as the FSEZ, so I think it’s safe to refer to the entity,” she gestured at the piles of meat. “As FS. There’s no surviving name.”

“Okay?” I asked. “And I … hit him hard enough to … what?” I looked over at Raven’s body. “We need to heal her.”

“She has a mild concussion,” said Bethel, momentarily appearing in humanish form. It was the first time I’d seen her since I’d come back from the dead. She had changed again, and I couldn’t help but notice a resemblance to Valencia. She wasn’t cowed and groveling, but had a quiet, unassuming, and professional look. “I’ll take her.” She zipped over and Raven’s body vanished. A few seconds later, Raven popped back out.

“Something happened,” said Raven.

“I think I killed FS,” I said. “A bad guy.” I was still laid out on the ground.

“Is he going to be okay?” asked Fenn, looking at me. She had stored her bow.

“The FSP is heavily redacted,” said Amaryllis. “Whatever happened left a hole. There are pages that should have more information, and headings left over. Parts are missing, left blank. There are conversations I can’t remember all of.”

With the state of alert over, Grak had stopped what he was doing and gone over to us. “Something happened,” he said.

“Antimemetic effect,” said Amaryllis. “But … one that appears to have originated from us.” She looked at Bethel. “You have no idea?”

Bethel shook her head. “The vorpal blade,” she said, looking over to where it was sitting. “Valencia suggests that you should pick it up.”

“Me?” I asked. I was feeling so weak, barely able to move, but I summoned the necessary scrap of will to get to my feet. “Are we sure this won’t kill me?” Whatever else I’d forgotten, I remembered the vorpal blade. It was not lightly drawn.

“No,” said Bethel.

I didn’t understand what I was doing, or why, but I went over to the vorpal blade and picked it up.

The effect was slow, but I could feel it. My life force was being returned to me, and the fog gradually lifted from my brain. The vorpal blade didn’t suck at my being like it had before, instead feeling calm and natural in my hand. It had been someone’s blade before. He had used it without being drained, but the more I thought about it, the more the thought seemed slippery, like something falling through fingers that were desperately trying to grasp it.

“What was that?” I asked, turning to look at Bethel.

“Valencia believed that having defeated its master, you might become its bearer,” said Bethel.

I stared at her, hoping that Valencia would get a look of my face by proxy. “Fine,” I finally said. “If it’s stupid and it works, then it’s still fucking stupid.” Valencia had no doubt gotten the idea from the Elder Wand in Harry Potter.

“Continue the dictionary attack,” said Amaryllis.

“Wait,” I said. I was feeling better, but still not completely back to my old self, and I held the vorpal blade, letting it seep life back into me. I walked over to the door. “What’s the dumbest password this door can possibly take?”

“You already said ‘password’,” said Amaryllis. “That was the first thing you tried. Besides, I had plenty of stupid passwords in the dictionary attack, or dumb references.” She turned to face the door. “Swordfish, hunter2, mellon, friend, friend and enter, pedo mellon a minno, annon edhellen edro hi ammen, admin, Joshua, tiger, correct horse battery staple, Mickey Minnie Pluto Huey Louie Dewey Donald Goofy Sacramento,12345, —”

“I’ve got the same combination on my luggage!” shouted Fenn as she walked over.

“Are we in danger?” asked Amaryllis, looking at Fenn. “Luck sense?”

“I think we’re fine,” she replied, shrugging. “I wouldn’t be joking if I thought it wasn’t safe.”

“Yes you would,” I replied.

Amaryllis turned to me. “Fine,” she said. “Then let’s have it, what do you think it is?”

“Password wasn’t dumb enough,” I replied. I stared at the door, then looked over at Grak. “Did Pallida finish her part of things before she died?” I asked. “Did you … do magic?”

“Pallida did what she could,” said Grak. “She described it as priming.” He pointed at the door. “I did magic.”

“So then if I understand correctly, two of the three locks are gone,” I said. “And all that’s left is the last part, the password?”

“It is not three locks,” said Grak. “It is all one cohesive lock. But yes.”

“Alright,” I said. I looked at Amaryllis. “You’re right that ‘password’ was dumb, but that would have been really insecure. It should have been more secure, and something Arthur could have guessed. ‘Password1’.”

As soon as I said it, the door slowly swung open.

Amaryllis stared at the open door.

“Was that just a lucky guess?” asked Fenn.

“Luck had nothing to do with it,” said Amaryllis. “It’s the will of the Dungeon Master.” She seemed mildly disgruntled by it, upset that something so dumb had worked, or maybe that the other dumb stuff hadn’t.

“We should go through,” said Grak. “It may close on its own. I am not convinced that we could reopen it without Pallida.”

“She lives, sedated,” said Bethel. “My healing was enough.”

Pallida popped out and swayed slightly on her feet. Her face looked like it had been smashed against a wall and then hastily reconstructed before a few years of healing and repair, though that was just the effect of accelerated healing.

“I’m out,” she said. “Fuck this.”

“Understood,” I said.

Beyond the door was a corridor of hewn stone, the marks of its working clearly visible to the naked eye. There were torches on the walls at regular intervals, all of them burning, with no sign of who had lit them or why. There were no tracks of any kind, and aside from the torches, no sign that the corridor had been used. It went on for perhaps a hundred feet, then terminated at a secondary door, this one of much simpler make. If not for the fact that this corridor was extending into some other dimension, it might have looked perfectly ordinary.

There was something else odd about it though, the more I looked at it. I had all kinds of heightened senses, and while they seemed to be working across the boundary, they couldn’t extend past the walls of the corridor. There were no vibrations, there was no water, no chemical reactions, nothing that should have been there.

I went forward, trying to breathe normally. After all this time, we were here, on the final approach.

I crossed the threshold. I don’t know why, but I was expecting an achievement to pop up. I had gotten used to them, but the game layer seemed to have died when I did, and unlike me, it hadn’t been brought back. So long as the benefits were there, it didn’t actually matter, but it still felt like a loss somehow.

“Okay,” I said, looking back at the others. “Once we’re in, this will probably be the only way back out. This is the last chance to back out. I wouldn’t blame anyone.”

Amaryllis went in right away, and Bethel went after her, keeping her humanoid form for the moment. I wasn’t necessarily judging them based on how fast they crossed over, but maybe I did take some of their slowness for hesitance. I think in Raven’s case, the slow, measured walk might have been the knowledge that this was the end, or perhaps just the lingering effects of having magically recovered from a concussion. Grak definitely took the time to think it over, though it was impossible to tell what he was thinking under his helmet. Eventually he moved forward, passing through. I knew that he didn’t really want to come, that this was more of an obligation for him. He knew there was a good chance we would need him.

Pallida stayed back, and after a brief check to confirm it wouldn’t work in this new dimension, Amaryllis tossed her the teleportation key. There were half a dozen entads that would have allowed Pallida to leave the zone, but I was pretty sure that Amaryllis had chosen that one for symbolic reasons.

That left Fenn.

“Coming?” I asked. “I wouldn’t blame you, at all.”

“I’m thinking,” she said. “I already died once, you know?”

“I know,” I said.

“You’ll need me though, right?” she asked.

“Probably,” I said.

She nodded, but stayed where she was. I waited patiently. Whoever or whatever FS was, I didn’t think that it was coming back. Every second meant that more souls were ending up in the hells, more people were experiencing pain, there were things that I could fix, if I had the ability to. It was important not to rush her though, to allow her to make a decision on her own terms.

The door began to slowly swing closed. I stepped forward to hold it open, but immediately found that I couldn’t do anything to stop it, not through force and not with magic.

Fenn stood there for a moment, but at the last possible moment, she cursed and dashed forward, slipping between the doors just before the opening was too narrow for her.

Just after her, something followed, a white toad that I almost didn’t spot. I knelt down and picked it up, looking at the greenery on its back. There were mosses, tiny flowers, and some microgreens there, giving him a bit of a jaunty look.

“Huh,” I said. I turned to Amaryllis. “Is this the other locus?”

Amaryllis stared at the toad in my hand. “Likely,” she said. “He was supposed to be … bigger. The size of a house, at least.”

I looked him over for a bit, then set him on my shoulder. “I guess he’s coming with,” I said.

“But where’s his domain?” asked Fenn. “He shouldn’t be, uh.”

“Don’t think about it too hard,” I said. “He’s very small, and it might hurt him.” I didn’t know whether that was true or not, but it was good practice when around a locus.

I turned to face the other door, and the path to the Long Stairs. Somewhere in there, Uther lay ahead of us.